<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-11-02T22:13:14-07:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Laurence Moroney - The AI Guy.</title><subtitle>This is the blog and general web site of Laurence Moroney, author, lecturer, teacher and AI lead at Google with Musings on AI, Quantum and other future tech
</subtitle><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Beatles Now and Then - made possible by AI</title><link href="/2023/11/02/nowandthen.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Beatles Now and Then - made possible by AI" /><published>2023-11-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-11-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2023/11/02/nowandthen</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/11/02/nowandthen.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-final-beatles-song&quot;&gt;The Final Beatles Song&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now and then is a beautiful song, and it will be the last song from the Beatles. Made possible by AI extracting audio of old recording sessions to access content such as John Lennon’s voice, it’s an epic and beautiful recording.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s particularly poignant when you listen to the lyrics “Now and then, I miss you, I want you to be there for me”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on the track started in February 1995 as part of the Beatles anthology project, but it had to halt because of the technological challenges in extracting John’s voice from a tape recording from 20 years earlier. It looked like it wouldn’t be possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, enter Peter Jackson, of ‘Lord of the Rings’ fame, who figured out how to uncouple John’s vocal from background sound. It’s musical archaeology in action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s a beautiful and fitting song!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen to it here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/AW55J2zE3N4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="coding" /><summary type="html">The Final Beatles Song Now and then is a beautiful song, and it will be the last song from the Beatles. Made possible by AI extracting audio of old recording sessions to access content such as John Lennon’s voice, it’s an epic and beautiful recording. And it’s particularly poignant when you listen to the lyrics “Now and then, I miss you, I want you to be there for me” Work on the track started in February 1995 as part of the Beatles anthology project, but it had to halt because of the technological challenges in extracting John’s voice from a tape recording from 20 years earlier. It looked like it wouldn’t be possible. Then, enter Peter Jackson, of ‘Lord of the Rings’ fame, who figured out how to uncouple John’s vocal from background sound. It’s musical archaeology in action. And it’s a beautiful and fitting song! Listen to it here:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AI-phobia and the damage it can bring</title><link href="/2023/09/03/nofear.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI-phobia and the damage it can bring" /><published>2023-09-03T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-09-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2023/09/03/nofear</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/09/03/nofear.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;ai-where-the-only-thing-to-fear-is-fear-itself&quot;&gt;AI: Where the Only Thing to Fear is Fear Itself&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In today’s world, the majority of headlines I see around Artificial Intelligence (AI) skew negative. Fueled by decades of science fiction projecting AI to be a future antagonist, and present day attention-grabbing headlines, many view AI as the ominous cloud on the horizon of human evolution. As something that will overtake us, and having done so, will then wipe us out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sentiment brings to mind the profound words of Franklin D. Roosevelt: “The only thing we have to fear is fear itself.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-birth-of-fear&quot;&gt;The Birth of Fear&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the work done in AI is a major and encouraging pinnacle of human ingenuity, representing our innate desire to break barriers and redefine the possible. With it, we have been able to break through computational barriers, building applications the likes of which were previously thought impossible. And we’re only getting started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, like any revolutionary advancement, the right hand of power can bring the left hand of darkness, in this case, that of uncertainty and apprehension. But is this fear rooted in the technology itself or our misunderstanding of it? I argue the latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Movies, novels, and popular culture have, for decades, painted AI as the unstoppable force that will eventually surpass human intelligence, casting a shadow over our dominion. These depictions are, of course, tailored for entertainment, emphasizing conflict and drama over factual representation. Yet, the impact of these narratives on public perception is undeniable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But one thing stands clear. Intelligence alone is not enough, be it artificial or biological. A living, conscious, sentient entity, capable of making value judgements – for good or evil – is a lot more than just an intelligence. Yet the column inches of fear focus entirely on the ‘I’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take Bostrom’s famous &lt;a href=&quot;https://cepr.org/voxeu/columns/ai-and-paperclip-problem#:~:text=Bostrom&apos;s%20thought%20experiment%20goes%20like,to%20achieve%20its%20goal%20better.&quot;&gt;paper clip thought experiment&lt;/a&gt; In this, an AI is tasked with making paperclips, and, given that it can learn how to make better paperclips, it will eventually realize that all of humanity’s resources are effectively wasted if they’re not being used to make paperclips, and it will run away, and destroy humanity in an apocalypse of paperclips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/clip-fun.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Clippy making a joke&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fallacy here, of course, is that in the discussion of the &lt;em&gt;possible&lt;/em&gt;, we’re ignoring the &lt;em&gt;probable&lt;/em&gt;, and the largest factor determining probability of this outcome would be giving this paper clip generator access to the resources that would allow it to destroy humanity. Maybe it could evolve a level of intelligence that would allow it to theorize a methodology to ‘break out’ of its thought experiment confines, but does that give it the ability to do so? And, when creating any kind of artificial intelligence, the model, while very sophisticated is usually very limited. It has a one-tracked mind, if you will, and this experiment pre-supposes that it can evolve beyond that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The narrative is overtaken by fear of the possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ai-as-a-mirror&quot;&gt;AI as a Mirror&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s essential to understand that AI, at its core, is neutral. It’s a tool, an extension of our collective knowledge. AI doesn’t have emotions, ambitions, or ulterior motives. It operates on data, algorithms, and the instructions we feed it. In many ways, AI is a mirror, reflecting both the biases of its creators and the vast potential of its applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps our fear of AI comes from the fact that we’re looking in that mirror and seeing what is terrifying in ourselves? Perhaps this is a great wakeup call for us as a species to recognize that which in ourselves is dangerous, and do something about it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I also think of historic mistakes made by our species. Today, AI is that great, feared, unknown. But that wasn’t always the case, was it? Modern day racism is rooted in the same ‘othering’ of outsiders. We made many mistakes, treating (or more accurately &lt;em&gt;mis&lt;/em&gt;treating) others outside our known civilizations as savages, less than human, something to be feared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we all continue to pay the price for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe this is an opportunity not to repeat that mistake. What if, some years from now, AI becomes AL – Artificial Life. Wouldn’t it be nice to be ready to be in a position where we can understand and treat with each other with mutual respect?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-real-challenge&quot;&gt;The Real Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to today, the actual challenge lies not in the technology but in its application. A well-programmed application that uses AI can help doctors diagnose diseases, assist students in learning, or predict weather patterns with astonishing accuracy. Conversely, an poorly built one can reinforce societal prejudices, make unfair decisions, or invade privacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This dichotomy means that our real focus should be on ensuring that our work should be to develop and grow AI and ML responsibly. One underlooked aspect of respobnsible development is in mitigating fear. When allowed to dominate the narrative, fear stunts critical thinking. It can halt progress and can keep us from harnessing the transformative power of AI for the greater good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-path-forward&quot;&gt;The Path Forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of getting wrapped up in a cycle of fear and misinformation, we need to channel our collective energies towards education, open dialogue, and understanding. Collaborative efforts between tech developers, ethicists, policymakers, and the public can ensure that AI’s development remains aligned with humanity’s best interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Embracing the future means embracing AI, but with open eyes, clear minds, and fearless hearts. We stand at the cusp of a technological renaissance, and our approach will determine the legacy of this era. As we move forward, let’s remember that the most significant achievements in history were born from hope and understanding, not from fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note: I used LLMs to help me create this post. They helped me hone my thoughts and sharpen my argument. They did not replace me as a writer, nor did they drive my opinion)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="coding" /><summary type="html">AI: Where the Only Thing to Fear is Fear Itself In today’s world, the majority of headlines I see around Artificial Intelligence (AI) skew negative. Fueled by decades of science fiction projecting AI to be a future antagonist, and present day attention-grabbing headlines, many view AI as the ominous cloud on the horizon of human evolution. As something that will overtake us, and having done so, will then wipe us out. This sentiment brings to mind the profound words of Franklin D. Roosevelt: “The only thing we have to fear is fear itself.” The Birth of Fear Much of the work done in AI is a major and encouraging pinnacle of human ingenuity, representing our innate desire to break barriers and redefine the possible. With it, we have been able to break through computational barriers, building applications the likes of which were previously thought impossible. And we’re only getting started. Yet, like any revolutionary advancement, the right hand of power can bring the left hand of darkness, in this case, that of uncertainty and apprehension. But is this fear rooted in the technology itself or our misunderstanding of it? I argue the latter. Movies, novels, and popular culture have, for decades, painted AI as the unstoppable force that will eventually surpass human intelligence, casting a shadow over our dominion. These depictions are, of course, tailored for entertainment, emphasizing conflict and drama over factual representation. Yet, the impact of these narratives on public perception is undeniable. But one thing stands clear. Intelligence alone is not enough, be it artificial or biological. A living, conscious, sentient entity, capable of making value judgements – for good or evil – is a lot more than just an intelligence. Yet the column inches of fear focus entirely on the ‘I’ Take Bostrom’s famous paper clip thought experiment In this, an AI is tasked with making paperclips, and, given that it can learn how to make better paperclips, it will eventually realize that all of humanity’s resources are effectively wasted if they’re not being used to make paperclips, and it will run away, and destroy humanity in an apocalypse of paperclips. The fallacy here, of course, is that in the discussion of the possible, we’re ignoring the probable, and the largest factor determining probability of this outcome would be giving this paper clip generator access to the resources that would allow it to destroy humanity. Maybe it could evolve a level of intelligence that would allow it to theorize a methodology to ‘break out’ of its thought experiment confines, but does that give it the ability to do so? And, when creating any kind of artificial intelligence, the model, while very sophisticated is usually very limited. It has a one-tracked mind, if you will, and this experiment pre-supposes that it can evolve beyond that. The narrative is overtaken by fear of the possible. AI as a Mirror It’s essential to understand that AI, at its core, is neutral. It’s a tool, an extension of our collective knowledge. AI doesn’t have emotions, ambitions, or ulterior motives. It operates on data, algorithms, and the instructions we feed it. In many ways, AI is a mirror, reflecting both the biases of its creators and the vast potential of its applications. Perhaps our fear of AI comes from the fact that we’re looking in that mirror and seeing what is terrifying in ourselves? Perhaps this is a great wakeup call for us as a species to recognize that which in ourselves is dangerous, and do something about it? Finally, I also think of historic mistakes made by our species. Today, AI is that great, feared, unknown. But that wasn’t always the case, was it? Modern day racism is rooted in the same ‘othering’ of outsiders. We made many mistakes, treating (or more accurately mistreating) others outside our known civilizations as savages, less than human, something to be feared. And we all continue to pay the price for that. Maybe this is an opportunity not to repeat that mistake. What if, some years from now, AI becomes AL – Artificial Life. Wouldn’t it be nice to be ready to be in a position where we can understand and treat with each other with mutual respect? The Real Challenge Back to today, the actual challenge lies not in the technology but in its application. A well-programmed application that uses AI can help doctors diagnose diseases, assist students in learning, or predict weather patterns with astonishing accuracy. Conversely, an poorly built one can reinforce societal prejudices, make unfair decisions, or invade privacy. This dichotomy means that our real focus should be on ensuring that our work should be to develop and grow AI and ML responsibly. One underlooked aspect of respobnsible development is in mitigating fear. When allowed to dominate the narrative, fear stunts critical thinking. It can halt progress and can keep us from harnessing the transformative power of AI for the greater good. The Path Forward Instead of getting wrapped up in a cycle of fear and misinformation, we need to channel our collective energies towards education, open dialogue, and understanding. Collaborative efforts between tech developers, ethicists, policymakers, and the public can ensure that AI’s development remains aligned with humanity’s best interests. Embracing the future means embracing AI, but with open eyes, clear minds, and fearless hearts. We stand at the cusp of a technological renaissance, and our approach will determine the legacy of this era. As we move forward, let’s remember that the most significant achievements in history were born from hope and understanding, not from fear. (Note: I used LLMs to help me create this post. They helped me hone my thoughts and sharpen my argument. They did not replace me as a writer, nor did they drive my opinion)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/roadway.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/roadway.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">AI-Generated 2.5D</title><link href="/2023/05/22/kenburns.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI-Generated 2.5D" /><published>2023-05-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-05-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2023/05/22/kenburns</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/05/22/kenburns.html">&lt;p&gt;I really love the combination of the ‘Ken Burns’ effect to bring images to life, with a way to cut the image up into layers, and then move each layer separately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s usually a lot of work in photoshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now, with the amazing work from &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1909.05483&quot;&gt;Simon Niklaus et al&lt;/a&gt;, it seems that ML models can perform this task by using segmentation to figure out foreground from background and inpainting to fill in the missing pixels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s ingenious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played with the image from above, and got this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hC6Ie4XTa-s&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still a bit of work to be done, and I’m hoping I can tweak for higher resolution in the video, but the effect is definitely stunning…considering it’s entirely automated!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="coding" /><summary type="html">I really love the combination of the ‘Ken Burns’ effect to bring images to life, with a way to cut the image up into layers, and then move each layer separately. It’s usually a lot of work in photoshop. But now, with the amazing work from Simon Niklaus et al, it seems that ML models can perform this task by using segmentation to figure out foreground from background and inpainting to fill in the missing pixels. It’s ingenious. I played with the image from above, and got this: Still a bit of work to be done, and I’m hoping I can tweak for higher resolution in the video, but the effect is definitely stunning…considering it’s entirely automated!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/scene.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/scene.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Artificial Intelligence - Where to start</title><link href="/ai%20tech%20google/2023/05/21/getstarted.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Artificial Intelligence - Where to start" /><published>2023-05-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-05-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/ai%20tech%20google/2023/05/21/getstarted</id><content type="html" xml:base="/ai%20tech%20google/2023/05/21/getstarted.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m often asked about how to get started in the field of Artificial Intelligence. First, it’s important to understand what you’re asking. What &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; AI? Why should you be interested?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At my talk for Google IO 2023, I made a quick video to give you the lay of the land. What it is, why you should care, and what it’s all about to get data, train models, deploy and manage them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal is to give you a good understanding in a short timeframe – so it’s just a few minutes to hopefully at least give you enough info to start asking all the right questions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3K1414RwNDU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="AI Tech Google" /><category term="life" /><category term="tech" /><summary type="html">I’m often asked about how to get started in the field of Artificial Intelligence. First, it’s important to understand what you’re asking. What is AI? Why should you be interested? At my talk for Google IO 2023, I made a quick video to give you the lay of the land. What it is, why you should care, and what it’s all about to get data, train models, deploy and manage them. The goal is to give you a good understanding in a short timeframe – so it’s just a few minutes to hopefully at least give you enough info to start asking all the right questions!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/ai-future.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/ai-future.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Space Cadets - An AI-illustrated Novel. Part Three.</title><link href="/2022/06/26/Space_Cadets_Part_Three.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Space Cadets - An AI-illustrated Novel. Part Three." /><published>2022-06-26T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2022/06/26/Space_Cadets_Part_Three</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2022/06/26/Space_Cadets_Part_Three.html">&lt;p&gt;Continuing my experiment to illustrate a novel using AI text-to-image generation techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, I’m going to use MidJourney. Previous chapters used DALL-E. Let me know what you think twitter.com/lmoroney&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;chapter-3&quot;&gt;CHAPTER 3&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;launch&quot;&gt;Launch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We should always reach for the sky.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From the very beginning of history, our ancestors were looking up and wondering what was beyond their reach. The stars were calling them. They weaved stories of gods and angels, but behind them all was the intense desire to be out there. A desire born of an instinct for survival.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of a girl looking at the stars from the african savannah&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It’s something we’ve forgotten as we’ve become civilized. We’ve become comfortable in our homes, our cities and our countries. We’ve defeated nature and haven’t had the same worries that they had. But we lost something in that complacency, I fear. And now, as our world gets overcrowded, as our environment collapses under us, we need to rediscover it. We need to look up, and not worry about tripping as we race towards a new destiny. We will be those gods and angels if we want to. And you can be one of them, if you just keep trying, and never give up…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of Aisha looking out the windows of the hotel towards the spaceport&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;THE SPACE ELEVATOR. Its relatively simple name belied the sheer scale of it. Craning her neck, Aisha looked up as it disappeared impossibly into the deep blue sky. The ‘shuttle’ was a box-like structure that could easily pass for another building, but for the rocket boosters placed on its corners. These boosters would provide the initial ‘launch’ to get the craft moving out of its gravitational inertia. After that, the rotation of the Earth would take over and drive the shuttle up the cable into orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of a space elevator viewed from orbit&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was so glad for last night’s dinner with Mother. Beforehand, it had felt like there was a tension building between them. Mother’s basking in her status had gotten under Aisha’s skin, and she had been worried that she might blow up at her before leaving. She was worried that she might end up regretting it, but there was only so long she could bite her tongue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of a Aishas mother watching the shuttle in the distance&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She almost thanked the reporter for his rude question. It had brought them closer together. She felt a pang of pride again at Mother’s words that she had done exactly what Father would have done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the same reporter had wrestled his way to the front of the audience, and was barking out questions to the cadets as they boarded the shuttle. She was happy she knew where he was, so she could actively ignore him as she passed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She gave Mother one final hug, and turned and walked along the long ramp up to the shuttle. With every step away from her, Aisha felt more and more alone. As the entrance loomed toward her, she felt the urge to turn and run back to Mother’s welcoming arms. Mother would hold her and protect her, and to heck with anyone who would criticize her for not going through with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of the spaceport on a hawaiian island&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But she didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She continued step-by-step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the top of the ramp, she turned for one more look back at the Earth. She caught Mother’s eye as she waved frantically, blowing kisses and smiling. “That’s my little girl!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She raised her hand to wave, hearing cameras popping, and returned the smile before turning to enter the shuttle. Her feet suddenly felt heavy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was really going through with this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was really leaving home and going into &lt;em&gt;space&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each step seemed to be a chore, doubt and indecision weighing on her more heavily than gravity ever could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step-by-step she continued forward. The entrance lobby curved away from the door, and in a few moments, the daylight was lost. Words she had learned from history came back to her. Alea iacta est. She smiled, thinking that her Classics teacher would be proud of her. The die is cast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of the entrance lobby of a space elevator shuttle, windows overlooking to ocean beyond&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interior of the shuttle was clearly designed to impress and soothe its occupants. Instead of the functional ships of yesteryear, it was all polished chrome and intricately-designed surfaces. In the days of rocket travel to the stars, every ounce of payload had to be carefully measured, with no room for luxury, as propelling something into orbit required enormous amounts of energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Space Elevator changed all that, so designers of spacecraft were free to allow their occupants to be comfortable with traveling into space. This was also an important factor as many more people would leave the surface of the Earth – and a good, comfortable experience made it more tolerable, and thus less training was necessary. Indeed, Aisha had little more training than a couple of video tutorials explaining how to deal with weightlessness, and what to eat or not to eat prior to boarding. It was also good advice to use the bathroom before getting on the ship, for while facilities were available, using them in weightless conditions wasn’t optimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She climbed stairs to the observation deck where she would spend most of the journey. The deck was a wide circle with multi story windows, and acceleration couches arranged facing outwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-7.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of the space elevator observation deck&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As we rise up the cable, the shuttle will spin slowly,” she had remembered the tutorial video telling her. “So pick any seat, and you’ll still be able to see everything.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-9.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of Aisha in an acceleration sofa&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deck was terraced, so that seats near the back would still have a great view, and their occupants may not have the feeling of vertigo that those closer to the front would encounter. She picked one in the back row, next to an Asian girl who looked about Aisha’s age. The girl was intensely reading a book on her tablet, and didn’t look up as Aisha sat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-8.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of Aisha in an acceleration sofa&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She suddenly spoke. “Aisha Parks, celebrity.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha looked at her. “I’m not sure about that.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The girl looked up, and her intense eyes searched Aisha’s. “Good to know,” she said finally, reaching a hand out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Soo-Kyung Kim,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-10.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of Aisha meeting Soo-Kyung&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I don’t need to tell you my name, I guess.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soo-Kyung smiled. Her plain face lit up when she smiled. She was beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So where are you from?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soo-Kyung smiled again. “You haven’t heard of me? Good. I guess I am not a celebrity, either.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an odd answer, and from Soo-Kyung’s reaction, it was clear that Aisha’s confusion was written on her face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I think we are going to be good friends,” said Soo-Kyung. “I like how you are straightforward. I am too, but that intimidates some people.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-11.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of Aisha and Soo-Kyung chatting&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So where are you from?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am from a small village called Sijungho,” continued Soo Kyung. “There’s not much to see there.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Sounds Korean,” said Aisha. “You from South Korea?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“North Korea,” corrected Soo-Kyung. “I’ve never even been to South Korea.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha felt her insides go cold. Against her will, she shuddered a little, and felt a sob begin to escape from her throat. Her father had died as a result of radiation sickness incurred in the second Korean War. And there was a North Korean girl here with her. Going into space with her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She knew there was incredulity in her voice, but she couldn’t mask it. “Are you going to the Academy too?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yes,” said Soo-Kyung. “And don’t worry, I’m as surprised as you are.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s what you meant by celebrity?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It seems the media made as big a deal about me being the first North Korean as it did about you being the first African-American to go through open enrollment. It’s all a sham though, isn’t it?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m beginning to gather that.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I mean, when the Academy was first built, it was apparent that it was for the Elites, most of whom are from Western society, with a few Russians and Chinese thrown in to get funding. Nobody really knows who the students were, but it was typically those who would be in private elite schools on the surface, so being in space made little difference.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha thought about what Soo-Kyung was saying, and realized that she was right. Amazing that she had never thought of this herself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Korean girl continued. “Now that they are all in place and established, it’s time to open it up to the rest of the world, so we can get their proverbial ‘sloppy seconds’, I guess.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s an academy,” said Aisha. “And we’re cadets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The cannon fodder, while they are the officers ordering us around.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So why are you going through with it? Why am &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; going through with it?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soo-Kyung shrugged. “Because it’s better than &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going through with it. Besides, there might be something great waiting for normal people like us.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“My father died in Korea,” said Aisha, surprising even herself at the change in subject. “But he always told my mother to tell me that I had a destiny. That the emerging age of space flight was one in which we must be free to explore the universe. He fought so that that freedom would still exist, so that I could do this. I can’t turn back.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Most of my family died in the same war,” said Soo-Kyung. “But nothing ever really changed, did it?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha realized that she must have sounded bitter, and the bitterness was reflected in Soo-Kyung’s answer. 
“I’m sorry,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No need,” said Soo-Kyung. “I’m glad that you are open and honest with me. Most people, particularly outside of my country, are not. They learn about where I’m from and think I need special treatment. I don’t. I’ve learned to stand on my own.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I wish I had your strength.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You don’t,” said Soo-Kyung, suddenly serious. “&lt;em&gt;That&lt;/em&gt; kind of strength comes from trying to make a life in a country destroyed by nuclear war. You never want it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-12.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of Soo-Kyung as a little girl in North Korea as nukes fall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s why we’re going into space, isn’t it? To make sure that wars like those will never put our species’ survival at risk.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That would be nice,” said Soo-Kyung. “But if anything I think it will cause more wars and hardship before things get better.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Why?” 
“Because the only thing that stopped the entire world from burning during the war over my country was that it was the only world we have. If we discover more planets, livable ones, that will no longer be the case. And I want to be as far away from this world as possible before the next bombs fall.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before Aisha could answer, the soft tone of the launch warning sounded. The rocket boost would be gentler than a typical aircraft take off, but safety protocols required that they be buckled into their crash seats in case anything went wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She rolled her eyes and smiled, and strapped herself in. When everything was snug, she turned to look at Soo-Kyung. Their eyes met again, and Soo-Kyung bowed slightly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The engines kicked in, and their seats lurched a little. From all around came the muffled sounds of the rockets roaring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the windows, Aisha could see the ground begin to slowly fall away. Within a few seconds the flotilla was no longer visible, and as they began to rise, she could see the entire outline of the nearby Kiritimati, where only yesterday they had landed. It felt like an eternity ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She wondered how Mother felt, watching her shuttle rise slowly to the sky. As suddenly as they had begun, the rockets cut out, and there was another slight lurch as the inertia of the ship was stopped. She remembered the video training – this was the scariest part of the trip, where the shuttle, under normal gravity, could fall back to Earth and kill everyone aboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it didn’t, and the force on the Space Elevator started pushing them skyward, with ever-increasing speed. The horizon began to spin also, and as they rose up, she watched the island recede. Before long they were high enough to see that the horizon was curved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was it. This was for real. She was headed into space!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-13.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of Aisha&apos;s mother watching the shuttle lift into space&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="books" /><category term="personal" /><summary type="html">Continuing my experiment to illustrate a novel using AI text-to-image generation techniques. In this article, I’m going to use MidJourney. Previous chapters used DALL-E. Let me know what you think twitter.com/lmoroney CHAPTER 3 Launch We should always reach for the sky. From the very beginning of history, our ancestors were looking up and wondering what was beyond their reach. The stars were calling them. They weaved stories of gods and angels, but behind them all was the intense desire to be out there. A desire born of an instinct for survival. It’s something we’ve forgotten as we’ve become civilized. We’ve become comfortable in our homes, our cities and our countries. We’ve defeated nature and haven’t had the same worries that they had. But we lost something in that complacency, I fear. And now, as our world gets overcrowded, as our environment collapses under us, we need to rediscover it. We need to look up, and not worry about tripping as we race towards a new destiny. We will be those gods and angels if we want to. And you can be one of them, if you just keep trying, and never give up… THE SPACE ELEVATOR. Its relatively simple name belied the sheer scale of it. Craning her neck, Aisha looked up as it disappeared impossibly into the deep blue sky. The ‘shuttle’ was a box-like structure that could easily pass for another building, but for the rocket boosters placed on its corners. These boosters would provide the initial ‘launch’ to get the craft moving out of its gravitational inertia. After that, the rotation of the Earth would take over and drive the shuttle up the cable into orbit. She was so glad for last night’s dinner with Mother. Beforehand, it had felt like there was a tension building between them. Mother’s basking in her status had gotten under Aisha’s skin, and she had been worried that she might blow up at her before leaving. She was worried that she might end up regretting it, but there was only so long she could bite her tongue. She almost thanked the reporter for his rude question. It had brought them closer together. She felt a pang of pride again at Mother’s words that she had done exactly what Father would have done. Of course, the same reporter had wrestled his way to the front of the audience, and was barking out questions to the cadets as they boarded the shuttle. She was happy she knew where he was, so she could actively ignore him as she passed. She gave Mother one final hug, and turned and walked along the long ramp up to the shuttle. With every step away from her, Aisha felt more and more alone. As the entrance loomed toward her, she felt the urge to turn and run back to Mother’s welcoming arms. Mother would hold her and protect her, and to heck with anyone who would criticize her for not going through with it. But she didn’t. She continued step-by-step. At the top of the ramp, she turned for one more look back at the Earth. She caught Mother’s eye as she waved frantically, blowing kisses and smiling. “That’s my little girl!” She raised her hand to wave, hearing cameras popping, and returned the smile before turning to enter the shuttle. Her feet suddenly felt heavy. She was really going through with this. She was really leaving home and going into space. Each step seemed to be a chore, doubt and indecision weighing on her more heavily than gravity ever could. Step-by-step she continued forward. The entrance lobby curved away from the door, and in a few moments, the daylight was lost. Words she had learned from history came back to her. Alea iacta est. She smiled, thinking that her Classics teacher would be proud of her. The die is cast. The interior of the shuttle was clearly designed to impress and soothe its occupants. Instead of the functional ships of yesteryear, it was all polished chrome and intricately-designed surfaces. In the days of rocket travel to the stars, every ounce of payload had to be carefully measured, with no room for luxury, as propelling something into orbit required enormous amounts of energy. The Space Elevator changed all that, so designers of spacecraft were free to allow their occupants to be comfortable with traveling into space. This was also an important factor as many more people would leave the surface of the Earth – and a good, comfortable experience made it more tolerable, and thus less training was necessary. Indeed, Aisha had little more training than a couple of video tutorials explaining how to deal with weightlessness, and what to eat or not to eat prior to boarding. It was also good advice to use the bathroom before getting on the ship, for while facilities were available, using them in weightless conditions wasn’t optimal. She climbed stairs to the observation deck where she would spend most of the journey. The deck was a wide circle with multi story windows, and acceleration couches arranged facing outwards. “As we rise up the cable, the shuttle will spin slowly,” she had remembered the tutorial video telling her. “So pick any seat, and you’ll still be able to see everything.” The deck was terraced, so that seats near the back would still have a great view, and their occupants may not have the feeling of vertigo that those closer to the front would encounter. She picked one in the back row, next to an Asian girl who looked about Aisha’s age. The girl was intensely reading a book on her tablet, and didn’t look up as Aisha sat. She suddenly spoke. “Aisha Parks, celebrity.” Aisha looked at her. “I’m not sure about that.” The girl looked up, and her intense eyes searched Aisha’s. “Good to know,” she said finally, reaching a hand out. “Soo-Kyung Kim,” she said. “I don’t need to tell you my name, I guess.” Soo-Kyung smiled. Her plain face lit up when she smiled. She was beautiful. “So where are you from?” Soo-Kyung smiled again. “You haven’t heard of me? Good. I guess I am not a celebrity, either.” Such an odd answer, and from Soo-Kyung’s reaction, it was clear that Aisha’s confusion was written on her face. “I think we are going to be good friends,” said Soo-Kyung. “I like how you are straightforward. I am too, but that intimidates some people.” “So where are you from?” “I am from a small village called Sijungho,” continued Soo Kyung. “There’s not much to see there.” “Sounds Korean,” said Aisha. “You from South Korea?” “North Korea,” corrected Soo-Kyung. “I’ve never even been to South Korea.” Aisha felt her insides go cold. Against her will, she shuddered a little, and felt a sob begin to escape from her throat. Her father had died as a result of radiation sickness incurred in the second Korean War. And there was a North Korean girl here with her. Going into space with her. She knew there was incredulity in her voice, but she couldn’t mask it. “Are you going to the Academy too?” “Yes,” said Soo-Kyung. “And don’t worry, I’m as surprised as you are.” “That’s what you meant by celebrity?” “It seems the media made as big a deal about me being the first North Korean as it did about you being the first African-American to go through open enrollment. It’s all a sham though, isn’t it?” “I’m beginning to gather that.” “I mean, when the Academy was first built, it was apparent that it was for the Elites, most of whom are from Western society, with a few Russians and Chinese thrown in to get funding. Nobody really knows who the students were, but it was typically those who would be in private elite schools on the surface, so being in space made little difference.” Aisha thought about what Soo-Kyung was saying, and realized that she was right. Amazing that she had never thought of this herself. The Korean girl continued. “Now that they are all in place and established, it’s time to open it up to the rest of the world, so we can get their proverbial ‘sloppy seconds’, I guess.” “It’s an academy,” said Aisha. “And we’re cadets.” “The cannon fodder, while they are the officers ordering us around.” “So why are you going through with it? Why am I going through with it?” Soo-Kyung shrugged. “Because it’s better than not going through with it. Besides, there might be something great waiting for normal people like us.” “My father died in Korea,” said Aisha, surprising even herself at the change in subject. “But he always told my mother to tell me that I had a destiny. That the emerging age of space flight was one in which we must be free to explore the universe. He fought so that that freedom would still exist, so that I could do this. I can’t turn back.” “Most of my family died in the same war,” said Soo-Kyung. “But nothing ever really changed, did it?” Aisha realized that she must have sounded bitter, and the bitterness was reflected in Soo-Kyung’s answer. “I’m sorry,” she said. “No need,” said Soo-Kyung. “I’m glad that you are open and honest with me. Most people, particularly outside of my country, are not. They learn about where I’m from and think I need special treatment. I don’t. I’ve learned to stand on my own.” “I wish I had your strength.” “You don’t,” said Soo-Kyung, suddenly serious. “That kind of strength comes from trying to make a life in a country destroyed by nuclear war. You never want it.” “That’s why we’re going into space, isn’t it? To make sure that wars like those will never put our species’ survival at risk.” “That would be nice,” said Soo-Kyung. “But if anything I think it will cause more wars and hardship before things get better.” “Why?” “Because the only thing that stopped the entire world from burning during the war over my country was that it was the only world we have. If we discover more planets, livable ones, that will no longer be the case. And I want to be as far away from this world as possible before the next bombs fall.” Before Aisha could answer, the soft tone of the launch warning sounded. The rocket boost would be gentler than a typical aircraft take off, but safety protocols required that they be buckled into their crash seats in case anything went wrong. She rolled her eyes and smiled, and strapped herself in. When everything was snug, she turned to look at Soo-Kyung. Their eyes met again, and Soo-Kyung bowed slightly. The engines kicked in, and their seats lurched a little. From all around came the muffled sounds of the rockets roaring. Through the windows, Aisha could see the ground begin to slowly fall away. Within a few seconds the flotilla was no longer visible, and as they began to rise, she could see the entire outline of the nearby Kiritimati, where only yesterday they had landed. It felt like an eternity ago. She wondered how Mother felt, watching her shuttle rise slowly to the sky. As suddenly as they had begun, the rockets cut out, and there was another slight lurch as the inertia of the ship was stopped. She remembered the video training – this was the scariest part of the trip, where the shuttle, under normal gravity, could fall back to Earth and kill everyone aboard. But it didn’t, and the force on the Space Elevator started pushing them skyward, with ever-increasing speed. The horizon began to spin also, and as they rose up, she watched the island recede. Before long they were high enough to see that the horizon was curved. This was it. This was for real. She was headed into space!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Space Cadets - An AI-illustrated Novel. Chapter Two.</title><link href="/2022/06/24/Space_Cadets_Part_Two.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Space Cadets - An AI-illustrated Novel. Chapter Two." /><published>2022-06-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2022/06/24/Space_Cadets_Part_Two</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2022/06/24/Space_Cadets_Part_Two.html">&lt;p&gt;Continuing the experimental re-publishing of my novel “Space Cadets,” illustrated using Text-to-Image AI models. For this chapter, I’m still using DALL-E. For future chapters, I’ll explore other models too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Space Cadets is the story of the first African American girl accepted into a prestigious space academy, and the story of discrimination, racism, and old-fashioned bullying she faces, and how she overcomes it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, here’s Chapter 2. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-2&quot;&gt;CHAPTER 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;press&quot;&gt;Press&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There are so many things I’ve learned since I broke away from the cocoon that we call our country. It’s a great place, a safe place, but perhaps it’s because of that safety that we look inward. 
And in the case of too many people, we look backward.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Future dreams will never last if we always focus on the past. On the terrible things that were done to our ancestors. If we are to look forward, we should remember them, but not dwell on them&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-2-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;DALL-E Generated image of Aisha reading the letter from her father&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TERMINUS, THE MASSIVE flotilla that surrounded the Space Elevator, was too mobile to be called a city in its purest sense. But for all intents and purposes, it was one. Their hotel was the finest Aisha had ever slept in, with big, comfortable beds and a wonderful breakfast. The slight rocking of their room caused by the waves only further lulled her to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-2-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;DALL-E Generated image of The floating city called Terminus&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it was in fine cheer that she greeted the press conference, the crankiness of travel a distant memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before long, she was biting her lip, trying not to snap at the monotony and repetition of the questions that were largely irrelevant to her future as a space cadet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What’s it like being the first African-American to qualify through open enrollment?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s great, but I can’t really answer what it’s like until I go up there. But I’m looking forward to it, and hoping I can be an effective student.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She watched as the reporters took notes, unhappy with such a straightforward statement. There was no story there. “How do you think you are going to cope with the pressure?” “Until I know what the pressure is, it’s hard to answer that question. I’m sure I will handle it the same way as any other student.” One of the reporters, a white man whose hair was whiter than his skin, interrupted. “But you aren’t like the other students, are you?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Why would you say that?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Because you are the first African-American student to qualify through open enrollment.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha could feel her anger rising. She tried to keep her calm as she answered evenly, “How does that make me different from the other students?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Please,” said the man. “We all see how &lt;em&gt;politically correct&lt;/em&gt; this situation is. There has been so much pressure on the board of governors to open enroll from amongst the general population so that we can meet &lt;em&gt;political&lt;/em&gt; needs of diversity. So, of course, the first thing we need to do is to have some African-Americans amongst the student body. And while we’re at it, why don’t we get a girl, so we kill two proverbial birds with one proverbial stone. Let’s also find one who lost a father in the second Korean War! Isn’t it obvious to you that you have been picked for all of these reasons and that you are going into orbit to be in a place where you are likely to be out of your depth, but will probably be handled by kid gloves, so as to satisfy those who are bearing political pressures?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-2-7.png&quot; alt=&quot;DALL-E Generated image of Aisha at the press conference&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha felt her jaw drop. Even Mother was stunned into silence. The worst part, though, was that in a room full of people, many of whom were African-American, nobody leapt to her defense. Instead the press turned to her, recorders pointed in her direction, awaiting her answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a bunch of sharks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She could feel herself begin to sweat as all eyes turned her way. Time slowed to a crawl as they awaited an answer. With every passing tick, and nothing to say in response, she began to wonder if the man was right. If she really was out of her depth. If she really didn’t belong here, and she was just fooling herself. Maybe she wasn’t as smart or as capable as she thought she was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What would Father do in these circumstances? She had always learned of how great and how wise he was. Mother tried to pass down his teachings, but they were often through her filters, and Aisha was left to parse what the man had really been like, and what he would really do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She remembered one phrase: Never start the fight, but always finish it. The path was clear. There was a simple way to finish this fight. Composing herself as best she could, she smiled, and stood. It still felt like everything was moving in slow motion. Instead of exiting through the back, she took the steps down from the stage towards the waiting press, walking towards them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some began to get upset at her not answering the question. That was the news they had come for, and they smelled blood in the water. But she maintained her composure, looking straight ahead and walking slowly, step-by-step, as they parted before her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her path took her straight towards the reporter that had asked the question. His skin was turning redder now. Was it anger? Embarrassment? It didn’t matter. She met his gaze, held it for a moment. She watched him prepare for whatever she was going to say, saw his eyes dilate, his pallor flush.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She gave him a little half-smile, and left the room to ever increasing volume and shouting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She finished the fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her insides burning, she wanted to get as far away from the press room as possible. She had maintained a calm composure, but the man’s words bounced around her head, making her angrier with each passing step. 
But what if he was right? What if she really was chosen for the reasons he had said? She had to admit to herself that she had taken pride at being the first of her race to be chosen. And with there being so many qualified boys, that the first was a girl. Maybe she shouldn’t have felt so proud. Maybe she shouldn’t have let mother’s braggadocios attitude wear off on her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth of the matter was that she &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; selected. That she &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; going to be a space cadet. In a few hours, she would be in orbit: Working with the best and brightest people in the world, learning how to fly spaceships, and being part of the research team that was building ships that would go &lt;em&gt;to the stars.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This small-mindedness would be left behind. Whether or not he was right, she was still going to be part of that, and still going to have an opportunity to excel. Not as an African-American. Not as a girl. But as herself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-2-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;DALL-E Generated image of Aisha upset after the press conference&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mother was unhappy at dinner. Aisha wasn’t sure if it was because she had cut the press conference short or if it was because of what the man said. Not knowing her mother’s feelings disturbed her even more. Finally, Mother spoke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What you did,” she said. “Reminded me of your father. It was like he was back there in the room with me. I’ve never been more proud of you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-2-4.png&quot; alt=&quot;DALL-E Generated image of Aisha and her mother having dinner&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha looked in her mother’s eyes. They were reddening. “It made me miss him all the more, and tonight you are leaving me too. I just realized how much I’ll miss you. It’ll be just me and your little brother now.” 
She stood up and walked round to Mother’s side of the table, embracing her warmly. She could feel Mother’s face on her shoulder, and the heat of her tears. Holding ever tighter, she felt the tears flow from her own face down Mother’s shoulder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I don’t have to go,” she said. “I can stay with you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mother pushed her back. “No,” she said. “You can’t deny yourself this. You know your father fought hard so that we can enjoy our freedom, and some day that will be impossible on this planet. I think that day is coming sooner than we think. You are going to that station. You are going to excel. And you are going to the stars, and taking memories of me, and your father, and your brother with you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-2-5.png&quot; alt=&quot;DALL-E Generated image of Aisha and her mother having dinner&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She held Aisha tightly. “I just wish I could be with you, so that they won’t attack you again.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They won’t, Mother. And you’ll always be with me.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-2-6.png&quot; alt=&quot;DALL-E Generated image of Aisha and her mother hugging, the terminus flotilla in the bg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="books" /><category term="personal" /><summary type="html">Continuing the experimental re-publishing of my novel “Space Cadets,” illustrated using Text-to-Image AI models. For this chapter, I’m still using DALL-E. For future chapters, I’ll explore other models too! Space Cadets is the story of the first African American girl accepted into a prestigious space academy, and the story of discrimination, racism, and old-fashioned bullying she faces, and how she overcomes it. So, here’s Chapter 2. Enjoy! CHAPTER 2 Press There are so many things I’ve learned since I broke away from the cocoon that we call our country. It’s a great place, a safe place, but perhaps it’s because of that safety that we look inward. And in the case of too many people, we look backward. Future dreams will never last if we always focus on the past. On the terrible things that were done to our ancestors. If we are to look forward, we should remember them, but not dwell on them TERMINUS, THE MASSIVE flotilla that surrounded the Space Elevator, was too mobile to be called a city in its purest sense. But for all intents and purposes, it was one. Their hotel was the finest Aisha had ever slept in, with big, comfortable beds and a wonderful breakfast. The slight rocking of their room caused by the waves only further lulled her to sleep. So it was in fine cheer that she greeted the press conference, the crankiness of travel a distant memory. Before long, she was biting her lip, trying not to snap at the monotony and repetition of the questions that were largely irrelevant to her future as a space cadet. “What’s it like being the first African-American to qualify through open enrollment?” “It’s great, but I can’t really answer what it’s like until I go up there. But I’m looking forward to it, and hoping I can be an effective student.” She watched as the reporters took notes, unhappy with such a straightforward statement. There was no story there. “How do you think you are going to cope with the pressure?” “Until I know what the pressure is, it’s hard to answer that question. I’m sure I will handle it the same way as any other student.” One of the reporters, a white man whose hair was whiter than his skin, interrupted. “But you aren’t like the other students, are you?” “Why would you say that?” “Because you are the first African-American student to qualify through open enrollment.” Aisha could feel her anger rising. She tried to keep her calm as she answered evenly, “How does that make me different from the other students?” “Please,” said the man. “We all see how politically correct this situation is. There has been so much pressure on the board of governors to open enroll from amongst the general population so that we can meet political needs of diversity. So, of course, the first thing we need to do is to have some African-Americans amongst the student body. And while we’re at it, why don’t we get a girl, so we kill two proverbial birds with one proverbial stone. Let’s also find one who lost a father in the second Korean War! Isn’t it obvious to you that you have been picked for all of these reasons and that you are going into orbit to be in a place where you are likely to be out of your depth, but will probably be handled by kid gloves, so as to satisfy those who are bearing political pressures?” Aisha felt her jaw drop. Even Mother was stunned into silence. The worst part, though, was that in a room full of people, many of whom were African-American, nobody leapt to her defense. Instead the press turned to her, recorders pointed in her direction, awaiting her answer. What a bunch of sharks! She could feel herself begin to sweat as all eyes turned her way. Time slowed to a crawl as they awaited an answer. With every passing tick, and nothing to say in response, she began to wonder if the man was right. If she really was out of her depth. If she really didn’t belong here, and she was just fooling herself. Maybe she wasn’t as smart or as capable as she thought she was. What would Father do in these circumstances? She had always learned of how great and how wise he was. Mother tried to pass down his teachings, but they were often through her filters, and Aisha was left to parse what the man had really been like, and what he would really do. She remembered one phrase: Never start the fight, but always finish it. The path was clear. There was a simple way to finish this fight. Composing herself as best she could, she smiled, and stood. It still felt like everything was moving in slow motion. Instead of exiting through the back, she took the steps down from the stage towards the waiting press, walking towards them. Some began to get upset at her not answering the question. That was the news they had come for, and they smelled blood in the water. But she maintained her composure, looking straight ahead and walking slowly, step-by-step, as they parted before her. Her path took her straight towards the reporter that had asked the question. His skin was turning redder now. Was it anger? Embarrassment? It didn’t matter. She met his gaze, held it for a moment. She watched him prepare for whatever she was going to say, saw his eyes dilate, his pallor flush. She gave him a little half-smile, and left the room to ever increasing volume and shouting. She finished the fight. Her insides burning, she wanted to get as far away from the press room as possible. She had maintained a calm composure, but the man’s words bounced around her head, making her angrier with each passing step. But what if he was right? What if she really was chosen for the reasons he had said? She had to admit to herself that she had taken pride at being the first of her race to be chosen. And with there being so many qualified boys, that the first was a girl. Maybe she shouldn’t have felt so proud. Maybe she shouldn’t have let mother’s braggadocios attitude wear off on her. The truth of the matter was that she was selected. That she was going to be a space cadet. In a few hours, she would be in orbit: Working with the best and brightest people in the world, learning how to fly spaceships, and being part of the research team that was building ships that would go to the stars. This small-mindedness would be left behind. Whether or not he was right, she was still going to be part of that, and still going to have an opportunity to excel. Not as an African-American. Not as a girl. But as herself. Mother was unhappy at dinner. Aisha wasn’t sure if it was because she had cut the press conference short or if it was because of what the man said. Not knowing her mother’s feelings disturbed her even more. Finally, Mother spoke. “What you did,” she said. “Reminded me of your father. It was like he was back there in the room with me. I’ve never been more proud of you.” Aisha looked in her mother’s eyes. They were reddening. “It made me miss him all the more, and tonight you are leaving me too. I just realized how much I’ll miss you. It’ll be just me and your little brother now.” She stood up and walked round to Mother’s side of the table, embracing her warmly. She could feel Mother’s face on her shoulder, and the heat of her tears. Holding ever tighter, she felt the tears flow from her own face down Mother’s shoulder. “I don’t have to go,” she said. “I can stay with you.” Mother pushed her back. “No,” she said. “You can’t deny yourself this. You know your father fought hard so that we can enjoy our freedom, and some day that will be impossible on this planet. I think that day is coming sooner than we think. You are going to that station. You are going to excel. And you are going to the stars, and taking memories of me, and your father, and your brother with you.” She held Aisha tightly. “I just wish I could be with you, so that they won’t attack you again.” “They won’t, Mother. And you’ll always be with me.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ML and the Stack Overflow 2022 Dev Survey</title><link href="/2022/06/22/stackoverflow.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ML and the Stack Overflow 2022 Dev Survey" /><published>2022-06-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2022/06/22/stackoverflow</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2022/06/22/stackoverflow.html">&lt;p&gt;Here’s the &lt;a href=&quot;https://survey.stackoverflow.co/2022/&quot;&gt;survey&lt;/a&gt; if you want to explore it for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off, explore the sample size used. It’s over 73K developers. Then, understanding that there  are about 27M developers world wide, when running a statistical size calculator, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.calculator.net/sample-size-calculator.html?type=1&amp;amp;cl=99&amp;amp;ci=1&amp;amp;pp=50&amp;amp;ps=27000000&amp;amp;x=91&amp;amp;y=34&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;, you’ll see that for a survey to be 99% accurate, with a margin of error of only 1%, you need a sample size of around 17,000&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when browsing the responses, particularly the ‘Professional Developers’ tabs, you’ll see that in general there are 3x to 4x the number of people answering than would be required for 99% accuracy with a 1% error margin!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;insights&quot;&gt;Insights:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;programming-languages---no-surprises&quot;&gt;Programming Languages - no surprises&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the most popular technologies section, 67.9% of developers say they used JavaScript. The programming language in second place was Python with 43.51% (in between was HTML/CSS and SQL, but I’m going to focus on more traditional coding languages here)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/sochart1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chart of top coding langauges&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That extrapolates to about &lt;em&gt;18 million&lt;/em&gt; JavaScript developers, and &lt;em&gt;12 million&lt;/em&gt; Python developers globally. Thus, as we build TensorFlow, these are the two main languages we support in developer documentation, education, etc. A surface of tens of millions of devs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ml-frameworks---the-widening-gap-between-tensorflow-and-pytorch&quot;&gt;ML Frameworks - the widening gap between TensorFlow and PyTorch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking into the ‘Other Frameworks and Libraries,’ one sees that 11.49% of Professional developers (i.e. about 3.1 Million) developers use TensorFlow, 7.61% (about 2M) use PyTorch and 6.47% (about 1.7M) use Keras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/sochart2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chart of top frameworks&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, when it comes to &lt;em&gt;developers&lt;/em&gt; using ML Frameworks, TensorFlow is clearly the &lt;em&gt;most popular&lt;/em&gt; one, with about 50% more developers using it than PyTorch, and that’s not counting the Keras devs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not clear from the survey how many of them are TF users, but even in the &lt;em&gt;worst case scenario&lt;/em&gt;, where it would be zero of them — TensorFlow would still have &lt;em&gt;50% more developers than PyTorch&lt;/em&gt; does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;em&gt;best case&lt;/em&gt;, where it would be all of them, then the population difference would be &lt;em&gt;more than double&lt;/em&gt;: 4.8M versus 2M.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, those folks that talk about PyTorch “eating TensorFlow’s lunch” simply aren’t supported by the numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And amongst the next generation of developers? 17.6% of ‘learners’ are using TensorFlow, 10.71% using Keras, and 10.68% using PyTorch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gap is &lt;em&gt;widening&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/sochart3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chart of top coding langauges being learned&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t a diss to PyTorch. I openly share that I’m excited that there is optionality in the ML space. If there was only 1 player, I would be very wary. But there isn’t. Competition is good. But it’s pretty clear that the conversation around ‘dominant’ frameworks is misplaced at best, and heavily biased at worst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and a big Kudos to the folks over at Hugging Face. With 1.92% of the respondents saying they use it, or bit more than half a million developers. That’s impressive for a brand new offering that’s specifically targeted to a particular scenario, as opposed to broad APIs like TensorFlow or PyTorch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;loved-and-dreaded-frameworks-popularity-doesnt-translate-to-beloved&quot;&gt;Loved and Dreaded Frameworks: Popularity doesn’t translate to beloved&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, when one looks at the Loved/Dreaded section — Hugging Face Transformers was the most beloved with a split of 72.2% loved versus 27.76% dreaded. PyTorch had a split of 68.29:31.71, and TensorFlow did a bit worse with 60.06:39.94. We have some work to do to make it more beloved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing to note here though is the number of respondents and their statistical relevance. So, for example, the PyTorch split is based on only 3952 answers, so it’s not going to be quite the 99% with a 1% margin of error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/sochart4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chart of loved frameworks&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;future-potential-from-people-who-want---the-widening-accelerates&quot;&gt;Future potential from people who ‘want’ - the widening accelerates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most insightful part, particularly when surveying the overall landscape is to look at what developers &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at this section, we see that 15.53% of developers want TensorFlow (from a survey of 53.442, so still well in the 99% with a 1% error margin), equating to a population of 4.19M developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a huge area of growth. The question was for those not already using it. So, if all of them to adopt, the TensorFlow developer community would grow from 3M to 7.19M.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/sochart5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chart of wanted frameworks&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the PyTorch community would grow from 2M to 4.39M, and the HuggingFace Transformers one could almost double to 1M.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it’s pretty clear — to me at least — the the ML framework community is vibrant, and that there are several players, the largest of which (by far!) is TensorFlow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And don’t just take my word for it — the World Economic Forum’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.weforum.org/docs/WEF_Jobs_of_Tomorrow_2020.pdf&quot;&gt;report on the jobs of tomorrow&lt;/a&gt; only names 1 framework: TensorFlow, and only names 1 way of learning it: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/professional-certificates/tensorflow-in-practice&quot;&gt;TensorFlow: In Practice specialization&lt;/a&gt; on Coursera!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Shameless self plug: I teach that course!)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="coding" /><summary type="html">Here’s the survey if you want to explore it for yourself. First off, explore the sample size used. It’s over 73K developers. Then, understanding that there are about 27M developers world wide, when running a statistical size calculator, like this one, you’ll see that for a survey to be 99% accurate, with a margin of error of only 1%, you need a sample size of around 17,000 So when browsing the responses, particularly the ‘Professional Developers’ tabs, you’ll see that in general there are 3x to 4x the number of people answering than would be required for 99% accuracy with a 1% error margin! Insights: Programming Languages - no surprises In the most popular technologies section, 67.9% of developers say they used JavaScript. The programming language in second place was Python with 43.51% (in between was HTML/CSS and SQL, but I’m going to focus on more traditional coding languages here) That extrapolates to about 18 million JavaScript developers, and 12 million Python developers globally. Thus, as we build TensorFlow, these are the two main languages we support in developer documentation, education, etc. A surface of tens of millions of devs. ML Frameworks - the widening gap between TensorFlow and PyTorch Looking into the ‘Other Frameworks and Libraries,’ one sees that 11.49% of Professional developers (i.e. about 3.1 Million) developers use TensorFlow, 7.61% (about 2M) use PyTorch and 6.47% (about 1.7M) use Keras. So, when it comes to developers using ML Frameworks, TensorFlow is clearly the most popular one, with about 50% more developers using it than PyTorch, and that’s not counting the Keras devs. It’s not clear from the survey how many of them are TF users, but even in the worst case scenario, where it would be zero of them — TensorFlow would still have 50% more developers than PyTorch does. In the best case, where it would be all of them, then the population difference would be more than double: 4.8M versus 2M. So, those folks that talk about PyTorch “eating TensorFlow’s lunch” simply aren’t supported by the numbers. And amongst the next generation of developers? 17.6% of ‘learners’ are using TensorFlow, 10.71% using Keras, and 10.68% using PyTorch. The gap is widening. This isn’t a diss to PyTorch. I openly share that I’m excited that there is optionality in the ML space. If there was only 1 player, I would be very wary. But there isn’t. Competition is good. But it’s pretty clear that the conversation around ‘dominant’ frameworks is misplaced at best, and heavily biased at worst. Oh, and a big Kudos to the folks over at Hugging Face. With 1.92% of the respondents saying they use it, or bit more than half a million developers. That’s impressive for a brand new offering that’s specifically targeted to a particular scenario, as opposed to broad APIs like TensorFlow or PyTorch. Loved and Dreaded Frameworks: Popularity doesn’t translate to beloved Indeed, when one looks at the Loved/Dreaded section — Hugging Face Transformers was the most beloved with a split of 72.2% loved versus 27.76% dreaded. PyTorch had a split of 68.29:31.71, and TensorFlow did a bit worse with 60.06:39.94. We have some work to do to make it more beloved. One thing to note here though is the number of respondents and their statistical relevance. So, for example, the PyTorch split is based on only 3952 answers, so it’s not going to be quite the 99% with a 1% margin of error. Future potential from people who ‘want’ - the widening accelerates Perhaps the most insightful part, particularly when surveying the overall landscape is to look at what developers want Looking at this section, we see that 15.53% of developers want TensorFlow (from a survey of 53.442, so still well in the 99% with a 1% error margin), equating to a population of 4.19M developers. That’s a huge area of growth. The question was for those not already using it. So, if all of them to adopt, the TensorFlow developer community would grow from 3M to 7.19M. Similarly, the PyTorch community would grow from 2M to 4.39M, and the HuggingFace Transformers one could almost double to 1M. So, it’s pretty clear — to me at least — the the ML framework community is vibrant, and that there are several players, the largest of which (by far!) is TensorFlow. And don’t just take my word for it — the World Economic Forum’s report on the jobs of tomorrow only names 1 framework: TensorFlow, and only names 1 way of learning it: the TensorFlow: In Practice specialization on Coursera! (Shameless self plug: I teach that course!)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Space Cadets - An AI-illustrated Novel. Chapter Three.</title><link href="/2022/06/20/Space_Cadets_Part_Three.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Space Cadets - An AI-illustrated Novel. Chapter Three." /><published>2022-06-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2022/06/20/Space_Cadets_Part_Three</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2022/06/20/Space_Cadets_Part_Three.html">&lt;p&gt;Continuing my experiment to illustrate a novel using AI text-to-image generation techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, I’m going to use MidJourney. Previous chapters used DALL-E. Let me know what you think twitter.com/lmoroney&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;chapter-3&quot;&gt;CHAPTER 3&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;launch&quot;&gt;Launch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We should always reach for the sky.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From the very beginning of history, our ancestors were looking up and wondering what was beyond their reach. The stars were calling them. They weaved stories of gods and angels, but behind them all was the intense desire to be out there. A desire born of an instinct for survival.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of a girl looking at the stars from the african savannah&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It’s something we’ve forgotten as we’ve become civilized. We’ve become comfortable in our homes, our cities and our countries. We’ve defeated nature and haven’t had the same worries that they had. But we lost something in that complacency, I fear. And now, as our world gets overcrowded, as our environment collapses under us, we need to rediscover it. We need to look up, and not worry about tripping as we race towards a new destiny. We will be those gods and angels if we want to. And you can be one of them, if you just keep trying, and never give up…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of Aisha looking out the windows of the hotel towards the spaceport&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;THE SPACE ELEVATOR. Its relatively simple name belied the sheer scale of it. Craning her neck, Aisha looked up as it disappeared impossibly into the deep blue sky. The ‘shuttle’ was a box-like structure that could easily pass for another building, but for the rocket boosters placed on its corners. These boosters would provide the initial ‘launch’ to get the craft moving out of its gravitational inertia. After that, the rotation of the Earth would take over and drive the shuttle up the cable into orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of a space elevator viewed from orbit&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was so glad for last night’s dinner with Mother. Beforehand, it had felt like there was a tension building between them. Mother’s basking in her status had gotten under Aisha’s skin, and she had been worried that she might blow up at her before leaving. She was worried that she might end up regretting it, but there was only so long she could bite her tongue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of a Aishas mother watching the shuttle in the distance&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She almost thanked the reporter for his rude question. It had brought them closer together. She felt a pang of pride again at Mother’s words that she had done exactly what Father would have done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the same reporter had wrestled his way to the front of the audience, and was barking out questions to the cadets as they boarded the shuttle. She was happy she knew where he was, so she could actively ignore him as she passed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She gave Mother one final hug, and turned and walked along the long ramp up to the shuttle. With every step away from her, Aisha felt more and more alone. As the entrance loomed toward her, she felt the urge to turn and run back to Mother’s welcoming arms. Mother would hold her and protect her, and to heck with anyone who would criticize her for not going through with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of the spaceport on a hawaiian island&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But she didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She continued step-by-step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the top of the ramp, she turned for one more look back at the Earth. She caught Mother’s eye as she waved frantically, blowing kisses and smiling. “That’s my little girl!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She raised her hand to wave, hearing cameras popping, and returned the smile before turning to enter the shuttle. Her feet suddenly felt heavy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was really going through with this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was really leaving home and going into &lt;em&gt;space&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each step seemed to be a chore, doubt and indecision weighing on her more heavily than gravity ever could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step-by-step she continued forward. The entrance lobby curved away from the door, and in a few moments, the daylight was lost. Words she had learned from history came back to her. Alea iacta est. She smiled, thinking that her Classics teacher would be proud of her. The die is cast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of the entrance lobby of a space elevator shuttle, windows overlooking to ocean beyond&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interior of the shuttle was clearly designed to impress and soothe its occupants. Instead of the functional ships of yesteryear, it was all polished chrome and intricately-designed surfaces. In the days of rocket travel to the stars, every ounce of payload had to be carefully measured, with no room for luxury, as propelling something into orbit required enormous amounts of energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Space Elevator changed all that, so designers of spacecraft were free to allow their occupants to be comfortable with traveling into space. This was also an important factor as many more people would leave the surface of the Earth – and a good, comfortable experience made it more tolerable, and thus less training was necessary. Indeed, Aisha had little more training than a couple of video tutorials explaining how to deal with weightlessness, and what to eat or not to eat prior to boarding. It was also good advice to use the bathroom before getting on the ship, for while facilities were available, using them in weightless conditions wasn’t optimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She climbed stairs to the observation deck where she would spend most of the journey. The deck was a wide circle with multi story windows, and acceleration couches arranged facing outwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-7.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of the space elevator observation deck&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As we rise up the cable, the shuttle will spin slowly,” she had remembered the tutorial video telling her. “So pick any seat, and you’ll still be able to see everything.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-9.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of Aisha in an acceleration sofa&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deck was terraced, so that seats near the back would still have a great view, and their occupants may not have the feeling of vertigo that those closer to the front would encounter. She picked one in the back row, next to an Asian girl who looked about Aisha’s age. The girl was intensely reading a book on her tablet, and didn’t look up as Aisha sat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-8.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of Aisha in an acceleration sofa&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She suddenly spoke. “Aisha Parks, celebrity.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha looked at her. “I’m not sure about that.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The girl looked up, and her intense eyes searched Aisha’s. “Good to know,” she said finally, reaching a hand out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Soo-Kyung Kim,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-10.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of Aisha meeting Soo-Kyung&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I don’t need to tell you my name, I guess.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soo-Kyung smiled. Her plain face lit up when she smiled. She was beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So where are you from?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soo-Kyung smiled again. “You haven’t heard of me? Good. I guess I am not a celebrity, either.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an odd answer, and from Soo-Kyung’s reaction, it was clear that Aisha’s confusion was written on her face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I think we are going to be good friends,” said Soo-Kyung. “I like how you are straightforward. I am too, but that intimidates some people.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-11.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of Aisha and Soo-Kyung chatting&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So where are you from?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am from a small village called Sijungho,” continued Soo Kyung. “There’s not much to see there.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Sounds Korean,” said Aisha. “You from South Korea?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“North Korea,” corrected Soo-Kyung. “I’ve never even been to South Korea.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha felt her insides go cold. Against her will, she shuddered a little, and felt a sob begin to escape from her throat. Her father had died as a result of radiation sickness incurred in the second Korean War. And there was a North Korean girl here with her. Going into space with her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She knew there was incredulity in her voice, but she couldn’t mask it. “Are you going to the Academy too?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yes,” said Soo-Kyung. “And don’t worry, I’m as surprised as you are.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s what you meant by celebrity?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It seems the media made as big a deal about me being the first North Korean as it did about you being the first African-American to go through open enrollment. It’s all a sham though, isn’t it?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m beginning to gather that.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I mean, when the Academy was first built, it was apparent that it was for the Elites, most of whom are from Western society, with a few Russians and Chinese thrown in to get funding. Nobody really knows who the students were, but it was typically those who would be in private elite schools on the surface, so being in space made little difference.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha thought about what Soo-Kyung was saying, and realized that she was right. Amazing that she had never thought of this herself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Korean girl continued. “Now that they are all in place and established, it’s time to open it up to the rest of the world, so we can get their proverbial ‘sloppy seconds’, I guess.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s an academy,” said Aisha. “And we’re cadets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The cannon fodder, while they are the officers ordering us around.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So why are you going through with it? Why am &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; going through with it?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soo-Kyung shrugged. “Because it’s better than &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going through with it. Besides, there might be something great waiting for normal people like us.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“My father died in Korea,” said Aisha, surprising even herself at the change in subject. “But he always told my mother to tell me that I had a destiny. That the emerging age of space flight was one in which we must be free to explore the universe. He fought so that that freedom would still exist, so that I could do this. I can’t turn back.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Most of my family died in the same war,” said Soo-Kyung. “But nothing ever really changed, did it?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha realized that she must have sounded bitter, and the bitterness was reflected in Soo-Kyung’s answer. 
“I’m sorry,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No need,” said Soo-Kyung. “I’m glad that you are open and honest with me. Most people, particularly outside of my country, are not. They learn about where I’m from and think I need special treatment. I don’t. I’ve learned to stand on my own.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I wish I had your strength.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You don’t,” said Soo-Kyung, suddenly serious. “&lt;em&gt;That&lt;/em&gt; kind of strength comes from trying to make a life in a country destroyed by nuclear war. You never want it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-12.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of Soo-Kyung as a little girl in North Korea as nukes fall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s why we’re going into space, isn’t it? To make sure that wars like those will never put our species’ survival at risk.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That would be nice,” said Soo-Kyung. “But if anything I think it will cause more wars and hardship before things get better.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Why?” 
“Because the only thing that stopped the entire world from burning during the war over my country was that it was the only world we have. If we discover more planets, livable ones, that will no longer be the case. And I want to be as far away from this world as possible before the next bombs fall.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before Aisha could answer, the soft tone of the launch warning sounded. The rocket boost would be gentler than a typical aircraft take off, but safety protocols required that they be buckled into their crash seats in case anything went wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She rolled her eyes and smiled, and strapped herself in. When everything was snug, she turned to look at Soo-Kyung. Their eyes met again, and Soo-Kyung bowed slightly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The engines kicked in, and their seats lurched a little. From all around came the muffled sounds of the rockets roaring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the windows, Aisha could see the ground begin to slowly fall away. Within a few seconds the flotilla was no longer visible, and as they began to rise, she could see the entire outline of the nearby Kiritimati, where only yesterday they had landed. It felt like an eternity ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She wondered how Mother felt, watching her shuttle rise slowly to the sky. As suddenly as they had begun, the rockets cut out, and there was another slight lurch as the inertia of the ship was stopped. She remembered the video training – this was the scariest part of the trip, where the shuttle, under normal gravity, could fall back to Earth and kill everyone aboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it didn’t, and the force on the Space Elevator started pushing them skyward, with ever-increasing speed. The horizon began to spin also, and as they rose up, she watched the island recede. Before long they were high enough to see that the horizon was curved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was it. This was for real. She was headed into space!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-13.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of Aisha&apos;s mother watching the shuttle lift into space&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="books" /><category term="personal" /><summary type="html">Continuing my experiment to illustrate a novel using AI text-to-image generation techniques. In this article, I’m going to use MidJourney. Previous chapters used DALL-E. Let me know what you think twitter.com/lmoroney CHAPTER 3 Launch We should always reach for the sky. From the very beginning of history, our ancestors were looking up and wondering what was beyond their reach. The stars were calling them. They weaved stories of gods and angels, but behind them all was the intense desire to be out there. A desire born of an instinct for survival. It’s something we’ve forgotten as we’ve become civilized. We’ve become comfortable in our homes, our cities and our countries. We’ve defeated nature and haven’t had the same worries that they had. But we lost something in that complacency, I fear. And now, as our world gets overcrowded, as our environment collapses under us, we need to rediscover it. We need to look up, and not worry about tripping as we race towards a new destiny. We will be those gods and angels if we want to. And you can be one of them, if you just keep trying, and never give up… THE SPACE ELEVATOR. Its relatively simple name belied the sheer scale of it. Craning her neck, Aisha looked up as it disappeared impossibly into the deep blue sky. The ‘shuttle’ was a box-like structure that could easily pass for another building, but for the rocket boosters placed on its corners. These boosters would provide the initial ‘launch’ to get the craft moving out of its gravitational inertia. After that, the rotation of the Earth would take over and drive the shuttle up the cable into orbit. She was so glad for last night’s dinner with Mother. Beforehand, it had felt like there was a tension building between them. Mother’s basking in her status had gotten under Aisha’s skin, and she had been worried that she might blow up at her before leaving. She was worried that she might end up regretting it, but there was only so long she could bite her tongue. She almost thanked the reporter for his rude question. It had brought them closer together. She felt a pang of pride again at Mother’s words that she had done exactly what Father would have done. Of course, the same reporter had wrestled his way to the front of the audience, and was barking out questions to the cadets as they boarded the shuttle. She was happy she knew where he was, so she could actively ignore him as she passed. She gave Mother one final hug, and turned and walked along the long ramp up to the shuttle. With every step away from her, Aisha felt more and more alone. As the entrance loomed toward her, she felt the urge to turn and run back to Mother’s welcoming arms. Mother would hold her and protect her, and to heck with anyone who would criticize her for not going through with it. But she didn’t. She continued step-by-step. At the top of the ramp, she turned for one more look back at the Earth. She caught Mother’s eye as she waved frantically, blowing kisses and smiling. “That’s my little girl!” She raised her hand to wave, hearing cameras popping, and returned the smile before turning to enter the shuttle. Her feet suddenly felt heavy. She was really going through with this. She was really leaving home and going into space. Each step seemed to be a chore, doubt and indecision weighing on her more heavily than gravity ever could. Step-by-step she continued forward. The entrance lobby curved away from the door, and in a few moments, the daylight was lost. Words she had learned from history came back to her. Alea iacta est. She smiled, thinking that her Classics teacher would be proud of her. The die is cast. The interior of the shuttle was clearly designed to impress and soothe its occupants. Instead of the functional ships of yesteryear, it was all polished chrome and intricately-designed surfaces. In the days of rocket travel to the stars, every ounce of payload had to be carefully measured, with no room for luxury, as propelling something into orbit required enormous amounts of energy. The Space Elevator changed all that, so designers of spacecraft were free to allow their occupants to be comfortable with traveling into space. This was also an important factor as many more people would leave the surface of the Earth – and a good, comfortable experience made it more tolerable, and thus less training was necessary. Indeed, Aisha had little more training than a couple of video tutorials explaining how to deal with weightlessness, and what to eat or not to eat prior to boarding. It was also good advice to use the bathroom before getting on the ship, for while facilities were available, using them in weightless conditions wasn’t optimal. She climbed stairs to the observation deck where she would spend most of the journey. The deck was a wide circle with multi story windows, and acceleration couches arranged facing outwards. “As we rise up the cable, the shuttle will spin slowly,” she had remembered the tutorial video telling her. “So pick any seat, and you’ll still be able to see everything.” The deck was terraced, so that seats near the back would still have a great view, and their occupants may not have the feeling of vertigo that those closer to the front would encounter. She picked one in the back row, next to an Asian girl who looked about Aisha’s age. The girl was intensely reading a book on her tablet, and didn’t look up as Aisha sat. She suddenly spoke. “Aisha Parks, celebrity.” Aisha looked at her. “I’m not sure about that.” The girl looked up, and her intense eyes searched Aisha’s. “Good to know,” she said finally, reaching a hand out. “Soo-Kyung Kim,” she said. “I don’t need to tell you my name, I guess.” Soo-Kyung smiled. Her plain face lit up when she smiled. She was beautiful. “So where are you from?” Soo-Kyung smiled again. “You haven’t heard of me? Good. I guess I am not a celebrity, either.” Such an odd answer, and from Soo-Kyung’s reaction, it was clear that Aisha’s confusion was written on her face. “I think we are going to be good friends,” said Soo-Kyung. “I like how you are straightforward. I am too, but that intimidates some people.” “So where are you from?” “I am from a small village called Sijungho,” continued Soo Kyung. “There’s not much to see there.” “Sounds Korean,” said Aisha. “You from South Korea?” “North Korea,” corrected Soo-Kyung. “I’ve never even been to South Korea.” Aisha felt her insides go cold. Against her will, she shuddered a little, and felt a sob begin to escape from her throat. Her father had died as a result of radiation sickness incurred in the second Korean War. And there was a North Korean girl here with her. Going into space with her. She knew there was incredulity in her voice, but she couldn’t mask it. “Are you going to the Academy too?” “Yes,” said Soo-Kyung. “And don’t worry, I’m as surprised as you are.” “That’s what you meant by celebrity?” “It seems the media made as big a deal about me being the first North Korean as it did about you being the first African-American to go through open enrollment. It’s all a sham though, isn’t it?” “I’m beginning to gather that.” “I mean, when the Academy was first built, it was apparent that it was for the Elites, most of whom are from Western society, with a few Russians and Chinese thrown in to get funding. Nobody really knows who the students were, but it was typically those who would be in private elite schools on the surface, so being in space made little difference.” Aisha thought about what Soo-Kyung was saying, and realized that she was right. Amazing that she had never thought of this herself. The Korean girl continued. “Now that they are all in place and established, it’s time to open it up to the rest of the world, so we can get their proverbial ‘sloppy seconds’, I guess.” “It’s an academy,” said Aisha. “And we’re cadets.” “The cannon fodder, while they are the officers ordering us around.” “So why are you going through with it? Why am I going through with it?” Soo-Kyung shrugged. “Because it’s better than not going through with it. Besides, there might be something great waiting for normal people like us.” “My father died in Korea,” said Aisha, surprising even herself at the change in subject. “But he always told my mother to tell me that I had a destiny. That the emerging age of space flight was one in which we must be free to explore the universe. He fought so that that freedom would still exist, so that I could do this. I can’t turn back.” “Most of my family died in the same war,” said Soo-Kyung. “But nothing ever really changed, did it?” Aisha realized that she must have sounded bitter, and the bitterness was reflected in Soo-Kyung’s answer. “I’m sorry,” she said. “No need,” said Soo-Kyung. “I’m glad that you are open and honest with me. Most people, particularly outside of my country, are not. They learn about where I’m from and think I need special treatment. I don’t. I’ve learned to stand on my own.” “I wish I had your strength.” “You don’t,” said Soo-Kyung, suddenly serious. “That kind of strength comes from trying to make a life in a country destroyed by nuclear war. You never want it.” “That’s why we’re going into space, isn’t it? To make sure that wars like those will never put our species’ survival at risk.” “That would be nice,” said Soo-Kyung. “But if anything I think it will cause more wars and hardship before things get better.” “Why?” “Because the only thing that stopped the entire world from burning during the war over my country was that it was the only world we have. If we discover more planets, livable ones, that will no longer be the case. And I want to be as far away from this world as possible before the next bombs fall.” Before Aisha could answer, the soft tone of the launch warning sounded. The rocket boost would be gentler than a typical aircraft take off, but safety protocols required that they be buckled into their crash seats in case anything went wrong. She rolled her eyes and smiled, and strapped herself in. When everything was snug, she turned to look at Soo-Kyung. Their eyes met again, and Soo-Kyung bowed slightly. The engines kicked in, and their seats lurched a little. From all around came the muffled sounds of the rockets roaring. Through the windows, Aisha could see the ground begin to slowly fall away. Within a few seconds the flotilla was no longer visible, and as they began to rise, she could see the entire outline of the nearby Kiritimati, where only yesterday they had landed. It felt like an eternity ago. She wondered how Mother felt, watching her shuttle rise slowly to the sky. As suddenly as they had begun, the rockets cut out, and there was another slight lurch as the inertia of the ship was stopped. She remembered the video training – this was the scariest part of the trip, where the shuttle, under normal gravity, could fall back to Earth and kill everyone aboard. But it didn’t, and the force on the Space Elevator started pushing them skyward, with ever-increasing speed. The horizon began to spin also, and as they rose up, she watched the island recede. Before long they were high enough to see that the horizon was curved. This was it. This was for real. She was headed into space!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Space Cadets - An AI-illustrated Novel. Part One.</title><link href="/2022/06/20/Space_Cadets_Part_One.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Space Cadets - An AI-illustrated Novel. Part One." /><published>2022-06-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2022/06/20/Space_Cadets_Part_One</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2022/06/20/Space_Cadets_Part_One.html">&lt;p&gt;In 2015, I wrote a novel called &lt;em&gt;Space Cadets&lt;/em&gt; which was beloved by its (very few) readers, but shortly after publication, the publisher went bust. As such I’ve been sitting on the novel for years, and instead of leaving it to gather digital dust, I’m using it for an experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An online, illustrated, novel, with all of the illustrations using AI. Here’s part one, and I used DALL-E throughout to try to visualize some of the scenes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want more, please reach out and let me know!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;training&quot;&gt;TRAINING&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IT NEVER FAILED to give her a thrill when she saw the moonscape rush by underneath her ship, and the blue curve of Earth rise above it. Aisha smiled at its beauty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-1-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;DALL-E Generated Image of Spaceship above the moon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Down there, girls her age were wondering about homecoming dances, what dress they’d wear, or which boy would ask them out. She was much happier here, piloting her ship, zipping at breakneck speeds across the Moon, and getting ready to break into deep space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I think I see them,” said David, her navigator, and co-pilot, sitting in one of the wing pods to her right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Two-seven-zero Karem one-nine-eight.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Confirmed,” came the clipped voice of Soo-Kyung, her gunner. Aisha glanced to the pod on her left and her eyes met Soo-Kyung’s. The Korean girl smiled and nodded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha always wanted a visual confirmation. Comm lines could be hacked and voices faked. Soo-Kyung knew this instinctively. That’s what made them a great team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-1-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;DALL-E Generated Image of a person flying a ship in VR&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Okay,” said Aisha. “Weapons hot. Let’s check them out.” She punched in the coordinates, and the ship turned towards its target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Visual range in five seconds,” said David.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I see them,” Aisha replied. Her heads-up display started to light up with targets. Squares projected on her canopy, wrapping tiny dots that could easily be mistaken for stars to the naked eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s a lot of ships,” she said, awe sneaking into her voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s a bloody awful lot of ships,” said David.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-1-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;DALL-E Generated Image of a person flying a ship in VR&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soo-Kyung was business as always. “Orders?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Can you confirm ship type?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They are mostly type-three fighters. About eighty of them.” “What else?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A single mothership. That’s the target.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No other fighters?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A couple of type-ones, but hard to tell with all the movement.” The fighters were moving around the mothership, following what looked like random patterns, making it hard to get a radar lock. “Are they moving to intercept?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No, sir.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“David, probe the edge of their defense shield.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His gentle voice sounded in her earpiece. “Yes, Sir.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David took the ship forward slowly, while Soo-Kyung watched the behavior of the enemy fighters. They knew from experience that these ships could turn from defense to offense in the blink of an eye. If they didn’t react, they could find themselves surrounded and destroyed in seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are at the edge of previous attack ranges,” said Soo-Kyung. “Recommend that we hold this position.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Do it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship halted, and they floated in space, watching the enemy. “Any update on ship types, David?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-1-5.png&quot; alt=&quot;DALL-E Generated Image of a spaceship hovering above the moon, alien ships in the background&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The best I got is maybe two or three type-ones, the rest are type-three.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She wished she had read the spec books more closely but was glad David was there. “Turning radius of type-threes?” “Two hundred degrees,” he answered, almost in reflex. “Distance of fighters from the mothership?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Average about three hundred clicks.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soo-Kyung raised an eyebrow. “Are you thinking what I’m thinking?” “Yes,” said Aisha. “Full frontal assault, all shields on front.” “If we leave our back exposed–”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hopefully they won’t get a chance. Maximum throttle, straight at the mothership, direct all energy to front shields.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Including lasers?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Including lasers. We’re on bullets and torpedoes. Can you do it?” She heard the smile in Soo-Kyung’s voice. “Done.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Good. And fire at will.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Roger.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“David. Punch course in.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Course, aye.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Manual control to me.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Roger.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Here goes nothing!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-1-6.png&quot; alt=&quot;DALL-E Generated Image of a spaceship hovering above the moon, getting ready to fly into a cloud of enemy ships&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha punched the program, and she felt the craft lurch as they accelerated forward. She continued its burn, getting faster and faster as they approached the enemy ships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ships turning to intercept.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Acknowledged.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She saw the enemy ships swarming to intercept. Suddenly their random patterns stopped, and they turned, almost as one, bearing down on her. They opened fire, but the forward shields held.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Intercept in five seconds,” said Soo-Kyung. Aisha marveled at her ability to stay calm, and it seemed the more stressful the situation, the calmer she was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And just like that, they flew through the squadrons of enemy fighters, on a course straight for the mothership. 
“They’re turning to intercept.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time seemed to slow down in her mind. The mothership approached weapons range at a painful crawl. The enemy fighters, now behind her, were slowly turning to follow them, with a clear shot at Aisha’s tail. She’d turned off their lasers, directing their energy to the shields, so they’d need to be close for ballistic weapons to be effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was going to be tight. Once the enemy fighters had turned around, the back of Aisha’s fighter was exposed. The lead ones had almost turned and were ready to open fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then Soo-Kyung had her target locked and opened up with everything she had on the mothership. Direct hits, but the ship stayed intact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hit on their right-wing made the ship lurch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Now would be a good time, Soo-Kyung.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha looked to her left, seeing her friend’s face deep in concentration. Another torpedo launched, hitting a module to the rear of the mothership’s bridge. A small explosion was followed by several large ones, but before the ship was destroyed, Aisha’s ship was hit again. This time right in the engines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-1-7.png&quot; alt=&quot;DALL-E Generated Image of an alien mothership hovering above the moon, with damage on its side&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha felt her ship lurch. Red lights were all over her console. The reactor had taken a direct hit. It was about to go critical. Her heart was beating hard. She reached for the eject buttons, hesitating long enough to see the mothership go up in a ball of flame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moment’s hesitation was enough. She felt the ship lurch as the reactor gave out. Her mind slowed as the white flash enveloped them. She had enough time to realize, with resignation, that she was dead. Both co-pilots too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simulator door opened, and Captain Simms’ craggy face looked in at her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You’re dead. All of you. Again,” he said. Disapproval in his voice. “I thought you guys were better than that.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-1-8.png&quot; alt=&quot;DALL-E Generated Image of Virtual Reality simulators with teenage pilots training within&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;part-one&quot;&gt;PART ONE:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-letter-from-my-father&quot;&gt;A Letter From My Father&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-1&quot;&gt;CHAPTER 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;departures&quot;&gt;Departures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My Dearest Aisha: 
I don’t even know how to begin writing this letter. I look at you now, sleeping in your crib, so small and so helpless, and I wish I could be there with you when you take your first steps. I wish I could see it when you get on the bus for your first day of school. I wish I could hold you when you come home crying for the first time, realizing that the world is a bigger and worse place than you could have ever imagined. 
But I won’t be. The disease that is tearing through my body will take me away from you soon. And I’m so very sorry. But, so that I won’t be a distant and mysterious memory, I’m writing you this letter. 
For you have a destiny. A bright and wonderful destiny…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;THE TRANSPORT PLANE was older and more rickety than she would have expected for one headed to the spaceport. Aisha peered out the window of the plane intently, waiting for her first glimpse of the great cable veering skyward from Kiritimati into the depths of space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-1-9.png&quot; alt=&quot;DALL-E Generated Image of a rickety airplane flying above polynesian islands&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It even had the old-school seats facing each other across a small table. A man sat there, and he was watching her closely. “It’s nothing really special,” he said. “You don’t see anything. It’s only interesting when a launch happens.” “How often?” she asked, knowing the answer already. She always knew the answer already, but she asked anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It depends,” he said, looking at his watch. “We build the shuttle onsite and then launch it. It’s not worth bringing it back to Earth, where it would burn up in the atmosphere, so it’s designed to be launched once, and then disassembled into different things to be used up there.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He pointed at the sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m going up tomorrow,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He nodded, smiling. “I figured. We get a lot of kids your age coming through here, heading for the Academy.” 
He smiled and went back to reading the news from his tablet. He hadn’t said anything about her color. Mother had insisted on telling everyone within earshot that Aisha was the first African-American to go to the Academy. And not only was she African-American, but she was also a girl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha groaned inwardly. She wished mother would just stop. It had been a couple of hours since they had left Hawaii. The plane flew south to the tiny atoll that Aisha couldn’t take her eyes off of. Upon arrival, they would take the short trip out to the bottom of the cable, and the fleet of ships imaginatively called Terminus. That would be the last stop before she launched into orbit, leaving Earth behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-1-10.png&quot; alt=&quot;DALL-E Generated Image of the base of a space elevator in the polynesian islands&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The man lowered his tablet and pointed to a silver dot on the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s a shuttle right there,” he said. “And if you look closely you can see the cable that makes up the Space Elevator.” Even the words sounded amazing to her. The Space Elevator. Since the invention of materials with the requisite strength in low enough density to make the concept buildable, many nations had gathered together to build this one. The idea was simple. Tether a cable on the Earth near the equator, and extend it out into space for about 35,000 kilometers. The object on the far end of the cable would then be in geostationary orbit, always above the same position on the Earth, much like communications or TV satellites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She peered, trying to make out the cable, but it was just too skinny to be seen from this distance – except for the occasional glint as the tropical sun reflected off it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the cable was tethered to the surface of the Earth, the rotation of the planet would send any object attached to the cable flying out from the center of gravity, propelling it into space. Once it reached the top of the cable, it could then launch itself outward, using a tiny fraction of the fuel that a traditional rocket launch would use up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-1-11.png&quot; alt=&quot;DALL-E Generated Image of the cable of the space elevator reaching into the sky&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost overnight, it revolutionized space travel. One of the first things the international community had agreed upon was to build an academy. Its goal: To teach a new generation of humans what it would be like to have a single, coherent community, not hindered by the tropes of the past. Ultimately, such a community would be the future of mankind, its backers had argued, and would put an end to the wars that nearly destroyed us all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-1-12.png&quot; alt=&quot;DALL-E Generated Image of the space elevator viewed from space&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha opened her locket and looked at his face, trying to remember him. Ravaged by cancers from radiation suffered in war, her father died before she reached her first birthday. He smiled back at her from the tiny picture, and she could see the pride in his smile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I did it, Dad. I made it into space, and I made sure that you would never be forgotten. That the next phase of humanity will have a little part of you in it. That was worth fighting for. I just wish you didn’t have to die for it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plane jolted as it began to descend, waking Mother. “Are we there yet?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha smiled to herself. “We’re almost at the Terminus.” Mother smiled and looked at the man sitting across from Aisha. “She’s going to the Space Academy, you know,” she said, smiling. The man nodded. “You must be so proud.” 
“Oh, I am,” said Mother. “She’ll always be my little girl, but to be the first African-American, and one of the first girls up there, it’s so exciting.” “I’m sure,” said the man. “I think she’ll do amazing things.” “Aww, you’re so nice,” said Mother, milking the compliment for all it was worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said nothing and went back to reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irked, mother looked around for someone else to impress. The plane lurched again, so she closed her eyes instead, fighting back airsickness. Mother was never good at flying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha turned back to the window, catching the man’s eye with his small smile. He nodded at her, and she returned the gesture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ground rushed at them, and with a jolt, they landed on the small airstrip. Since the construction of the Space Elevator had begun, this tiny island had changed from being a rock in the middle of the ocean to a thriving miniature city. But land was at a premium, so all passenger transport still came through the tiny airstrip on the western side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha had read that a new floating airport was under construction. When it opened, the island would be connected directly to the mainland of the USA and other countries, instead of needing a transport plane like this one flying out of Hawaii. 
As she got out of the plane, Aisha could feel the warm breeze and hear the crash of the surf. A rocky beach lay just to her right, within walking distance of the airstrip. Mother emerged, blinking in the bright light. A representative of the Academy greeted them and led them towards a small set of prefabricated buildings that served as the registration center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tiny look of disappointment crossed Mother’s face. Aisha rolled her eyes. Mother was probably expecting more press to meet them here, presumably not having enough of them in Hawaii.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only cadet on the arriving flight, Aisha strolled after the greeter, calling for Mother to keep up. The warm humid air felt good in her lungs. For the next few years she would be breathing processed air in the space station, so she wanted to make the most of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She wondered if there would be time for the beach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The administrative center was as plain on the inside as it was on the outside. A threadbare box, it housed several desks at which sat tired-looking administrators swiping through computer terminals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The greeter read Mother’s disappointed gaze. “Here’s where we just make sure you are whom you say you are before taking the boat across to the Elevator. It helps us make sure that people don’t sneak aboard.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mother raised her eyebrows. “What kind of people sneak aboard? Terrorists? It doesn’t look like you could stop them!” The greeter smiled a little, and to Aisha, it looked practiced. “No terrorist could get within a thousand miles of this place. No, we’re more concerned about curious onlookers, too many relatives of cadets, that type of thing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His words confused Aisha. How could a terrorist be stopped from getting here, when just about anybody could fly here, including too many family members? Was it all a front, or were they profiling everything about every person who even tried to come to this place? She held her tongue. If Mother thought there was any profiling going on, she’d launch into one of her rants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I hear the hotel is very nice,” Aisha said, changing the subject. “Yes,” said the greeter. “We want your last night on planet Earth to be special.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But she’ll be coming back, for vacations and the like,” said Mother. “So it’s hardly her last night.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Of course,” said the greeter, smiling, before ushering them to a desk where the clerk had finally booted up his screen. “You’re our last flight of the day today,” he said cheerfully. “But don’t worry - you aren’t the only launchie. The others are at the Terminus ahead of you, so you’ll have plenty of friends for the ride up.” Aisha smiled. She didn’t need friends, but it was best not to argue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ah Miss Parks,” he continued, checking her credentials. “I heard you were coming today, it’s very nice to have you aboard.” “Thanks,” said Aisha. “But I just want to be like any other student.” “Yes,” he continued. “The media have made a big deal about it down here, but once you get up there, all that will be forgotten.” Mother piqued up. “What?” 
“We try to keep the kids insulated from political and social matters down on Earth,” he said in a trained voice. “That way they can focus on their work.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But she is the first African-American to be accepted since open enrollment. Not only that, she’s one of the first girls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That makes her very important.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ma’am,” said the receptionist. “Your daughter is extremely important, and in time you’ll find it’s not for those reasons, but for who she is and what she’s capable of doing. Her race, her gender, those things don’t matter.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But she is the first African-American–”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The man interrupted, albeit politely. “Of course,” he said. “And the press at Terminus will want to ask you all about that.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-1-14.png&quot; alt=&quot;DALL-E Generated Image of the cable of the space elevator reaching into the sky&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="books" /><category term="personal" /><summary type="html">In 2015, I wrote a novel called Space Cadets which was beloved by its (very few) readers, but shortly after publication, the publisher went bust. As such I’ve been sitting on the novel for years, and instead of leaving it to gather digital dust, I’m using it for an experiment. An online, illustrated, novel, with all of the illustrations using AI. Here’s part one, and I used DALL-E throughout to try to visualize some of the scenes. If you want more, please reach out and let me know! TRAINING IT NEVER FAILED to give her a thrill when she saw the moonscape rush by underneath her ship, and the blue curve of Earth rise above it. Aisha smiled at its beauty. Down there, girls her age were wondering about homecoming dances, what dress they’d wear, or which boy would ask them out. She was much happier here, piloting her ship, zipping at breakneck speeds across the Moon, and getting ready to break into deep space. “I think I see them,” said David, her navigator, and co-pilot, sitting in one of the wing pods to her right. “Two-seven-zero Karem one-nine-eight.” “Confirmed,” came the clipped voice of Soo-Kyung, her gunner. Aisha glanced to the pod on her left and her eyes met Soo-Kyung’s. The Korean girl smiled and nodded. Aisha always wanted a visual confirmation. Comm lines could be hacked and voices faked. Soo-Kyung knew this instinctively. That’s what made them a great team. “Okay,” said Aisha. “Weapons hot. Let’s check them out.” She punched in the coordinates, and the ship turned towards its target. “Visual range in five seconds,” said David. “I see them,” Aisha replied. Her heads-up display started to light up with targets. Squares projected on her canopy, wrapping tiny dots that could easily be mistaken for stars to the naked eye. “That’s a lot of ships,” she said, awe sneaking into her voice. “That’s a bloody awful lot of ships,” said David. Soo-Kyung was business as always. “Orders?” “Can you confirm ship type?” “They are mostly type-three fighters. About eighty of them.” “What else?” “A single mothership. That’s the target.” “No other fighters?” “A couple of type-ones, but hard to tell with all the movement.” The fighters were moving around the mothership, following what looked like random patterns, making it hard to get a radar lock. “Are they moving to intercept?” “No, sir.” “David, probe the edge of their defense shield.” His gentle voice sounded in her earpiece. “Yes, Sir.” David took the ship forward slowly, while Soo-Kyung watched the behavior of the enemy fighters. They knew from experience that these ships could turn from defense to offense in the blink of an eye. If they didn’t react, they could find themselves surrounded and destroyed in seconds. “We are at the edge of previous attack ranges,” said Soo-Kyung. “Recommend that we hold this position.” “Do it.” The ship halted, and they floated in space, watching the enemy. “Any update on ship types, David?” “The best I got is maybe two or three type-ones, the rest are type-three.” She wished she had read the spec books more closely but was glad David was there. “Turning radius of type-threes?” “Two hundred degrees,” he answered, almost in reflex. “Distance of fighters from the mothership?” “Average about three hundred clicks.” Soo-Kyung raised an eyebrow. “Are you thinking what I’m thinking?” “Yes,” said Aisha. “Full frontal assault, all shields on front.” “If we leave our back exposed–” “Hopefully they won’t get a chance. Maximum throttle, straight at the mothership, direct all energy to front shields.” “Including lasers?” “Including lasers. We’re on bullets and torpedoes. Can you do it?” She heard the smile in Soo-Kyung’s voice. “Done.” “Good. And fire at will.” “Roger.” “David. Punch course in.” “Course, aye.” “Manual control to me.” “Roger.” “Here goes nothing!” Aisha punched the program, and she felt the craft lurch as they accelerated forward. She continued its burn, getting faster and faster as they approached the enemy ships. “Ships turning to intercept.” “Acknowledged.” She saw the enemy ships swarming to intercept. Suddenly their random patterns stopped, and they turned, almost as one, bearing down on her. They opened fire, but the forward shields held. “Intercept in five seconds,” said Soo-Kyung. Aisha marveled at her ability to stay calm, and it seemed the more stressful the situation, the calmer she was. And just like that, they flew through the squadrons of enemy fighters, on a course straight for the mothership. “They’re turning to intercept.” Time seemed to slow down in her mind. The mothership approached weapons range at a painful crawl. The enemy fighters, now behind her, were slowly turning to follow them, with a clear shot at Aisha’s tail. She’d turned off their lasers, directing their energy to the shields, so they’d need to be close for ballistic weapons to be effective. It was going to be tight. Once the enemy fighters had turned around, the back of Aisha’s fighter was exposed. The lead ones had almost turned and were ready to open fire. But then Soo-Kyung had her target locked and opened up with everything she had on the mothership. Direct hits, but the ship stayed intact. A hit on their right-wing made the ship lurch. “Now would be a good time, Soo-Kyung.” Aisha looked to her left, seeing her friend’s face deep in concentration. Another torpedo launched, hitting a module to the rear of the mothership’s bridge. A small explosion was followed by several large ones, but before the ship was destroyed, Aisha’s ship was hit again. This time right in the engines. Aisha felt her ship lurch. Red lights were all over her console. The reactor had taken a direct hit. It was about to go critical. Her heart was beating hard. She reached for the eject buttons, hesitating long enough to see the mothership go up in a ball of flame. The moment’s hesitation was enough. She felt the ship lurch as the reactor gave out. Her mind slowed as the white flash enveloped them. She had enough time to realize, with resignation, that she was dead. Both co-pilots too. The simulator door opened, and Captain Simms’ craggy face looked in at her. “You’re dead. All of you. Again,” he said. Disapproval in his voice. “I thought you guys were better than that.” PART ONE: A Letter From My Father CHAPTER 1 Departures My Dearest Aisha: I don’t even know how to begin writing this letter. I look at you now, sleeping in your crib, so small and so helpless, and I wish I could be there with you when you take your first steps. I wish I could see it when you get on the bus for your first day of school. I wish I could hold you when you come home crying for the first time, realizing that the world is a bigger and worse place than you could have ever imagined. But I won’t be. The disease that is tearing through my body will take me away from you soon. And I’m so very sorry. But, so that I won’t be a distant and mysterious memory, I’m writing you this letter. For you have a destiny. A bright and wonderful destiny… THE TRANSPORT PLANE was older and more rickety than she would have expected for one headed to the spaceport. Aisha peered out the window of the plane intently, waiting for her first glimpse of the great cable veering skyward from Kiritimati into the depths of space. It even had the old-school seats facing each other across a small table. A man sat there, and he was watching her closely. “It’s nothing really special,” he said. “You don’t see anything. It’s only interesting when a launch happens.” “How often?” she asked, knowing the answer already. She always knew the answer already, but she asked anyway. “It depends,” he said, looking at his watch. “We build the shuttle onsite and then launch it. It’s not worth bringing it back to Earth, where it would burn up in the atmosphere, so it’s designed to be launched once, and then disassembled into different things to be used up there.” He pointed at the sky. “I’m going up tomorrow,” she said. He nodded, smiling. “I figured. We get a lot of kids your age coming through here, heading for the Academy.” He smiled and went back to reading the news from his tablet. He hadn’t said anything about her color. Mother had insisted on telling everyone within earshot that Aisha was the first African-American to go to the Academy. And not only was she African-American, but she was also a girl. Aisha groaned inwardly. She wished mother would just stop. It had been a couple of hours since they had left Hawaii. The plane flew south to the tiny atoll that Aisha couldn’t take her eyes off of. Upon arrival, they would take the short trip out to the bottom of the cable, and the fleet of ships imaginatively called Terminus. That would be the last stop before she launched into orbit, leaving Earth behind. The man lowered his tablet and pointed to a silver dot on the horizon. “That’s a shuttle right there,” he said. “And if you look closely you can see the cable that makes up the Space Elevator.” Even the words sounded amazing to her. The Space Elevator. Since the invention of materials with the requisite strength in low enough density to make the concept buildable, many nations had gathered together to build this one. The idea was simple. Tether a cable on the Earth near the equator, and extend it out into space for about 35,000 kilometers. The object on the far end of the cable would then be in geostationary orbit, always above the same position on the Earth, much like communications or TV satellites. She peered, trying to make out the cable, but it was just too skinny to be seen from this distance – except for the occasional glint as the tropical sun reflected off it. Because the cable was tethered to the surface of the Earth, the rotation of the planet would send any object attached to the cable flying out from the center of gravity, propelling it into space. Once it reached the top of the cable, it could then launch itself outward, using a tiny fraction of the fuel that a traditional rocket launch would use up. Almost overnight, it revolutionized space travel. One of the first things the international community had agreed upon was to build an academy. Its goal: To teach a new generation of humans what it would be like to have a single, coherent community, not hindered by the tropes of the past. Ultimately, such a community would be the future of mankind, its backers had argued, and would put an end to the wars that nearly destroyed us all. Aisha opened her locket and looked at his face, trying to remember him. Ravaged by cancers from radiation suffered in war, her father died before she reached her first birthday. He smiled back at her from the tiny picture, and she could see the pride in his smile. I did it, Dad. I made it into space, and I made sure that you would never be forgotten. That the next phase of humanity will have a little part of you in it. That was worth fighting for. I just wish you didn’t have to die for it. The plane jolted as it began to descend, waking Mother. “Are we there yet?” Aisha smiled to herself. “We’re almost at the Terminus.” Mother smiled and looked at the man sitting across from Aisha. “She’s going to the Space Academy, you know,” she said, smiling. The man nodded. “You must be so proud.” “Oh, I am,” said Mother. “She’ll always be my little girl, but to be the first African-American, and one of the first girls up there, it’s so exciting.” “I’m sure,” said the man. “I think she’ll do amazing things.” “Aww, you’re so nice,” said Mother, milking the compliment for all it was worth. He said nothing and went back to reading. Irked, mother looked around for someone else to impress. The plane lurched again, so she closed her eyes instead, fighting back airsickness. Mother was never good at flying. Aisha turned back to the window, catching the man’s eye with his small smile. He nodded at her, and she returned the gesture. The ground rushed at them, and with a jolt, they landed on the small airstrip. Since the construction of the Space Elevator had begun, this tiny island had changed from being a rock in the middle of the ocean to a thriving miniature city. But land was at a premium, so all passenger transport still came through the tiny airstrip on the western side. Aisha had read that a new floating airport was under construction. When it opened, the island would be connected directly to the mainland of the USA and other countries, instead of needing a transport plane like this one flying out of Hawaii. As she got out of the plane, Aisha could feel the warm breeze and hear the crash of the surf. A rocky beach lay just to her right, within walking distance of the airstrip. Mother emerged, blinking in the bright light. A representative of the Academy greeted them and led them towards a small set of prefabricated buildings that served as the registration center. A tiny look of disappointment crossed Mother’s face. Aisha rolled her eyes. Mother was probably expecting more press to meet them here, presumably not having enough of them in Hawaii. The only cadet on the arriving flight, Aisha strolled after the greeter, calling for Mother to keep up. The warm humid air felt good in her lungs. For the next few years she would be breathing processed air in the space station, so she wanted to make the most of it. She wondered if there would be time for the beach. The administrative center was as plain on the inside as it was on the outside. A threadbare box, it housed several desks at which sat tired-looking administrators swiping through computer terminals. The greeter read Mother’s disappointed gaze. “Here’s where we just make sure you are whom you say you are before taking the boat across to the Elevator. It helps us make sure that people don’t sneak aboard.” Mother raised her eyebrows. “What kind of people sneak aboard? Terrorists? It doesn’t look like you could stop them!” The greeter smiled a little, and to Aisha, it looked practiced. “No terrorist could get within a thousand miles of this place. No, we’re more concerned about curious onlookers, too many relatives of cadets, that type of thing.” His words confused Aisha. How could a terrorist be stopped from getting here, when just about anybody could fly here, including too many family members? Was it all a front, or were they profiling everything about every person who even tried to come to this place? She held her tongue. If Mother thought there was any profiling going on, she’d launch into one of her rants. “I hear the hotel is very nice,” Aisha said, changing the subject. “Yes,” said the greeter. “We want your last night on planet Earth to be special.” “But she’ll be coming back, for vacations and the like,” said Mother. “So it’s hardly her last night.” “Of course,” said the greeter, smiling, before ushering them to a desk where the clerk had finally booted up his screen. “You’re our last flight of the day today,” he said cheerfully. “But don’t worry - you aren’t the only launchie. The others are at the Terminus ahead of you, so you’ll have plenty of friends for the ride up.” Aisha smiled. She didn’t need friends, but it was best not to argue. “Ah Miss Parks,” he continued, checking her credentials. “I heard you were coming today, it’s very nice to have you aboard.” “Thanks,” said Aisha. “But I just want to be like any other student.” “Yes,” he continued. “The media have made a big deal about it down here, but once you get up there, all that will be forgotten.” Mother piqued up. “What?” “We try to keep the kids insulated from political and social matters down on Earth,” he said in a trained voice. “That way they can focus on their work.” “But she is the first African-American to be accepted since open enrollment. Not only that, she’s one of the first girls. That makes her very important.” “Ma’am,” said the receptionist. “Your daughter is extremely important, and in time you’ll find it’s not for those reasons, but for who she is and what she’s capable of doing. Her race, her gender, those things don’t matter.” “But she is the first African-American–” The man interrupted, albeit politely. “Of course,” he said. “And the press at Terminus will want to ask you all about that.” *</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Famous $19 Apple Cleaning Cloth</title><link href="/2022/01/19/famouscloth.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Famous $19 Apple Cleaning Cloth" /><published>2022-01-19T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-01-19T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/2022/01/19/famouscloth</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2022/01/19/famouscloth.html">&lt;p&gt;So I took the plunge and bought one of the famous $19 Cleaning Cloths from Apple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This much maligned and lampooned cloth is actually quite nice. Let’s take a look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It arrives in letterbox packaging like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cloth1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cloth package&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apple makes great products, and they fully understand that the packaging is part of the experience. If you’ve ever spent time in Asia, it’s a very asian thing. Your moments of delight start right at the first glance and touch on the product. That’s what they’ve done here. It feels nice and sturdy. It has a pull tag at the bottom that’s labeled with a little green arrow that you can peel to open the package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You tear and unfold to see this. Simple. Elegant. Almost cute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cloth4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;First look at the cloth&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remove the cloth and you’ll see that the cloth is folded in half, and is roughly square in shape. It has a very nice embossed monogram.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cloth5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Monogram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a closer look at the monogram and the cloth itself. It’s much sturdier than I originally thought, and I can so see myself using this to clean my MacBook pro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cloth2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Monogram Closeup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now people might mock spending $19 on a cloth, and if it were just a cloth, I might agree. To be fair, it’s a super premium one, and instead of paying 10x what you should pay, it’s probably more like 2x.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kinda like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, the compatibility list online is definitely worth a little mockery!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find the cloth &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/shop/product/MM6F3AM/A/polishing-cloth&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; – and be sure to check the compatibility list to see if the cloth will work for you! For example, it won’t work on my 2011 iMac. But enquiring minds want to know – if I try to clean it with this cloth, will it break the cloth, or will it break the iMac???&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="life" /><category term="tech" /><summary type="html">So I took the plunge and bought one of the famous $19 Cleaning Cloths from Apple. This much maligned and lampooned cloth is actually quite nice. Let’s take a look. It arrives in letterbox packaging like this. Apple makes great products, and they fully understand that the packaging is part of the experience. If you’ve ever spent time in Asia, it’s a very asian thing. Your moments of delight start right at the first glance and touch on the product. That’s what they’ve done here. It feels nice and sturdy. It has a pull tag at the bottom that’s labeled with a little green arrow that you can peel to open the package. You tear and unfold to see this. Simple. Elegant. Almost cute. Remove the cloth and you’ll see that the cloth is folded in half, and is roughly square in shape. It has a very nice embossed monogram. Here’s a closer look at the monogram and the cloth itself. It’s much sturdier than I originally thought, and I can so see myself using this to clean my MacBook pro. Now people might mock spending $19 on a cloth, and if it were just a cloth, I might agree. To be fair, it’s a super premium one, and instead of paying 10x what you should pay, it’s probably more like 2x. I kinda like it. But, the compatibility list online is definitely worth a little mockery! You can find the cloth here – and be sure to check the compatibility list to see if the cloth will work for you! For example, it won’t work on my 2011 iMac. But enquiring minds want to know – if I try to clean it with this cloth, will it break the cloth, or will it break the iMac???</summary></entry></feed>