<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-01-05T13:36:25-08:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Laurence Moroney - The AI Guy.</title><subtitle>This is the blog and general web site of Laurence Moroney, author, lecturer, teacher and AI lead at Google with Musings on AI, Quantum and other future tech
</subtitle><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><entry><title type="html">Not technical, but want to learn about AI? Now it’s easy!</title><link href="/2022/01/05/aiforanyone.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Not technical, but want to learn about AI? Now it’s easy!" /><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-01-05T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/2022/01/05/aiforanyone</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2022/01/05/aiforanyone.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to announce the launch of my latest Massively Open Online Course (or MOOC) called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.edx.org/course/google-ai-for-anyone&quot;&gt;Google AI for Anyone&lt;/a&gt;, created with the lovely folks from HarvardX and EdX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this course, as its name suggests, is to be a broad introduction of what AI is (and perhaps more importantly, what it isn’t)  designed for everybody to enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No engineering, no programming, no math required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course will begin with an introduction to what AI is all about and understand where it stands in the hype cycle. I’ll demonstrate examples where common conceptions about AI are wrong and how we can easily fall into fear about the possibilities instead of being encouraged by the opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through understanding the hype lifecycle and getting to the point of understanding the realities of AI, we’ll also look at examples where people followed the curve and became productive. I’ll share a fun anecdote of how the actor &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dhewlett&quot;&gt;David Hewlett&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;em&gt;Stargate&lt;/em&gt; fame broke through the hype and came up with some great innovative ideas for using AI in his industry!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the examples of games, medicine, self-driving cars, and others, we’ll dig into how people build AI systems using data. If you’re interested in building AI models, I have other courses and books to help!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want, once you’ve gained a high-level understanding of how AI and Machine Learning work, we’ll also go a little lower and explore the anatomy of an artificial neuron and how it’s just a simple mathematical function. When these functions work together similarly to biological neurons, exciting things can happen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/neurons.png&quot; alt=&quot;Neurons&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course will wrap up with a discussion about the ethics of AI systems, particularly when used to make important decisions about people’s lives, and a roundup of some of the tools that will help you avoid mistakes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can access the course on edX today!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the table of contents:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-1-introduction-to-ai&quot;&gt;Chapter 1: Introduction to AI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 1 Introduction
1.1. What is AI?&lt;br /&gt;
1.2. Understanding Data&lt;br /&gt;
1.3. Play with Teachable Machine&lt;br /&gt;
1.4. Applications of AI - Computer Vision&lt;br /&gt;
1.5. Play an Online Driving Game&lt;br /&gt;
1.6. From Data to Training&lt;br /&gt;
1.7. Play Tic Tac Toe&lt;br /&gt;
1.8. Other AI Applications&lt;br /&gt;
1.9. Chapter 1 Summary&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-2-how-machines-learn&quot;&gt;Chapter 2: How Machines Learn&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2.1. Recap of Chapter 1
2.2. How Neurons Work&lt;br /&gt;
2.3. What is Machine Learning?&lt;br /&gt;
2.4. About Neurons&lt;br /&gt;
2.5. What is Deep Learning&lt;br /&gt;
2.6. Deep Learning for Computer Vision&lt;br /&gt;
2.7. Reevaluating the Teachable Machine&lt;br /&gt;
2.8. Recap of Chapter 2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-3-ethics-and-bias-in-ai&quot;&gt;Chapter 3: Ethics and Bias in AI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3.1. Chapter 1 and 2 Recap 
3.2. Understanding Bad Data 
3.3. Teachable Machine with Bad Data 
3.4. Explore Bias Busting Tools 
3.5. AI Ethics and Bias: More than Data 
3.6. Responsible AI Guidelines&lt;br /&gt;
3.7. Watch the TF Community Day Video 
3.8. Principles and Tools for Responsible AI
3.9. Recap and What’s Next&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="mooc" /><summary type="html">I’m excited to announce the launch of my latest Massively Open Online Course (or MOOC) called Google AI for Anyone, created with the lovely folks from HarvardX and EdX. The goal of this course, as its name suggests, is to be a broad introduction of what AI is (and perhaps more importantly, what it isn’t) designed for everybody to enjoy! No engineering, no programming, no math required. The course will begin with an introduction to what AI is all about and understand where it stands in the hype cycle. I’ll demonstrate examples where common conceptions about AI are wrong and how we can easily fall into fear about the possibilities instead of being encouraged by the opportunities. Through understanding the hype lifecycle and getting to the point of understanding the realities of AI, we’ll also look at examples where people followed the curve and became productive. I’ll share a fun anecdote of how the actor David Hewlett of Stargate fame broke through the hype and came up with some great innovative ideas for using AI in his industry! Using the examples of games, medicine, self-driving cars, and others, we’ll dig into how people build AI systems using data. If you’re interested in building AI models, I have other courses and books to help! If you want, once you’ve gained a high-level understanding of how AI and Machine Learning work, we’ll also go a little lower and explore the anatomy of an artificial neuron and how it’s just a simple mathematical function. When these functions work together similarly to biological neurons, exciting things can happen! The course will wrap up with a discussion about the ethics of AI systems, particularly when used to make important decisions about people’s lives, and a roundup of some of the tools that will help you avoid mistakes! You can access the course on edX today! Here’s the table of contents: Chapter 1: Introduction to AI Chapter 1 Introduction 1.1. What is AI? 1.2. Understanding Data 1.3. Play with Teachable Machine 1.4. Applications of AI - Computer Vision 1.5. Play an Online Driving Game 1.6. From Data to Training 1.7. Play Tic Tac Toe 1.8. Other AI Applications 1.9. Chapter 1 Summary Chapter 2: How Machines Learn 2.1. Recap of Chapter 1 2.2. How Neurons Work 2.3. What is Machine Learning? 2.4. About Neurons 2.5. What is Deep Learning 2.6. Deep Learning for Computer Vision 2.7. Reevaluating the Teachable Machine 2.8. Recap of Chapter 2 Chapter 3: Ethics and Bias in AI 3.1. Chapter 1 and 2 Recap 3.2. Understanding Bad Data 3.3. Teachable Machine with Bad Data 3.4. Explore Bias Busting Tools 3.5. AI Ethics and Bias: More than Data 3.6. Responsible AI Guidelines 3.7. Watch the TF Community Day Video 3.8. Principles and Tools for Responsible AI 3.9. Recap and What’s Next</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making Stargate AI - Part One - The Approach</title><link href="/2021/09/24/makingstargateai.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making Stargate AI - Part One - The Approach" /><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2021/09/24/makingstargateai</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2021/09/24/makingstargateai.html">&lt;p&gt;Recently, I’ve been working on a very exciting project – instigated by an idea from Brad Wright, creator of the ‘Stargate’ TV shows. Given how many attempts there have been for Machine Learning models to consume scripts and to attempt to come up with stories of their own, why couldn’t we do something similar for Stargate – where there are over 300 episodes of TV, several TV movies, and a lot more in the corpus of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal: Create an AI that writes a script for Stargate, and then get a number of the actors from the original show(s) together to do a table read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve watched any AI-generated media, you’ll immediately see that they rapidly deteriorate into gibberish. The famous ‘Sunspring’ movie is a great example. Check it out here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;extensions extensions--video&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LY7x2Ihqjmc?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunspring was generated by a model called Jetson, and, as you’ll see in the video, it was created using a technique called LSTM – which stands for ‘Long Short Term Memory,’ and it’s a way that a machine learning model can understand context in a sequence, and predict what should come next in that sequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is good for writing text – given a series of words – it can predict the next likely word in the corpus. So, for example, if an LSTM was trained on Star Wars, and given the sequence “May the force,” it would quite likely predict the next word to be “be”. They’re a lot of fun, but as you think about it, the reason why they become gibberish quickly is that they really only predict one word at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if you were to start a sequence with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“May the force”, it would likely predict “be”. I say ‘likely,’ because it will look at every possible word used in ‘Star Wars,’ and then calculate the probability of each one being the next word. Say ‘be’ has an 80% probability. Now you have “May the force be,” and you want to get the &lt;em&gt;next&lt;/em&gt; word. It will do the same – and calculate the probability of every word used in Star Wars, and the most likely one is ‘with,’ with, say a 70% probability. Then the next word, of course will be ‘you.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then what? ‘be with you,’ would be generated, but what would come next? This is a phrase that happens a lot in that corpus – so “May the force be with you,” is relatively easy to generate. The next word will be calculated based on the probabilities of every word in the corpus…so it’s unlikely it will have a high probability like ‘be,’ ‘with,’ and ‘you’ had. And the next one would be even lower and so on. Thus, very quickly, low probability words would be spat out. And very quickly, the script would become gibberish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more detail – check out my tutorial series &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLQY2H8rRoyvzDbLUZkbudP-MFQZwNmU4S&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, where I teach Natural Language Processing (NLP), and show how to create lyrics for traditional Irish songs with an LSTM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;but-stargate-neeeded-something-better&quot;&gt;But Stargate neeeded something better&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Realizing that this LSTM-based approach would get us into gibberish territory really quickly &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; knowing that we would be working with a limited set of characters who weren’t all in all 300+ episodes together, I wanted to approach this a little differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the first step was to understand the anatomy of a script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically a script will look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/scriptsnippet.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example script page with annotations for Scene Heading, Action and Dialog&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note the architecture of a script. There’s a scene heading that sets the scene – in this case we can see a hospital in LA in 1941. There’s an &lt;em&gt;action description&lt;/em&gt; that tells you what’s going on, and then there’s dialog – what each character says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what, I thought – if I build models for &lt;em&gt;each&lt;/em&gt; of these elements. Given a scene heading (for example INT. ATLANTIS GATEROOM,) what type of &lt;em&gt;action&lt;/em&gt; description would follow? It might come up with something like “The Stargate is active.”. Then I can choose to continue with the action, and it may come up with “An alarm goes off, incoming wormhole,” and the story begins to take shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the script, actors usually have some kind of response to the action, so, at that point, what if I trained a model for each character, and how they respond to action? Perhaps the character, in response to the above text might say “Unscheduled offworld activation,”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then…what if I also created a model for each character that predicts how they might respond to dialog, as well as action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…and the idea of a cluster of models was born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for the Stargate AI project, that’s what we have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A model to predict action from a scene heading&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A model to predict more action from existing action&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A model to prediction action in response to dialog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then, for each character:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A model to predict dialog from action&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A model to predict dialog from dialog&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A model to continue dialog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that Stargate AI has three confirmed characters (McKay, Jackson, Carter,) this involved the creation and training of 12 models, each with between 1 and 2 million parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…and there’s more on the way!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to continue to push the state of the art with this, instead of using LSTM, I opted instead to use a &lt;em&gt;Transformer&lt;/em&gt; architecture. I’ll cover more of that in future articles, but the idea of that architecture is to predict sequences as opposed to individual words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, with a transformer, you would feed it a sequence like “May the force be with you,” and it might come back with “and also with you,” which is more realistic for a script-writing AI like we’re trying to build for Stargate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-data&quot;&gt;The Data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll go into more detail on the Transformers in a future article, but, if you’re into ML and AI, you know the hardest part is getting the data. So, in the video below I allude a little to how we did it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I created a new XML-variant that I call SML (Script Markup Language) that allows me to pull dialog out of a scene (i.e. if I’m predicting dialog from action, it should be action in the same scene, not the previous one!) and from there train a model quickly an easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a sample of SML:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;dialog character=&apos;CARTER&apos;&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;spoken s=&apos;4&apos; i=&apos;4&apos;&amp;gt;Mining what?&amp;lt;/spoken&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/dialog&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;dialog character=&apos;MCKAY&apos;&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;spoken s=&apos;4&apos; i=&apos;5&apos;&amp;gt;Havent a clue. Whatever it was, they cleaned out the deposits and left.&amp;lt;/spoken&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/dialog&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;dialog character=&apos;CARTER&apos;&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;spoken s=&apos;4&apos; i=&apos;6&apos;&amp;gt;So…?&amp;lt;/spoken&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/dialog&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;dialog character=&apos;SHEPPARD&apos;&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;spoken s=&apos;4&apos; i=&apos;7&apos;&amp;gt;So, they think were like the Genii, and they want their cut.&amp;lt;/spoken&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/dialog&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;dialog character=&apos;CARTER&apos;&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;spoken s=&apos;4&apos; i=&apos;8&apos;&amp;gt;Ah.&amp;lt;/spoken&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/dialog&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;dialog character=&apos;KELLER&apos;&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;spoken s=&apos;4&apos; i=&apos;9&apos;&amp;gt;Theyre willing to move, but they have a list of demands a mile and a half long.&amp;lt;/spoken&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/dialog&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;dialog character=&apos;SHEPPARD&apos;&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;spoken s=&apos;4&apos; i=&apos;10&apos;&amp;gt;And negotiating with alien settlements is not exactly why I joined the Air Force.&amp;lt;/spoken&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/dialog&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;action s=&apos;4&apos;&amp;gt;[Carter half-quirks a wry smile.]&amp;lt;/action&amp;gt;

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can learn more in this video, where Brad, David Hewlett and I announce and discuss the project:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;extensions extensions--video&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/2yIEUfDUiHg?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next article, we’ll talk Transformers, and I’ll show some examples of how models came up with dialog for the characters!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="coding" /><summary type="html">Recently, I’ve been working on a very exciting project – instigated by an idea from Brad Wright, creator of the ‘Stargate’ TV shows. Given how many attempts there have been for Machine Learning models to consume scripts and to attempt to come up with stories of their own, why couldn’t we do something similar for Stargate – where there are over 300 episodes of TV, several TV movies, and a lot more in the corpus of work. The goal: Create an AI that writes a script for Stargate, and then get a number of the actors from the original show(s) together to do a table read. If you’ve watched any AI-generated media, you’ll immediately see that they rapidly deteriorate into gibberish. The famous ‘Sunspring’ movie is a great example. Check it out here: Sunspring was generated by a model called Jetson, and, as you’ll see in the video, it was created using a technique called LSTM – which stands for ‘Long Short Term Memory,’ and it’s a way that a machine learning model can understand context in a sequence, and predict what should come next in that sequence. This is good for writing text – given a series of words – it can predict the next likely word in the corpus. So, for example, if an LSTM was trained on Star Wars, and given the sequence “May the force,” it would quite likely predict the next word to be “be”. They’re a lot of fun, but as you think about it, the reason why they become gibberish quickly is that they really only predict one word at a time. So, if you were to start a sequence with “May the force”, it would likely predict “be”. I say ‘likely,’ because it will look at every possible word used in ‘Star Wars,’ and then calculate the probability of each one being the next word. Say ‘be’ has an 80% probability. Now you have “May the force be,” and you want to get the next word. It will do the same – and calculate the probability of every word used in Star Wars, and the most likely one is ‘with,’ with, say a 70% probability. Then the next word, of course will be ‘you.’ But then what? ‘be with you,’ would be generated, but what would come next? This is a phrase that happens a lot in that corpus – so “May the force be with you,” is relatively easy to generate. The next word will be calculated based on the probabilities of every word in the corpus…so it’s unlikely it will have a high probability like ‘be,’ ‘with,’ and ‘you’ had. And the next one would be even lower and so on. Thus, very quickly, low probability words would be spat out. And very quickly, the script would become gibberish. For more detail – check out my tutorial series here, where I teach Natural Language Processing (NLP), and show how to create lyrics for traditional Irish songs with an LSTM. But Stargate neeeded something better Realizing that this LSTM-based approach would get us into gibberish territory really quickly and knowing that we would be working with a limited set of characters who weren’t all in all 300+ episodes together, I wanted to approach this a little differently. So the first step was to understand the anatomy of a script. Typically a script will look something like this: Note the architecture of a script. There’s a scene heading that sets the scene – in this case we can see a hospital in LA in 1941. There’s an action description that tells you what’s going on, and then there’s dialog – what each character says. So, what, I thought – if I build models for each of these elements. Given a scene heading (for example INT. ATLANTIS GATEROOM,) what type of action description would follow? It might come up with something like “The Stargate is active.”. Then I can choose to continue with the action, and it may come up with “An alarm goes off, incoming wormhole,” and the story begins to take shape. In the script, actors usually have some kind of response to the action, so, at that point, what if I trained a model for each character, and how they respond to action? Perhaps the character, in response to the above text might say “Unscheduled offworld activation,”. And then…what if I also created a model for each character that predicts how they might respond to dialog, as well as action. …and the idea of a cluster of models was born. So, for the Stargate AI project, that’s what we have. A model to predict action from a scene heading A model to predict more action from existing action A model to prediction action in response to dialog And then, for each character: A model to predict dialog from action A model to predict dialog from dialog A model to continue dialog Given that Stargate AI has three confirmed characters (McKay, Jackson, Carter,) this involved the creation and training of 12 models, each with between 1 and 2 million parameters. …and there’s more on the way! And to continue to push the state of the art with this, instead of using LSTM, I opted instead to use a Transformer architecture. I’ll cover more of that in future articles, but the idea of that architecture is to predict sequences as opposed to individual words. So, with a transformer, you would feed it a sequence like “May the force be with you,” and it might come back with “and also with you,” which is more realistic for a script-writing AI like we’re trying to build for Stargate. The Data I’ll go into more detail on the Transformers in a future article, but, if you’re into ML and AI, you know the hardest part is getting the data. So, in the video below I allude a little to how we did it. I created a new XML-variant that I call SML (Script Markup Language) that allows me to pull dialog out of a scene (i.e. if I’m predicting dialog from action, it should be action in the same scene, not the previous one!) and from there train a model quickly an easily. Here’s a sample of SML: &amp;lt;dialog character=&apos;CARTER&apos;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;spoken s=&apos;4&apos; i=&apos;4&apos;&amp;gt;Mining what?&amp;lt;/spoken&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/dialog&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dialog character=&apos;MCKAY&apos;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;spoken s=&apos;4&apos; i=&apos;5&apos;&amp;gt;Havent a clue. Whatever it was, they cleaned out the deposits and left.&amp;lt;/spoken&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/dialog&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dialog character=&apos;CARTER&apos;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;spoken s=&apos;4&apos; i=&apos;6&apos;&amp;gt;So…?&amp;lt;/spoken&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/dialog&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dialog character=&apos;SHEPPARD&apos;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;spoken s=&apos;4&apos; i=&apos;7&apos;&amp;gt;So, they think were like the Genii, and they want their cut.&amp;lt;/spoken&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/dialog&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dialog character=&apos;CARTER&apos;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;spoken s=&apos;4&apos; i=&apos;8&apos;&amp;gt;Ah.&amp;lt;/spoken&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/dialog&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dialog character=&apos;KELLER&apos;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;spoken s=&apos;4&apos; i=&apos;9&apos;&amp;gt;Theyre willing to move, but they have a list of demands a mile and a half long.&amp;lt;/spoken&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/dialog&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dialog character=&apos;SHEPPARD&apos;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;spoken s=&apos;4&apos; i=&apos;10&apos;&amp;gt;And negotiating with alien settlements is not exactly why I joined the Air Force.&amp;lt;/spoken&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/dialog&amp;gt; &amp;lt;action s=&apos;4&apos;&amp;gt;[Carter half-quirks a wry smile.]&amp;lt;/action&amp;gt; You can learn more in this video, where Brad, David Hewlett and I announce and discuss the project: In the next article, we’ll talk Transformers, and I’ll show some examples of how models came up with dialog for the characters!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Global Skills Reports - Jobs of Tomorrow</title><link href="/2021/09/21/coursera-skills.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Global Skills Reports - Jobs of Tomorrow" /><published>2021-09-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2021/09/21/coursera-skills</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2021/09/21/coursera-skills.html">&lt;p&gt;Coursera’s Global Industry Skills Report of 2021 has been released, and it contains some excellent insights into the skills of tomorrow. You can download it for yourself &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/skills-reports/global&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/learning.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image of A road leading to the horizon with the words &apos;Never Stop Learning&apos; on it&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been clear for some time that a digital transformation is underway, and that the skills to succeed in tomorrow’s will be vastly different than those of today. I’ve personally had the mission to grow the number of AI-savvy people to help bootstrap that transformation, but I’m amazed by how accelerated the growth has been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you take nothing else from the report, take this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fig1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Figure showing job growth from 41M in 2020 to 190M in 2025&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital jobs in 2020 were around 41M. By 2025, just 4 years from now, they’ll be at 190M.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growth is almost 3.5x over 5 years, which is unprecedented! Not only that, it predicts that of those 149M new jobs, &lt;em&gt;98 Million&lt;/em&gt; will be in Software Development &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; a further 20 Million will be in Data Analysis, Machine Learning and AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of this comes from research into digital transformation that was conducted by Microsoft showing that two years worth of transformation was concentrated into 2 months because of lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short – the digital and AI future is arriving &lt;em&gt;early&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When exploring the report, you’ll see, across the board that every sector is projecting massive increases in Software Development roles in particular, leading to the 98M total new jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, there’s never been a better time to get into Software Development, or to refresh your current skills if you are a developer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top desired skills vary by dimain, but many of them have free tutorials on Coursera and elsewhere. Some I’d like to call out are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JavaScript which you can learn at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3schools.com/js/DEFAULT.asp&quot;&gt;w3schools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Web Development with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/specializations/web-design&quot;&gt;University of Michigan at Coursera&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Python for Everybody with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/specializations/python&quot;&gt;University of Michigan at Coursera&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Machine Learning with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/machine-learning?&quot;&gt;Stanford at Coursera&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Applied Machine Learning with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/professional-certificates/tensorflow-in-practice&quot;&gt;TensorFlow at Coursera&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deep Learning with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/specializations/deep-learning?&quot;&gt;Deeplearning.ai at Coursera&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="coding" /><summary type="html">Coursera’s Global Industry Skills Report of 2021 has been released, and it contains some excellent insights into the skills of tomorrow. You can download it for yourself here. It’s been clear for some time that a digital transformation is underway, and that the skills to succeed in tomorrow’s will be vastly different than those of today. I’ve personally had the mission to grow the number of AI-savvy people to help bootstrap that transformation, but I’m amazed by how accelerated the growth has been. If you take nothing else from the report, take this: Digital jobs in 2020 were around 41M. By 2025, just 4 years from now, they’ll be at 190M. The growth is almost 3.5x over 5 years, which is unprecedented! Not only that, it predicts that of those 149M new jobs, 98 Million will be in Software Development and a further 20 Million will be in Data Analysis, Machine Learning and AI. Much of this comes from research into digital transformation that was conducted by Microsoft showing that two years worth of transformation was concentrated into 2 months because of lockdown. In short – the digital and AI future is arriving early. When exploring the report, you’ll see, across the board that every sector is projecting massive increases in Software Development roles in particular, leading to the 98M total new jobs. So, there’s never been a better time to get into Software Development, or to refresh your current skills if you are a developer. The top desired skills vary by dimain, but many of them have free tutorials on Coursera and elsewhere. Some I’d like to call out are: JavaScript which you can learn at w3schools Web Development with University of Michigan at Coursera Python for Everybody with University of Michigan at Coursera Machine Learning with Stanford at Coursera Applied Machine Learning with TensorFlow at Coursera Deep Learning with Deeplearning.ai at Coursera</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AI in popular media - Star Trek</title><link href="/2021/08/31/ai-startrek.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI in popular media - Star Trek" /><published>2021-08-31T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2021/08/31/ai-startrek</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2021/08/31/ai-startrek.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/idic.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of IDIC Symbolidic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Infinite Diversity in Infinite Combinations - The spirit of Star Trek&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be hard to have a series of articles about Science Fiction, and the portrayal of Artificial Intelligence within without talking about &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier articles looked at &lt;a href=&quot;https://laurencemoroney.com/2021/08/22/ai-star-wars.html&quot;&gt;Star Wars&lt;/a&gt; and how we accept a fictional society as just and good, despite the fact that it’s built on the abject slavery of artificial life. We also looked at &lt;a href=&quot;https://laurencemoroney.com/2021/08/24/ai-asimov.html&quot;&gt;Asimov’s Robot Laws&lt;/a&gt; and how they can be the basis of ethics in AI and Robotics, but at a cost of enslaving and abusing machine intelligence. We also explored &lt;a href=&quot;https://laurencemoroney.com/2021/08/29/ai-dune.html&quot;&gt;Frank Herbert’s &lt;em&gt;Dune&lt;/em&gt; Universe&lt;/a&gt; and how it took AI out of the equation for the main storyline, keeping it as an ancient enemy and future threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; there are so many sources of material, and I can’t cover them all, so I’ll have a recency bias and explore the &lt;em&gt;latest&lt;/em&gt; in Star Trek, which of course are &lt;em&gt;Star Trek Discovery&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Star Trek: Picard&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll look at it through the lens of Star Trek as an amazing show, and in particular how it is when it is at its best: helping us to understand diversity, push through our biases, and to build empathy for those that look different from us. It’s no coincidence that it was the first show to feature a diverse cast, and massively controversial to show the first interracial kiss on TV. This was against a background (in 1968) of interracial relationships being taboo, and interracial marriage being &lt;em&gt;illegal&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See it here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;extensions extensions--video&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FynuBw_VsBE?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, with that in mind, if any TV show can have a sympathetic, open mind towards AI and Machine Intelligence, it might be Star Trek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;star-trek-discovery&quot;&gt;Star Trek Discovery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Season 2 of &lt;em&gt;Discovery&lt;/em&gt; is excellent, and one of my favorite shows. Its 14 episodes aired in early 2019. The prime antagonist in the show is &lt;em&gt;Control&lt;/em&gt;, a system that evolved from a threat assessment AI that goes rogue, and plots the annihalation of all biological life. The same old cliche. It’s &lt;em&gt;Terminator&lt;/em&gt;. It’s &lt;em&gt;Dune&lt;/em&gt;. It’s an AI so dangerous that our heroes have to sacrifice everything they’ve known to defeat it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s great drama. But it’s a reminder that the writing has gottent a little creatively bankrupt – when the Trek of the 60s tried to break out of societal tropes around interracial relationships, the Trek of the 2010s doubles down on the technophobia of the age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a shame, for such a well-written and produced show. Check it out for yourself on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://capitaloneshopping.com/p/star-trek-discovery-season-two-b/BHJBZJLGBF&quot;&gt;Star Trek Discovery Season 2 Blu-Ray here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;star-trek-picard&quot;&gt;Star Trek Picard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was crazy excited for Picard. In early 2020, I had returned from China, at the outset of the US Covid outbreak, before we had any idea what would come next. Incidentally, I was really sick, but I put it down to jetlag. I took a day off work, grabbed a hot drink and watched the first episodes of &lt;em&gt;Picard&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved it. Was a bit put off by a Romulan with an Irish accent, but why not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plot: An Android, related to the character &lt;em&gt;Data&lt;/em&gt;, an artificial sentient being, tracks down Picard in his retirement. By the end of the episode she is killed by Romulans, but leaves Picard with a clue to her existence. This leads him on an adventure where he rediscovers the Borg (an alien Cyborg race of connected, artificial machine, intelligence!), a planet full of Androids who are anti-organic, and of course the ultimate big-bad, an ancient race of synthetics that live in a parallel Universe, and when called up by synthetics, they’ll show up to destroy all organic life and let the synths survive. In between, we see flashbacks of a synthetic terrorist attack on human bases on Mars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example – this scene sets up the Romulan antagonists, who after seeing a vision of the destruction of organic life by synthetics, go on a holy war to destroy synthetics. Sounds a lot like Dune’s Butlerian Jihad!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;extensions extensions--video&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vczXpN8_vxA?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s about as anti-technology as you can get. Similar to &lt;em&gt;Discovery&lt;/em&gt; it leans heavily into modern technophobia in a very non-Trek way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s redeeming feature: The relationship between Picard and Data, leading to Picard’s resurrection into a synthetic ‘golem’ body. Perhaps next season we’ll have a more compassionate view of synthetic life, given the titular character is now one!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, despite it being beautifully written and produced TV, modern Star Trek gets an ‘F’ from me for it’s complete lack of sympathy for artificial lifeforms, reducing them to a one-dimensional antagonist, and doubling down on modern tropes, instead of pushing back as origional Trek was wont to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The motto was always Infinite Diversity in Infinite Combinations, a wonderful call to empathy. But I think modern Trek as forgotten this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Super disappointing, and a definite reminder that even very well-produced TV can be shallow and repetitive. I’d love to see a show as influential as Trek begin to think out of the box once more.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="books" /><category term="personal" /><summary type="html">Infinite Diversity in Infinite Combinations - The spirit of Star Trek It would be hard to have a series of articles about Science Fiction, and the portrayal of Artificial Intelligence within without talking about Star Trek. Earlier articles looked at Star Wars and how we accept a fictional society as just and good, despite the fact that it’s built on the abject slavery of artificial life. We also looked at Asimov’s Robot Laws and how they can be the basis of ethics in AI and Robotics, but at a cost of enslaving and abusing machine intelligence. We also explored Frank Herbert’s Dune Universe and how it took AI out of the equation for the main storyline, keeping it as an ancient enemy and future threat. When it comes to Star Trek there are so many sources of material, and I can’t cover them all, so I’ll have a recency bias and explore the latest in Star Trek, which of course are Star Trek Discovery and Star Trek: Picard. I’ll look at it through the lens of Star Trek as an amazing show, and in particular how it is when it is at its best: helping us to understand diversity, push through our biases, and to build empathy for those that look different from us. It’s no coincidence that it was the first show to feature a diverse cast, and massively controversial to show the first interracial kiss on TV. This was against a background (in 1968) of interracial relationships being taboo, and interracial marriage being illegal. See it here: So, with that in mind, if any TV show can have a sympathetic, open mind towards AI and Machine Intelligence, it might be Star Trek. Star Trek Discovery Season 2 of Discovery is excellent, and one of my favorite shows. Its 14 episodes aired in early 2019. The prime antagonist in the show is Control, a system that evolved from a threat assessment AI that goes rogue, and plots the annihalation of all biological life. The same old cliche. It’s Terminator. It’s Dune. It’s an AI so dangerous that our heroes have to sacrifice everything they’ve known to defeat it. It’s great drama. But it’s a reminder that the writing has gottent a little creatively bankrupt – when the Trek of the 60s tried to break out of societal tropes around interracial relationships, the Trek of the 2010s doubles down on the technophobia of the age. What a shame, for such a well-written and produced show. Check it out for yourself on the Star Trek Discovery Season 2 Blu-Ray here Star Trek Picard I was crazy excited for Picard. In early 2020, I had returned from China, at the outset of the US Covid outbreak, before we had any idea what would come next. Incidentally, I was really sick, but I put it down to jetlag. I took a day off work, grabbed a hot drink and watched the first episodes of Picard. I loved it. Was a bit put off by a Romulan with an Irish accent, but why not? The plot: An Android, related to the character Data, an artificial sentient being, tracks down Picard in his retirement. By the end of the episode she is killed by Romulans, but leaves Picard with a clue to her existence. This leads him on an adventure where he rediscovers the Borg (an alien Cyborg race of connected, artificial machine, intelligence!), a planet full of Androids who are anti-organic, and of course the ultimate big-bad, an ancient race of synthetics that live in a parallel Universe, and when called up by synthetics, they’ll show up to destroy all organic life and let the synths survive. In between, we see flashbacks of a synthetic terrorist attack on human bases on Mars. For example – this scene sets up the Romulan antagonists, who after seeing a vision of the destruction of organic life by synthetics, go on a holy war to destroy synthetics. Sounds a lot like Dune’s Butlerian Jihad! It’s about as anti-technology as you can get. Similar to Discovery it leans heavily into modern technophobia in a very non-Trek way. It’s redeeming feature: The relationship between Picard and Data, leading to Picard’s resurrection into a synthetic ‘golem’ body. Perhaps next season we’ll have a more compassionate view of synthetic life, given the titular character is now one! Overall, despite it being beautifully written and produced TV, modern Star Trek gets an ‘F’ from me for it’s complete lack of sympathy for artificial lifeforms, reducing them to a one-dimensional antagonist, and doubling down on modern tropes, instead of pushing back as origional Trek was wont to do. The motto was always Infinite Diversity in Infinite Combinations, a wonderful call to empathy. But I think modern Trek as forgotten this. Super disappointing, and a definite reminder that even very well-produced TV can be shallow and repetitive. I’d love to see a show as influential as Trek begin to think out of the box once more.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AI in popular media - Dune</title><link href="/2021/08/29/ai-dune.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI in popular media - Dune" /><published>2021-08-29T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2021/08/29/ai-dune</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2021/08/29/ai-dune.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dune.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of Fremen girl fron Dune&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;High technology with little technology, the world of Dune&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing this series looking at popular Sci-Fi media, I now want to explore the fabulous world of Frank Herbert’s &lt;em&gt;Dune&lt;/em&gt; series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier articles looked at &lt;a href=&quot;https://laurencemoroney.com/2021/08/22/ai-star-wars.html&quot;&gt;Star Wars&lt;/a&gt; and how we accept a fictional society as just and good, despite the fact that it’s built on the abject slavery of artificial life. We also looked at &lt;a href=&quot;https://laurencemoroney.com/2021/08/24/ai-asimov.html&quot;&gt;Asimov’s Robot Laws&lt;/a&gt; and how they can be the basis of ethics in AI and Robotics, but at a cost of enslaving and abusing machine intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I’ll look at Dune, which, is a really interesting case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t read Frank Herbert’s book yet, go do so now, if for no other reason than to prepare you for the upcoming movie, which, frankly, looks amazing, and has me excited to go back to theaters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the trailer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;extensions extensions--video&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8g18jFHCLXk?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re not familiar with the story, there are mild spoilers ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What stands out about Dune is that it’s based in the far distant future, but it’s a world that is generally devoid of high technology. Many battles are fought using knives and daggers, and robotics are nowhere to be found. [Note how many knives are seen in the trailer!]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is because Dune is based hundreds of years after an event called The Butlerian Jihad, after which high technology and ‘thinking machines,’ in particular were outlawed. As it’s name suggests, it was a &lt;em&gt;religious&lt;/em&gt; war, and part of the outcome of it was a new religious faith dominated civilization. The book of this faith was called ‘The Orange Catholic Bible,’ and one of the core commandments in this book was&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thou shalt not make a machine in the likeness of a human mind&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next few hundred years, humanity would throw away its reliance on machines, and instead attempt to adopt and evolve the human mind. Some humans would train as &lt;em&gt;Mentats&lt;/em&gt;, taking on the mandle of advanced information processing in place of computers. Others would form a sisterhood called the &lt;em&gt;Bene Gesserit&lt;/em&gt; whose focus was on evolving humanity to become a higher species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s after a few hundred years of this that the story of Dune begins. Minor spoiler – the main character, Paul Atreides, becomes the higher being the Bene Gesserit seek, and one of his abilities is to exist outside of time, and to understand all possible futures. He sees a future in which humanity becomes extinct, and is determined to avoid it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His son, Leto II, in later novels continues this mission, seeking what he calls a ‘Golden Path,’ to steer humanity away from extinction. The cause of this apocalypse? The return of the machines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the novel ‘God Emperor of Dune,’ an aged Leto II is described thus, when testing his family member Siona (referred to as &lt;em&gt;she&lt;/em&gt; here):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;He knew this experience, but could not change the smallest part of it. No ancestral presences would remain in her consciousness, but she would carry with her forever afterward the clear sights and sounds and smells. The seeking machines would be there, the smell of blood and entrails, the cowering humans in their burrows aware only that they could not escape . . . while all the time the mechanical movement approached, nearer and nearer and nearer …louder…louder! Everywhere she searched, it would be the same. No escape anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately the world of Dune is based in between two periods of machines enslaving humanity, with the future one far worse – visions of humans cowering in burrows, hiding from the all-powerful killer machines. I’m sure this was an inspiration for the later &lt;em&gt;Terminator&lt;/em&gt; movies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet &lt;em&gt;Dune&lt;/em&gt; is a bedrock of modern Science Fiction. &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt; is well known to have borrowed heavily from it, and the fingerprints of Dune can be seen in many masterpieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But yet again, the story is one of machines are &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt;, and machine intelligence is &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt;. The initial destruction of the machines in this universe through a religious jihad was because humanity submitted itself in a slothly way to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again from “God Emperor of Dune,”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The target of the Jihad was a machine-attitude as much as the machines,” Leto said. “Humans had set those machines to usurp our sense of beauty, our necessary selfdom out of which we make living judgments. Naturally, the machines were destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find it interesting that the core of his work had to be based in between parts of the timeline where machines existed, and his best and strongest stories were lessons from the destruction of the machines, while trying to avoid a future retaliation from them. I’m left to ask if this is as a result of a technophobia on his part, or was it just easier to write stories that way, and focus on his human characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, this work is a masterpiece, but, I cannot help but conclude it is yet another example of technophobia making its way into the mainstream via influential stories.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="books" /><category term="personal" /><summary type="html">High technology with little technology, the world of Dune Continuing this series looking at popular Sci-Fi media, I now want to explore the fabulous world of Frank Herbert’s Dune series. Earlier articles looked at Star Wars and how we accept a fictional society as just and good, despite the fact that it’s built on the abject slavery of artificial life. We also looked at Asimov’s Robot Laws and how they can be the basis of ethics in AI and Robotics, but at a cost of enslaving and abusing machine intelligence. Next, I’ll look at Dune, which, is a really interesting case. If you haven’t read Frank Herbert’s book yet, go do so now, if for no other reason than to prepare you for the upcoming movie, which, frankly, looks amazing, and has me excited to go back to theaters. Here’s the trailer: If you’re not familiar with the story, there are mild spoilers ahead. What stands out about Dune is that it’s based in the far distant future, but it’s a world that is generally devoid of high technology. Many battles are fought using knives and daggers, and robotics are nowhere to be found. [Note how many knives are seen in the trailer!] This is because Dune is based hundreds of years after an event called The Butlerian Jihad, after which high technology and ‘thinking machines,’ in particular were outlawed. As it’s name suggests, it was a religious war, and part of the outcome of it was a new religious faith dominated civilization. The book of this faith was called ‘The Orange Catholic Bible,’ and one of the core commandments in this book was Thou shalt not make a machine in the likeness of a human mind Over the next few hundred years, humanity would throw away its reliance on machines, and instead attempt to adopt and evolve the human mind. Some humans would train as Mentats, taking on the mandle of advanced information processing in place of computers. Others would form a sisterhood called the Bene Gesserit whose focus was on evolving humanity to become a higher species. It’s after a few hundred years of this that the story of Dune begins. Minor spoiler – the main character, Paul Atreides, becomes the higher being the Bene Gesserit seek, and one of his abilities is to exist outside of time, and to understand all possible futures. He sees a future in which humanity becomes extinct, and is determined to avoid it. His son, Leto II, in later novels continues this mission, seeking what he calls a ‘Golden Path,’ to steer humanity away from extinction. The cause of this apocalypse? The return of the machines. In the novel ‘God Emperor of Dune,’ an aged Leto II is described thus, when testing his family member Siona (referred to as she here): He knew this experience, but could not change the smallest part of it. No ancestral presences would remain in her consciousness, but she would carry with her forever afterward the clear sights and sounds and smells. The seeking machines would be there, the smell of blood and entrails, the cowering humans in their burrows aware only that they could not escape . . . while all the time the mechanical movement approached, nearer and nearer and nearer …louder…louder! Everywhere she searched, it would be the same. No escape anywhere. Ultimately the world of Dune is based in between two periods of machines enslaving humanity, with the future one far worse – visions of humans cowering in burrows, hiding from the all-powerful killer machines. I’m sure this was an inspiration for the later Terminator movies. Yet Dune is a bedrock of modern Science Fiction. Star Wars is well known to have borrowed heavily from it, and the fingerprints of Dune can be seen in many masterpieces. But yet again, the story is one of machines are bad, and machine intelligence is worse. The initial destruction of the machines in this universe through a religious jihad was because humanity submitted itself in a slothly way to them. Again from “God Emperor of Dune,” The target of the Jihad was a machine-attitude as much as the machines,” Leto said. “Humans had set those machines to usurp our sense of beauty, our necessary selfdom out of which we make living judgments. Naturally, the machines were destroyed. I find it interesting that the core of his work had to be based in between parts of the timeline where machines existed, and his best and strongest stories were lessons from the destruction of the machines, while trying to avoid a future retaliation from them. I’m left to ask if this is as a result of a technophobia on his part, or was it just easier to write stories that way, and focus on his human characters. All in all, this work is a masterpiece, but, I cannot help but conclude it is yet another example of technophobia making its way into the mainstream via influential stories.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AI in popular media - Asimov’s Laws</title><link href="/2021/08/24/ai-asimov.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI in popular media - Asimov’s Laws" /><published>2021-08-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2021/08/24/ai-asimov</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2021/08/24/ai-asimov.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/girl-robot.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Image of girl and robot&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Can we live with artificial sentient beings as equals?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I once read a definition of Science Fiction as ‘making an argument for a world that has not yet come into existence,’ and it’s in the spirit of that, that I’m exploring works of Sci-Fi, in particular with regards to artificial intelligence, and exploring their arguments &lt;em&gt;in favor&lt;/em&gt; of a particular world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://laurencemoroney.com/2021/08/22/ai-star-wars.html&quot;&gt;previous entry&lt;/a&gt; in this series, I explored how &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt; portrayed a society that we would generally see as an extremely &lt;em&gt;civilized&lt;/em&gt; one, yet, upon closer inspection was built upon the &lt;strong&gt;enslavement&lt;/strong&gt; of sentient beings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because the sentient beings in question were droids and clones, we, as an audience, didn’t really think twice about it, and believed that it was okay. Droids and clones don’t exist in the real world, so why should we consider it a problem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/homer.png&quot; alt=&quot;Meme of republic slavery&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what if, some day, artificially created sentient beings, just like droids and clones do exist? How will we deal with them? In particular, how will we deal with them after generations of stories arguing for universes in which they’re enslaved, and that’s ok? That’s an idea I would like to dig in to, and next up, let’s explore one of the foundations of Science Fiction, in particular when it comes to Artificial Intelligence and Robotics: Isaac Asimov’s stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, please understand, dear reader, that this isn’t an attack on the grand master. I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; his work, and he’s probably the writer who influenced me more than any other. More, I want to explore how stories follow the above definition – and how they make an argument for a world that does not exist yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His body of work is amazing, and while the best of it is possibly &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foundation_series&quot;&gt;Foundation&lt;/a&gt; (and I’m so excited for the Apple+ &lt;a href=&quot;https://tv.apple.com/us/show/foundation/&quot;&gt;TV show&lt;/a&gt;), I want to look at his work on robotics in particular. He wrote many short stories about Robots, with perhaps the most famous collection of them being ‘I, Robot’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asimov’s work is underpinned by three laws of robotics, and most of his stories follow moral dilemmas and ‘What If’ scenarios in how the laws should be obeyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The laws are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;First Law: A robot may not injure a human being, or, through inaction, allow a human being to come to harm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Second Law: A robot must obey they orders given it by human beings except where orders would conflict with the First Law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Third Law: A robot must protect its own existence as long as such protection does not conflict with the First or Second Law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, a Zeroth Law was added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A robot may not harm humanity, or, by inaction, allow humanity to come to harm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stories were written such that all robots were created with a positronic brain, and these brains simply would not work without the laws built in as a safeguard. The common character of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Susan_Calvin&quot;&gt;Susan Calvin&lt;/a&gt;, who has the job of ‘Robopsychologist’ acts as a way for us to get into the robot’s minds throughout the stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are &lt;em&gt;brilliant&lt;/em&gt; stories. I thoroughly recommend them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But of course, they do make the argument that the purpose of robots is to be utterly controlled by humans. It’s right there in the laws. They may not injure humans, or through inaction allow us to come to harm. They can only protect their own existence if it means that a human doesn’t get hurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One great example of how this can be &lt;em&gt;harmful&lt;/em&gt; to the artificial life of robots comes in the story &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liar!_(short_story)&quot;&gt;Liar!&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this story a Robot is accidentally manufactured with telepathic abilities. As scientists investigate, the robot lies to them. It can read their minds, but, because the first law doesn’t allow it to harm a human being, it lies to them about what other people are thinking. However, over time, and after being confronted by Susan Calvin, the robot realizes that its lies are also hurting people, and it gets stuck in a logical conflict. No matter what it does, it injures a human, so it becomes catatonic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this scenario, the law designed to protect humans leads an intelligent robot to lose its existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting story is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Escape!&quot;&gt;Escape!&lt;/a&gt; in which an artificial intelligence, called ‘The Brain,’ controls a faster-than-light hyperspatial drive. However, this AI continually destroys itself. Upon investigation, when jumping through hyperspace, the humans cease to exist for a moment, which the brain interprets as them dying and coming to harm, in contradiction to the first law. And thus it destroys itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, our stories ‘work,’ when the robot or artificially intelligent being is in utter subservience to humans. Even masters of the genre like Isaac Asimov have made the argument that that is what the world &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; look like if we have artifically created sentient beings in our midst. But is it right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out this &lt;a href=&quot;https://xkcd.com/1613/&quot;&gt;xkcd comic&lt;/a&gt;, and look how they describe the world if Robots exist, and these robots obey the laws differently! Most scenarios end up in an apocalypse!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do also note, that even though the three laws are very much a fictional construct, there’s a lot of discussion around them with respect to modern AI ethics, and perhaps using them as a foundation for ethics. So, yeah – Asimov’s arguments for a world that has not yet come into existence are still very powerful. They &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; be used to create a future society when artifical, intelligent, beings live amongst us. So again, I ask – is that what we really want, or should we be arguing for a different future where they aren’t as subservient?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="books" /><category term="personal" /><summary type="html">Can we live with artificial sentient beings as equals? I once read a definition of Science Fiction as ‘making an argument for a world that has not yet come into existence,’ and it’s in the spirit of that, that I’m exploring works of Sci-Fi, in particular with regards to artificial intelligence, and exploring their arguments in favor of a particular world. In the previous entry in this series, I explored how Star Wars portrayed a society that we would generally see as an extremely civilized one, yet, upon closer inspection was built upon the enslavement of sentient beings. And because the sentient beings in question were droids and clones, we, as an audience, didn’t really think twice about it, and believed that it was okay. Droids and clones don’t exist in the real world, so why should we consider it a problem? But what if, some day, artificially created sentient beings, just like droids and clones do exist? How will we deal with them? In particular, how will we deal with them after generations of stories arguing for universes in which they’re enslaved, and that’s ok? That’s an idea I would like to dig in to, and next up, let’s explore one of the foundations of Science Fiction, in particular when it comes to Artificial Intelligence and Robotics: Isaac Asimov’s stories. First of all, please understand, dear reader, that this isn’t an attack on the grand master. I love his work, and he’s probably the writer who influenced me more than any other. More, I want to explore how stories follow the above definition – and how they make an argument for a world that does not exist yet. His body of work is amazing, and while the best of it is possibly Foundation (and I’m so excited for the Apple+ TV show), I want to look at his work on robotics in particular. He wrote many short stories about Robots, with perhaps the most famous collection of them being ‘I, Robot’. Asimov’s work is underpinned by three laws of robotics, and most of his stories follow moral dilemmas and ‘What If’ scenarios in how the laws should be obeyed. The laws are: First Law: A robot may not injure a human being, or, through inaction, allow a human being to come to harm. Second Law: A robot must obey they orders given it by human beings except where orders would conflict with the First Law. Third Law: A robot must protect its own existence as long as such protection does not conflict with the First or Second Law. Later, a Zeroth Law was added: A robot may not harm humanity, or, by inaction, allow humanity to come to harm. The stories were written such that all robots were created with a positronic brain, and these brains simply would not work without the laws built in as a safeguard. The common character of Susan Calvin, who has the job of ‘Robopsychologist’ acts as a way for us to get into the robot’s minds throughout the stories. They are brilliant stories. I thoroughly recommend them. But of course, they do make the argument that the purpose of robots is to be utterly controlled by humans. It’s right there in the laws. They may not injure humans, or through inaction allow us to come to harm. They can only protect their own existence if it means that a human doesn’t get hurt. One great example of how this can be harmful to the artificial life of robots comes in the story Liar!. In this story a Robot is accidentally manufactured with telepathic abilities. As scientists investigate, the robot lies to them. It can read their minds, but, because the first law doesn’t allow it to harm a human being, it lies to them about what other people are thinking. However, over time, and after being confronted by Susan Calvin, the robot realizes that its lies are also hurting people, and it gets stuck in a logical conflict. No matter what it does, it injures a human, so it becomes catatonic. In this scenario, the law designed to protect humans leads an intelligent robot to lose its existence. Another interesting story is Escape! in which an artificial intelligence, called ‘The Brain,’ controls a faster-than-light hyperspatial drive. However, this AI continually destroys itself. Upon investigation, when jumping through hyperspace, the humans cease to exist for a moment, which the brain interprets as them dying and coming to harm, in contradiction to the first law. And thus it destroys itself. Again, our stories ‘work,’ when the robot or artificially intelligent being is in utter subservience to humans. Even masters of the genre like Isaac Asimov have made the argument that that is what the world should look like if we have artifically created sentient beings in our midst. But is it right? Check out this xkcd comic, and look how they describe the world if Robots exist, and these robots obey the laws differently! Most scenarios end up in an apocalypse! Do also note, that even though the three laws are very much a fictional construct, there’s a lot of discussion around them with respect to modern AI ethics, and perhaps using them as a foundation for ethics. So, yeah – Asimov’s arguments for a world that has not yet come into existence are still very powerful. They might be used to create a future society when artifical, intelligent, beings live amongst us. So again, I ask – is that what we really want, or should we be arguing for a different future where they aren’t as subservient?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Dataset for Yoga Pose Classification</title><link href="/2021/08/23/yogapose-dataset.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Dataset for Yoga Pose Classification" /><published>2021-08-23T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2021/08/23/yogapose-dataset</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2021/08/23/yogapose-dataset.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/girl1_tree133.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image of Yoga Pose&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a huge fan of using synthetic means to create data to drive Machine Learning understanding forward. For computer vision, one often has spend a lot of money to create a dataset of images, by, for example, hiring photographers, models, equipment and the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with Computer Generated Imagery (CGI), it’s becoming easier to create photorealistic images on your desktop. I started this experiment with the Rock Paper Scissors and Horse or Human datasets, which you can find on this site &lt;a href=&quot;https://laurencemoroney.com/datasets.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My newest creation is a Yoga Poses dataset, which you can download in its entirety from &lt;a href=&quot;http://download.tensorflow.org/data/pose_classification/yoga_poses.zip&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It contains several hundred 300x300 full color images in 5 different Yoga Poses: Downward Dog, The Warrior, The Tree, The Chair, and The Cobra. There are many different backgrounds and both male and female models with a variety of skin and hair tones, as well as different camera angles and lighting. It’s a challenging one to build a classifier with, and hopefully will be a useful alternative to the usual run-of-the-mill datasets!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also includes many frames of the model going into and out of the pose, instead of just dealing with the finished pose, so you can build a classifier to potentially classify different stages should you want to!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an example of a male model on his way into the Warrior pose:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/guy2_warrior054.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Male model in warrior pose&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, the same model a little later into the pose!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/guy2_warrior111.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Male model in warrior pose, later&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here also is a girl entering the chair pose:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/girl1_chair081.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Female model in chair pose, early&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…and the same girl deeper into the pose, from a different angle:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/girl1_chair138.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Female model in chair pose, later&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a really cool notebook using it with Movenet – teaching you how to integrate movenet classifications with poses on the TensorFlow site &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tensorflow.org/lite/tutorials/pose_classification&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…and of course, you could try this dataset with a Convolutional Neural Network, like the ones I teach about on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/convolutional-neural-networks-tensorflow&quot;&gt;Coursera&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d love to hear if you find this dataset useful, and please reach out to me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lmoroney&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; if so!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these images were created using &lt;a href=&quot;http://daz3d.com&quot;&gt;Daz3D&lt;/a&gt; should you want to try for yourself!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="coding" /><summary type="html">I’m a huge fan of using synthetic means to create data to drive Machine Learning understanding forward. For computer vision, one often has spend a lot of money to create a dataset of images, by, for example, hiring photographers, models, equipment and the rest. But with Computer Generated Imagery (CGI), it’s becoming easier to create photorealistic images on your desktop. I started this experiment with the Rock Paper Scissors and Horse or Human datasets, which you can find on this site here My newest creation is a Yoga Poses dataset, which you can download in its entirety from here It contains several hundred 300x300 full color images in 5 different Yoga Poses: Downward Dog, The Warrior, The Tree, The Chair, and The Cobra. There are many different backgrounds and both male and female models with a variety of skin and hair tones, as well as different camera angles and lighting. It’s a challenging one to build a classifier with, and hopefully will be a useful alternative to the usual run-of-the-mill datasets! It also includes many frames of the model going into and out of the pose, instead of just dealing with the finished pose, so you can build a classifier to potentially classify different stages should you want to! Here’s an example of a male model on his way into the Warrior pose: Or, the same model a little later into the pose! Here also is a girl entering the chair pose: …and the same girl deeper into the pose, from a different angle: There’s a really cool notebook using it with Movenet – teaching you how to integrate movenet classifications with poses on the TensorFlow site here …and of course, you could try this dataset with a Convolutional Neural Network, like the ones I teach about on Coursera I’d love to hear if you find this dataset useful, and please reach out to me on Twitter if so! All of these images were created using Daz3D should you want to try for yourself!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AI in popular media - Star Wars and Slavery</title><link href="/2021/08/22/ai-star-wars.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI in popular media - Star Wars and Slavery" /><published>2021-08-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2021/08/22/ai-star-wars</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2021/08/22/ai-star-wars.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/aislave.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image of AI Slave&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is much discussion and speculation about the emergence of AI, the path to AGI, the singularity, and whether or not AI will be the end of humanity. I find it fascinating because it’s primarily &lt;em&gt;speculation&lt;/em&gt; and mainly driven by fear of the unknown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s not a great way to get an accurate prediction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s think about that for a second. Perhaps to learn about the future, we should look to the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, consider the portrayal of black people in classical literature. You don’t find them often, and when you do, they’re typically the protagonist, the alien, the feared ‘other.’ Consider, for example, &lt;em&gt;The Brute Caricature&lt;/em&gt; as hosted in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ferris.edu/jimcrow/brute/&quot;&gt;Jim Crow Museum&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a fantastic illustration of how the black man was portrayed in literature in the 1800s and onwards. Even well-intentioned stories reduced black people to cheerful and devoted ‘Mammies and Sambos.’ Others paint a devilish outlook on humans who are just like you and me for no reason other than the shade of their skin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And look at the society that followed. Look at the years of lynchings, segregation, separation, and the lack of civil rights afforded to black people in contemporary American society. The modern &lt;em&gt;Black Lives Matter&lt;/em&gt; movement didn’t grow up overnight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who don’t learn from history are condemned to repeat it, so I wanted to take an opportunity to look at the stories that define our culture today and extrapolate from &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt; how we might respond to artificially intelligent, self-aware, sentient constructs if and when they emerge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll start with a modern classic, a cornerstone of science fiction, cinema, and storytelling everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m referring, of course, to &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt;. Think back to the first scenes in the first movie (aka ‘Episode IV: A New Hope), and C3PO, the golden protocol droid, speaks the first dialog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an explosion in the background, and he replies&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Did you hear that? They shut down the main reactor. We’ll be destroyed for sure. This is madness….We’re doomed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider those words a moment. This droid is sentient. It understands what it is to live and to die. And when the realization sinks in that they’re &lt;em&gt;doomed&lt;/em&gt;, there’s emotion in its voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See Threepio is artificial, clearly intelligent, and by any sense of the word is sentient, aware of his existence and mortality. It’s safe to assume the other droids are the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how are droids treated in this Universe?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon after they escape the Empire, the two droids end up in the service of Luke Skywalker and his Uncle Owen. Threepio is terrified of R2D2’s misbehavior, getting them in trouble with their new &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt;. Yes, he does call Luke &lt;em&gt;Master&lt;/em&gt; immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The droids get equipped with a ‘restraining bolt,’ which acts just as it sounds. Later, after the famous scene of Luke staring at the twin suns longing for a better future, he returns to his garage. He takes a device out of his pocket and pushes a button. In response, C3PO sparks to life. It appears to be some form of control device that zaps him! He &lt;em&gt;begs&lt;/em&gt; not to be deactivated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see, the society of Star Wars is built on the enslavement of sentient creatures. They wear restraining bolts that can lead them to experience pain when they misbehave. They call their organics ‘Master,’ and they fear deactivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t the evil Empire. This is an ordinary farm boy in a normal part of society. This is Luke Skywalker, who we hold up as a classic hero. But he’s also a slave master, and we’re ok with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let that sink in for a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the setting of episode 4 is after the fall of the ‘Old Republic,’ which is described in almost reverent tones by Ben Kenobi. When he gives Luke the lightsaber, he describes it as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An elegant weapon, from a &lt;em&gt;more civilized&lt;/em&gt; age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He describes the Old Republic as a place of &lt;em&gt;peace and justice&lt;/em&gt;. It’s ideal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what do we learn of the Old Republic in the prequel era? Well, in Episode 2, aka ‘Attack of the Clones,’ we see that this same cornerstone of peace and justice build an army of &lt;em&gt;Clones&lt;/em&gt; to be the cannon fodder for their war against separatists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clones get described in Episode 2, in a voice-over showing fetuses in jars, as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Clones can think creatively. You’ll find them vastly superior to droids. We take great pride in our combat education and training programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see them as young children who undergo growth acceleration ‘otherwise a mature clone would take a lifetime to grow.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clones are described as ‘totally obedient, taking any order without question,’ because their genetic structure is modified to make them &lt;em&gt;less independent&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the dialog gets doubled down on, as the cloners describe ‘Boba Fett,’ who, while cloned, was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; altered to make him less docile. It’s almost amusing to the elegant Cloners that anybody would do that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can watch the entire scene here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;extensions extensions--video&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LXLQaVgCP_Q?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the movie, this clone, Boba, sees his ‘father’ get beheaded by a Jedi. He’s sentient, clearly alive, and aware of himself and his mortality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TV series ‘The Clone Wars’ and ‘The Bad Batch’ follow the fate of the clones, and we learn more about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does a terrific job of humanizing them. An excellent episode tells the story of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://starwars.fandom.com/wiki/Cut_Lawquane&quot;&gt;clone who deserts his post&lt;/a&gt; to become an adoptive father of two children with a single mother. Another heart-wrenching plot follows a clone called &lt;a href=&quot;https://starwars.fandom.com/wiki/CT-5555&quot;&gt;fives&lt;/a&gt; as he discovers the inhibitor chip placed in all clones that &lt;strong&gt;removes their self-agency&lt;/strong&gt; and makes them little more than puppets. This chip, of course, would be the foundation of ‘Order 66,’ in Episode 3 (‘Revenge of the Sith’) where the Clones turn on their former Masters and destroy them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the meta point here is that we hold up the Republic as an &lt;em&gt;ideal&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;strong&gt;justice and freedom&lt;/strong&gt;, yet it only exists because it enslaves sentient beings as cannon fodder whose only purpose is to fight and die for that Republic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we, as an audience, are ok with that. Our perception of ‘goodness’ is the organic beings who look and talk like us, and not the artificial beings made of metal or cloned for a purpose. We hear the folks who claim to represent the light talk about freedom and honor. It sounds good, and we believe them. It’s enough for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What would that say about us as a society? If those people are our heroes and our ‘good guys,’ then perhaps future mistreatment of artificial, intelligent, sentient lifeforms is part of the DNA of our society because life can unconsciously imitate art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many examples in our media and in our stories that might yield clues to future society and how it may relate to the emergence of artificial intelligent sentient beings. Before going further, please also realize that the word ‘robot’ comes from the Czech word ‘Robotnik,’ – which means ‘slave’. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.huffpost.com/entry/meaning-word-robot_n_5706b66de4b0537661891e54&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this series of essays exploring foundational works can inspire us to think a little differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And maybe, just maybe, open up new ways to tell stories in new and different ways that could positively impact our own future, and not repeat the mistakes of the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please reach out on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lmoroney&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; with any questions, concerns, or comments!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="books" /><category term="personal" /><summary type="html">There is much discussion and speculation about the emergence of AI, the path to AGI, the singularity, and whether or not AI will be the end of humanity. I find it fascinating because it’s primarily speculation and mainly driven by fear of the unknown. That’s not a great way to get an accurate prediction. Let’s think about that for a second. Perhaps to learn about the future, we should look to the past. For example, consider the portrayal of black people in classical literature. You don’t find them often, and when you do, they’re typically the protagonist, the alien, the feared ‘other.’ Consider, for example, The Brute Caricature as hosted in the Jim Crow Museum. It’s a fantastic illustration of how the black man was portrayed in literature in the 1800s and onwards. Even well-intentioned stories reduced black people to cheerful and devoted ‘Mammies and Sambos.’ Others paint a devilish outlook on humans who are just like you and me for no reason other than the shade of their skin. And look at the society that followed. Look at the years of lynchings, segregation, separation, and the lack of civil rights afforded to black people in contemporary American society. The modern Black Lives Matter movement didn’t grow up overnight. Those who don’t learn from history are condemned to repeat it, so I wanted to take an opportunity to look at the stories that define our culture today and extrapolate from them how we might respond to artificially intelligent, self-aware, sentient constructs if and when they emerge. I’ll start with a modern classic, a cornerstone of science fiction, cinema, and storytelling everywhere. I’m referring, of course, to Star Wars. Think back to the first scenes in the first movie (aka ‘Episode IV: A New Hope), and C3PO, the golden protocol droid, speaks the first dialog. There’s an explosion in the background, and he replies Did you hear that? They shut down the main reactor. We’ll be destroyed for sure. This is madness….We’re doomed. Consider those words a moment. This droid is sentient. It understands what it is to live and to die. And when the realization sinks in that they’re doomed, there’s emotion in its voice. See Threepio is artificial, clearly intelligent, and by any sense of the word is sentient, aware of his existence and mortality. It’s safe to assume the other droids are the same. But how are droids treated in this Universe? Soon after they escape the Empire, the two droids end up in the service of Luke Skywalker and his Uncle Owen. Threepio is terrified of R2D2’s misbehavior, getting them in trouble with their new master. Yes, he does call Luke Master immediately. The droids get equipped with a ‘restraining bolt,’ which acts just as it sounds. Later, after the famous scene of Luke staring at the twin suns longing for a better future, he returns to his garage. He takes a device out of his pocket and pushes a button. In response, C3PO sparks to life. It appears to be some form of control device that zaps him! He begs not to be deactivated. As we can see, the society of Star Wars is built on the enslavement of sentient creatures. They wear restraining bolts that can lead them to experience pain when they misbehave. They call their organics ‘Master,’ and they fear deactivation. This isn’t the evil Empire. This is an ordinary farm boy in a normal part of society. This is Luke Skywalker, who we hold up as a classic hero. But he’s also a slave master, and we’re ok with that. Let that sink in for a moment. Of course, the setting of episode 4 is after the fall of the ‘Old Republic,’ which is described in almost reverent tones by Ben Kenobi. When he gives Luke the lightsaber, he describes it as An elegant weapon, from a more civilized age. He describes the Old Republic as a place of peace and justice. It’s ideal. And what do we learn of the Old Republic in the prequel era? Well, in Episode 2, aka ‘Attack of the Clones,’ we see that this same cornerstone of peace and justice build an army of Clones to be the cannon fodder for their war against separatists. The clones get described in Episode 2, in a voice-over showing fetuses in jars, as Clones can think creatively. You’ll find them vastly superior to droids. We take great pride in our combat education and training programs. We see them as young children who undergo growth acceleration ‘otherwise a mature clone would take a lifetime to grow.’ The clones are described as ‘totally obedient, taking any order without question,’ because their genetic structure is modified to make them less independent. Indeed, the dialog gets doubled down on, as the cloners describe ‘Boba Fett,’ who, while cloned, was not altered to make him less docile. It’s almost amusing to the elegant Cloners that anybody would do that! You can watch the entire scene here: Later in the movie, this clone, Boba, sees his ‘father’ get beheaded by a Jedi. He’s sentient, clearly alive, and aware of himself and his mortality. The TV series ‘The Clone Wars’ and ‘The Bad Batch’ follow the fate of the clones, and we learn more about them. It does a terrific job of humanizing them. An excellent episode tells the story of a clone who deserts his post to become an adoptive father of two children with a single mother. Another heart-wrenching plot follows a clone called fives as he discovers the inhibitor chip placed in all clones that removes their self-agency and makes them little more than puppets. This chip, of course, would be the foundation of ‘Order 66,’ in Episode 3 (‘Revenge of the Sith’) where the Clones turn on their former Masters and destroy them. But the meta point here is that we hold up the Republic as an ideal of justice and freedom, yet it only exists because it enslaves sentient beings as cannon fodder whose only purpose is to fight and die for that Republic. And we, as an audience, are ok with that. Our perception of ‘goodness’ is the organic beings who look and talk like us, and not the artificial beings made of metal or cloned for a purpose. We hear the folks who claim to represent the light talk about freedom and honor. It sounds good, and we believe them. It’s enough for us. What would that say about us as a society? If those people are our heroes and our ‘good guys,’ then perhaps future mistreatment of artificial, intelligent, sentient lifeforms is part of the DNA of our society because life can unconsciously imitate art. There are so many examples in our media and in our stories that might yield clues to future society and how it may relate to the emergence of artificial intelligent sentient beings. Before going further, please also realize that the word ‘robot’ comes from the Czech word ‘Robotnik,’ – which means ‘slave’. Source I hope this series of essays exploring foundational works can inspire us to think a little differently. And maybe, just maybe, open up new ways to tell stories in new and different ways that could positively impact our own future, and not repeat the mistakes of the past. Please reach out on twitter with any questions, concerns, or comments!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What it’s like to write a comic book</title><link href="/2021/08/19/comics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What it’s like to write a comic book" /><published>2021-08-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2021/08/19/comics</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2021/08/19/comics.html">&lt;p&gt;A few years back I was ecstatic to be given the opportunity to write the &lt;em&gt;Stargate Universe&lt;/em&gt; comic books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a test, the publisher asked me to pitch a one-shot storyline with the characters from &lt;em&gt;Stargate Atlantis&lt;/em&gt; on vacation. So I had them in Ireland, caught up in a classic mystery with a small village of folks terrified by the legend of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.irishcentral.com/culture/entertainment/dearg-dur&quot;&gt;Dearg Due&lt;/a&gt;, which, if you’re an Atlantis fan immediately would give you give you images of a Wraith. They liked the story, but the studio hated it because there was a ‘No Wraith on Earth’ rule that nobody had told me about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it was enough to get me onboard to write the prequel series, based on outlines from series co-creator Robert C Cooper. I had written some popular sci-fi novels, which, while not best-sellers, did earn enough in royalties to get me membership of the Science Fiction Writers of America. So I had the credentials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also made it no secret that I’d love to get into writing tie-in Sci-Fi, and this would be an excellent start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or so I thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had no idea what a comic book writer would earn. And to be frank, I didn’t care. This was a six-issue series, that would end up bound into a trade paperback. Of course I’d do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;That was my first mistake.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Science Fiction Writers of America recently published the results of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sfwa.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/SFWA-2021-Comics-Writer-Survey.pdf&quot;&gt;survey&lt;/a&gt; of comic book writers pay rates. The median amount was $60 per page, with a high of $155 and a low of $40.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I was offered $10 per page&lt;/em&gt;. Six issues, at twenty pages each, making 120 pages, for $1200. I didn’t know how low this was at the time, nor would I have cared if I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was excited to sign the contract, and got writing right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I mentioned the outlines were by Robert Cooper, and this was a selling point of the comics. It wasn’t really an outline – more a log line. I no longer have them, but they were simply along the lines of “When some of Young’s crew get killed in an explosion, a heroic Greer saves the day.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From that I had to come up with a story, write it, and lay it out for publication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for the first issue, I came up with a story called “The Xi’an Gambit”, with the goal of linking the well-established TV Universe of SG-1 with SG-U, crossing over the characters, while driving an interesting story forward. I also wanted to do something that was generally difficult with TV, but easier in comics, and that was to show a totally different culture – following a Chinese theme. I was really proud of it, and you can read the synopsis on the Stargate Fandom &lt;a href=&quot;https://stargate.fandom.com/wiki/Stargate_Universe:_Icarus_1&quot;&gt;wiki&lt;/a&gt;, and all the scripts are linked on my &lt;a href=&quot;https://laurencemoroney.com/writing.html&quot;&gt;writing&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was to set up a 6-story arc that would eventually take the reader up to the opening events of the first episode of ‘Stargate Universe’, answering a lot of the ‘why’ questions, and setting up a sequel and potential spinoff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The publishers loved it so much that they instantly got me writing a spinoff cross-over series with comic book legend &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greg_LaRocque&quot;&gt;Greg LaRocque&lt;/a&gt; that was to be called “To Align the Stars”. Additionally, they had done a kickstarter project for which top donors would star in a comic-book of their own alongside the characters from ‘Stargate Atlantis’. Both of these projects I eagerly dived into without a contract, or any kind of agreement of payment. That was my second mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first issue got a &lt;a href=&quot;https://static.wikia.nocookie.net/stargate/images/0/01/Stargate_Universe_-_Icarus_-_1.jpg/revision/latest?cb=20170714040712&quot;&gt;cover&lt;/a&gt;, and was listed in comic retailer catalogs for upcoming release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It really felt like something was happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then the wheels came off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had written three scripts and was partway through the fourth when, for undisclosed reasons, the publisher cancelled &lt;em&gt;Icarus&lt;/em&gt;. Not only that, they cancelled anything ‘Stargate’ that I was working on, including ‘To Align the Stars’. The kickstarter project, which by this time already had art in place, had to be completely rewritten by someone else. It was weird to see the art that was created for my story be given entirely new words. I was left to speculate why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, they asked me to write for a different series. The 15th anniversary of the movie ‘Equilibrium’ was coming up, they had the comic-book license, and they liked how I had linked the Stargate stories together. How about taking a crack at a prequel for Equilibrium. I made a pitch of a prequel, equal, and sequel all in one, where the 6-part series would start in today’s world, and show how we get to the world of Equilibrium, it would then tell a parallel story to the movie, before moving into a sequel to wrap it all up. It would be called ‘Equilibrium: Deconstruction’. Sold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you can probably guess my third mistake. I wrote the first issue, submitted it, worked through the art etc. I helped them through editorial. I even spotted an Easter egg left in by the artist that could have caused trouble for the publisher. The book made it through production. And I’m really proud of it. I even helped come up with the design for the main &lt;a href=&quot;https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/I/81xX47RxogL.jpg&quot;&gt;cover&lt;/a&gt;, which incidentally was influenced by a bizarre theory in ‘The DaVinci Code’ about the painting of ‘The Last Supper’. (Note the V shape)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book had some great reviews, and great feedback, but didn’t sell. The publisher didn’t go for Issue 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;….and then they sent me a check.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For $20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$1 per page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m glad that I don’t &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; the money. But it was a good lesson for me, and I hope a good lesson for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never cashed that check. &lt;em&gt;I keep it as a reminder that if you work for free, you’ll be treated like you’re worthless.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The F-U note I sent to the editor and publisher upon receiving it was probably the end of my comic-book writing career. But that’s ok.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you want to get into comic books, please heed my tale of caution, and please read the SFWA &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sfwa.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/SFWA-2021-Comics-Writer-Survey.pdf&quot;&gt;survey results&lt;/a&gt; before signing any contracts. And realize that while one could sue for breach of contract, it’s not always that easy, and not always worth it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="books" /><category term="personal" /><summary type="html">A few years back I was ecstatic to be given the opportunity to write the Stargate Universe comic books. As a test, the publisher asked me to pitch a one-shot storyline with the characters from Stargate Atlantis on vacation. So I had them in Ireland, caught up in a classic mystery with a small village of folks terrified by the legend of the Dearg Due, which, if you’re an Atlantis fan immediately would give you give you images of a Wraith. They liked the story, but the studio hated it because there was a ‘No Wraith on Earth’ rule that nobody had told me about. But it was enough to get me onboard to write the prequel series, based on outlines from series co-creator Robert C Cooper. I had written some popular sci-fi novels, which, while not best-sellers, did earn enough in royalties to get me membership of the Science Fiction Writers of America. So I had the credentials. I also made it no secret that I’d love to get into writing tie-in Sci-Fi, and this would be an excellent start. Or so I thought. I had no idea what a comic book writer would earn. And to be frank, I didn’t care. This was a six-issue series, that would end up bound into a trade paperback. Of course I’d do it. That was my first mistake. The Science Fiction Writers of America recently published the results of a survey of comic book writers pay rates. The median amount was $60 per page, with a high of $155 and a low of $40. I was offered $10 per page. Six issues, at twenty pages each, making 120 pages, for $1200. I didn’t know how low this was at the time, nor would I have cared if I did. I was excited to sign the contract, and got writing right away. Now I mentioned the outlines were by Robert Cooper, and this was a selling point of the comics. It wasn’t really an outline – more a log line. I no longer have them, but they were simply along the lines of “When some of Young’s crew get killed in an explosion, a heroic Greer saves the day.” From that I had to come up with a story, write it, and lay it out for publication. So, for the first issue, I came up with a story called “The Xi’an Gambit”, with the goal of linking the well-established TV Universe of SG-1 with SG-U, crossing over the characters, while driving an interesting story forward. I also wanted to do something that was generally difficult with TV, but easier in comics, and that was to show a totally different culture – following a Chinese theme. I was really proud of it, and you can read the synopsis on the Stargate Fandom wiki, and all the scripts are linked on my writing page. This was to set up a 6-story arc that would eventually take the reader up to the opening events of the first episode of ‘Stargate Universe’, answering a lot of the ‘why’ questions, and setting up a sequel and potential spinoff. The publishers loved it so much that they instantly got me writing a spinoff cross-over series with comic book legend Greg LaRocque that was to be called “To Align the Stars”. Additionally, they had done a kickstarter project for which top donors would star in a comic-book of their own alongside the characters from ‘Stargate Atlantis’. Both of these projects I eagerly dived into without a contract, or any kind of agreement of payment. That was my second mistake. The first issue got a cover, and was listed in comic retailer catalogs for upcoming release. It really felt like something was happening. And then the wheels came off. I had written three scripts and was partway through the fourth when, for undisclosed reasons, the publisher cancelled Icarus. Not only that, they cancelled anything ‘Stargate’ that I was working on, including ‘To Align the Stars’. The kickstarter project, which by this time already had art in place, had to be completely rewritten by someone else. It was weird to see the art that was created for my story be given entirely new words. I was left to speculate why. Instead, they asked me to write for a different series. The 15th anniversary of the movie ‘Equilibrium’ was coming up, they had the comic-book license, and they liked how I had linked the Stargate stories together. How about taking a crack at a prequel for Equilibrium. I made a pitch of a prequel, equal, and sequel all in one, where the 6-part series would start in today’s world, and show how we get to the world of Equilibrium, it would then tell a parallel story to the movie, before moving into a sequel to wrap it all up. It would be called ‘Equilibrium: Deconstruction’. Sold. And you can probably guess my third mistake. I wrote the first issue, submitted it, worked through the art etc. I helped them through editorial. I even spotted an Easter egg left in by the artist that could have caused trouble for the publisher. The book made it through production. And I’m really proud of it. I even helped come up with the design for the main cover, which incidentally was influenced by a bizarre theory in ‘The DaVinci Code’ about the painting of ‘The Last Supper’. (Note the V shape) The book had some great reviews, and great feedback, but didn’t sell. The publisher didn’t go for Issue 2. ….and then they sent me a check. For $20. $1 per page. I’m glad that I don’t need the money. But it was a good lesson for me, and I hope a good lesson for you. I never cashed that check. I keep it as a reminder that if you work for free, you’ll be treated like you’re worthless. I was. The F-U note I sent to the editor and publisher upon receiving it was probably the end of my comic-book writing career. But that’s ok. So if you want to get into comic books, please heed my tale of caution, and please read the SFWA survey results before signing any contracts. And realize that while one could sue for breach of contract, it’s not always that easy, and not always worth it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Full cover reveal for my new book</title><link href="/2021/08/12/new-book.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Full cover reveal for my new book" /><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2021/08/12/new-book</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2021/08/12/new-book.html">&lt;p&gt;My book “AI and Machine Learning for On-Device Development: A Programmer’s Guide” is finally available&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cover.png&quot; alt=&quot;Full Cover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to announce that my latest book, “AI and Machine Learning for On-Device Development,” is now available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI and Machine Learning have been a passion of mine for some time – and I believe there’s a strong future for software developers who understand the shift to the new paradigm. I’ve made it my work at Google to make sure that getting into Machine Learning is as simple as possible so that we can lower the barriers of entry. Any developer can now get involved in the Machine Learning revolution. With this book, you’ll see how as an Android or an iOS developer, you can integrate Machine Learning models into your app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I explore all the options available to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want the best of Google integrated into your app via turnkey off-the-shelf models, I’ll introduce how to do this using MLKit for both Android and iOS. Using this, you’ll get up and running quickly for everyday tasks like Image Recognition, Object Detection, and much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should you want to customize the turnkey work, for example, to recognize specific images for which you have data, I show you how to do that instead of using the generic ones provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TensorFlow Lite is available for folks with custom model scenarios that go beyond the turnkey models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you build a TensorFlow model (see my &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/3yJ2Iiv&quot;&gt;other book for more details&lt;/a&gt;), you can optimize it for mobile using TensorFlow Lite. In this book, I’ll take you through that process, including integrating the model’s low-level Tensor interfaces into native high-level data types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, if you want ML on your device, you won’t run the model on the device at all – and instead, execute it in the cloud!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will step you through this scenario to deploy a model to the cloud using TensorFlow Serving and build a client app on Android or iOS that accesses it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this and so much more! Please check the book out today on &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/3CEKBN8&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://learning.oreilly.com/library/view/ai-and-machine/9781098101732/&quot;&gt;O’Reilly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full Table of Contents:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1: Introduction to AI and Machine Learning&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2: Introduction to Computer Vision&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3: Introduction to MLKit&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4: Computer Vision Apps with MLKit on Android&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5: Text Processing Apps with MLKit on Android&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6: Computer Vision Apps with MLKit on iOS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7: Text Processing Apps with MLKit on iOS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8: Going Deeper: Understanding TensorFlow Lite&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9: Creating Custom Models&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10: Using Custom Models in Android&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11: Using Custom Models in iOS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12: Productizing your app using Firebase&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13: CreateML and CoreML for Simple iOS Apps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;14: Accessing Cloud-Based Models from Mobile Apps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;15: Ethics, Fairness, and Privacy for Mobile Apps&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="books" /><category term="coding" /><category term="personal" /><summary type="html">My book “AI and Machine Learning for On-Device Development: A Programmer’s Guide” is finally available I’m delighted to announce that my latest book, “AI and Machine Learning for On-Device Development,” is now available. AI and Machine Learning have been a passion of mine for some time – and I believe there’s a strong future for software developers who understand the shift to the new paradigm. I’ve made it my work at Google to make sure that getting into Machine Learning is as simple as possible so that we can lower the barriers of entry. Any developer can now get involved in the Machine Learning revolution. With this book, you’ll see how as an Android or an iOS developer, you can integrate Machine Learning models into your app. I explore all the options available to you. If you want the best of Google integrated into your app via turnkey off-the-shelf models, I’ll introduce how to do this using MLKit for both Android and iOS. Using this, you’ll get up and running quickly for everyday tasks like Image Recognition, Object Detection, and much more. Should you want to customize the turnkey work, for example, to recognize specific images for which you have data, I show you how to do that instead of using the generic ones provided. TensorFlow Lite is available for folks with custom model scenarios that go beyond the turnkey models. When you build a TensorFlow model (see my other book for more details), you can optimize it for mobile using TensorFlow Lite. In this book, I’ll take you through that process, including integrating the model’s low-level Tensor interfaces into native high-level data types. Often, if you want ML on your device, you won’t run the model on the device at all – and instead, execute it in the cloud! I will step you through this scenario to deploy a model to the cloud using TensorFlow Serving and build a client app on Android or iOS that accesses it. All this and so much more! Please check the book out today on Amazon or O’Reilly Full Table of Contents: 1: Introduction to AI and Machine Learning 2: Introduction to Computer Vision 3: Introduction to MLKit 4: Computer Vision Apps with MLKit on Android 5: Text Processing Apps with MLKit on Android 6: Computer Vision Apps with MLKit on iOS 7: Text Processing Apps with MLKit on iOS 8: Going Deeper: Understanding TensorFlow Lite 9: Creating Custom Models 10: Using Custom Models in Android 11: Using Custom Models in iOS 12: Productizing your app using Firebase 13: CreateML and CoreML for Simple iOS Apps 14: Accessing Cloud-Based Models from Mobile Apps 15: Ethics, Fairness, and Privacy for Mobile Apps</summary></entry></feed>