<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-01-26T21:09:59-08:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Laurence Moroney - The AI Guy.</title><subtitle>This is the blog and general web site of Laurence Moroney, author, lecturer, teacher and AI lead at Google with Musings on AI, Quantum and other future tech
</subtitle><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><entry><title type="html">NFTs - Navigating Beyond the Hype Towards Real Value</title><link href="/2024/01/26/nft.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NFTs - Navigating Beyond the Hype Towards Real Value" /><published>2024-01-26T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-26T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/2024/01/26/nft</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/01/26/nft.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/boredape.png&quot; alt=&quot;A Bored Ape&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the wake of the cryptocurrency boom, Non-Fungible Tokens (NFTs) emerged as the digital darlings of the art and collectibles world. However, as we navigate through 2024, the luster of NFTs seems to be fading. A recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://dappgambl.com/nfts/dead-nfts/&quot;&gt;report by DappGambl&lt;/a&gt; highlights that a staggering 95% of NFT collections are now considered ‘dead,’ with little to no market value. This stark revelation is a wake-up call to the NFT community and potential investors, signaling a shift from the gold rush mentality to a more sustainable and value-oriented approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial appeal of NFTs lay in their novelty as unique digital assets - be it art, music, or video clips. This allure drove a speculative frenzy, culminating in record-breaking sales and headline-grabbing auctions. However, as with any gold rush, the inevitable market correction has left many investors holding assets with diminished or no value. According to DappGambl, the majority of NFT collections have failed to find a sustainable market, reflecting an oversupply and a lack of adequate demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps more pressing than the market dynamics is the environmental cost of NFTs. The energy-intensive process of minting NFTs on blockchain networks has significant carbon footprints. With thousands of NFTs generating emissions equivalent to that of small countries, the environmental impact is no longer a secondary concern but a primary issue that needs addressing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/pile.png&quot; alt=&quot;A Waste Pile of old NFTs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amidst this backdrop, the future of NFTs hinges on a critical pivot - from transient, speculative assets to digital assets with intrinsic, tangible value. The era of NFTs serving merely as digital avatars or speculative art pieces is waning. Instead, the real opportunity lies in leveraging the unique properties of NFTs for applications with inherent utility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine digital assets that are not just collectibles but integral to digital identity, gaming, real estate, and more. NFTs could represent fractional ownership in physical assets, offer exclusive access to services, or play a crucial role in supply chain management. The key is in their uniqueness and the immutable proof of ownership that blockchain technology provides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the evolution of NFTs must be cognizant of the environmental impact. The shift towards more energy-efficient blockchain protocols or the integration of eco-friendly practices in NFT creation and trading could mitigate the environmental concerns, aligning the NFT market with broader sustainability goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, while the hype around NFTs as speculative art pieces may be fading, their potential as digital assets with real-world utility is only beginning to be tapped. As the market matures and becomes more discerning, the future of NFTs will likely be defined by their ability to offer value beyond the digital realm, aligning with environmental considerations and practical use cases. The gold rush might be over, but a more sustainable and value-driven era for NFTs is on the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[This Blog Post was written with the assistance of LLMs]&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="futures" /><summary type="html">In the wake of the cryptocurrency boom, Non-Fungible Tokens (NFTs) emerged as the digital darlings of the art and collectibles world. However, as we navigate through 2024, the luster of NFTs seems to be fading. A recent report by DappGambl highlights that a staggering 95% of NFT collections are now considered ‘dead,’ with little to no market value. This stark revelation is a wake-up call to the NFT community and potential investors, signaling a shift from the gold rush mentality to a more sustainable and value-oriented approach. The initial appeal of NFTs lay in their novelty as unique digital assets - be it art, music, or video clips. This allure drove a speculative frenzy, culminating in record-breaking sales and headline-grabbing auctions. However, as with any gold rush, the inevitable market correction has left many investors holding assets with diminished or no value. According to DappGambl, the majority of NFT collections have failed to find a sustainable market, reflecting an oversupply and a lack of adequate demand. But perhaps more pressing than the market dynamics is the environmental cost of NFTs. The energy-intensive process of minting NFTs on blockchain networks has significant carbon footprints. With thousands of NFTs generating emissions equivalent to that of small countries, the environmental impact is no longer a secondary concern but a primary issue that needs addressing. Amidst this backdrop, the future of NFTs hinges on a critical pivot - from transient, speculative assets to digital assets with intrinsic, tangible value. The era of NFTs serving merely as digital avatars or speculative art pieces is waning. Instead, the real opportunity lies in leveraging the unique properties of NFTs for applications with inherent utility. Imagine digital assets that are not just collectibles but integral to digital identity, gaming, real estate, and more. NFTs could represent fractional ownership in physical assets, offer exclusive access to services, or play a crucial role in supply chain management. The key is in their uniqueness and the immutable proof of ownership that blockchain technology provides. Moreover, the evolution of NFTs must be cognizant of the environmental impact. The shift towards more energy-efficient blockchain protocols or the integration of eco-friendly practices in NFT creation and trading could mitigate the environmental concerns, aligning the NFT market with broader sustainability goals. In conclusion, while the hype around NFTs as speculative art pieces may be fading, their potential as digital assets with real-world utility is only beginning to be tapped. As the market matures and becomes more discerning, the future of NFTs will likely be defined by their ability to offer value beyond the digital realm, aligning with environmental considerations and practical use cases. The gold rush might be over, but a more sustainable and value-driven era for NFTs is on the horizon. [This Blog Post was written with the assistance of LLMs]</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Prompt Engineering Best Practices</title><link href="/2023/12/19/prompts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Prompt Engineering Best Practices" /><published>2023-12-19T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-12-19T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/2023/12/19/prompts</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/12/19/prompts.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;effective-prompt-design-strategies-and-best-practices&quot;&gt;Effective Prompt Design: Strategies and Best Practices&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The art of prompt design is pivotal in harnessing the full potential of AI models. A well-crafted prompt can be the difference between an average and an exceptional AI response. My team in Google have published guidelines for this that are well worth &lt;a href=&quot;https://ai.google.dev/docs/prompt_best_practices&quot;&gt;checking out in more detail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/prompt_eng.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Prompt Engineering, visualized&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some key strategies and best practices to consider:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;clarity-in-instructions&quot;&gt;Clarity in Instructions:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clear, concise instructions are crucial. They guide the AI to understand and respond accurately to the task at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;inclusion-of-examples&quot;&gt;Inclusion of Examples:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Including examples in prompts can significantly enhance the model’s understanding and accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;partial-input-completion&quot;&gt;Partial Input Completion:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Designing prompts that allow the model to complete partial inputs can lead to more precise and relevant responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;specific-response-formats&quot;&gt;Specific Response Formats:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prompting for responses in specific formats ensures consistency and relevance in the outputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;contextual-information&quot;&gt;Contextual Information:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding context to prompts helps in refining and focusing the model’s responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;effective-use-of-prefixes&quot;&gt;Effective Use of Prefixes:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prefixes can guide the model in understanding the kind of response expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;experimentation&quot;&gt;Experimentation:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trying different phrasings, parameter values, and prompt structures can lead to improved outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;iterative-design&quot;&gt;Iterative Design:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continuous refinement and iteration of prompts are key to achieving optimal responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fallback-responses&quot;&gt;Fallback Responses:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Planning for fallback responses in case of inadequate or incorrect outputs is essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;caution-with-factual-generation&quot;&gt;Caution with Factual Generation:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be wary of over-reliance on the model for generating factual content, and exercise caution with tasks involving complex logic or mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These strategies, rooted in Google AI’s guidelines, are fundamental in crafting effective prompts that lead to high-quality, reliable AI outputs. For a more detailed exploration of these best practices, visit Google AI’s Prompt Design Strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="futures" /><summary type="html">Effective Prompt Design: Strategies and Best Practices The art of prompt design is pivotal in harnessing the full potential of AI models. A well-crafted prompt can be the difference between an average and an exceptional AI response. My team in Google have published guidelines for this that are well worth checking out in more detail Here are some key strategies and best practices to consider: Clarity in Instructions: Clear, concise instructions are crucial. They guide the AI to understand and respond accurately to the task at hand. Inclusion of Examples: Including examples in prompts can significantly enhance the model’s understanding and accuracy. Partial Input Completion: Designing prompts that allow the model to complete partial inputs can lead to more precise and relevant responses. Specific Response Formats: Prompting for responses in specific formats ensures consistency and relevance in the outputs. Contextual Information: Adding context to prompts helps in refining and focusing the model’s responses. Effective Use of Prefixes: Prefixes can guide the model in understanding the kind of response expected. Experimentation: Trying different phrasings, parameter values, and prompt structures can lead to improved outcomes. Iterative Design: Continuous refinement and iteration of prompts are key to achieving optimal responses. Fallback Responses: Planning for fallback responses in case of inadequate or incorrect outputs is essential. Caution with Factual Generation: Be wary of over-reliance on the model for generating factual content, and exercise caution with tasks involving complex logic or mathematics. Conclusion: These strategies, rooted in Google AI’s guidelines, are fundamental in crafting effective prompts that lead to high-quality, reliable AI outputs. For a more detailed exploration of these best practices, visit Google AI’s Prompt Design Strategies.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Towards Artificial Understanding</title><link href="/2023/12/14/towards-au.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Towards Artificial Understanding" /><published>2023-12-14T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-12-14T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/2023/12/14/towards-au</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/12/14/towards-au.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our journey through the technological renaissance, we’ve witnessed the rise and evolution of artificial intelligence (AI). However, a new concept is emerging, poised to redefine our understanding of machine intelligence: and I call it Artificial Understanding (AU). This groundbreaking idea extends the capabilities of AI, pushing it beyond mere data processing and content generation. Today, we explore what Artificial Understanding entails and how it can reshape the landscape of AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/au.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;AU drawn by DALL-E&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-essence-of-artificial-understanding&quot;&gt;The Essence of Artificial &lt;em&gt;Understanding&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Artificial Understanding represents a significant leap in the field of AI. It’s about endowing machines with the ability to not just process but to interpret and comprehend information in a contextually meaningful way. AU takes AI a step further from performing predefined tasks to possessing a level of understanding akin to basic human cognition. This advancement is pivotal as it transforms AI from a tool that follows instructions to an entity that can grasp context, nuances, and the subtleties of the data it processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;point-1-transformers---the-building-blocks-of-understanding&quot;&gt;Point 1: Transformers - The Building Blocks of Understanding&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;understanding-sequences-of-text&quot;&gt;Understanding Sequences of Text&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Central to the concept of AU are transformer models. Unlike conventional algorithms that treat data as isolated points, transformers understand sequences of text, grasping the context and relationships within. This capability is akin to a rudimentary form of understanding, where the model discerns patterns and meanings beyond mere words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;case-studies&quot;&gt;Case Studies&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GPT (Generative Pre-trained Transformer) and BERT (Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers) serve as prime examples of this technology. They demonstrate how transformers can not only generate coherent and contextually relevant text but also interpret and respond to human language with a surprising degree of understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;point-2-efficient-compression-of-knowledge&quot;&gt;Point 2: Efficient Compression of Knowledge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;beyond-generative-capabilities&quot;&gt;Beyond Generative Capabilities&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The true marvel of transformer models, such as GPT or Gemini, lies in their remarkable efficiency in knowledge compression. This efficiency is a critical aspect of Artificial Understanding. These models manage to compress vast amounts of text – potentially equivalent to petabytes of data – into a model of just a few billion (or hundred-million) parameters, which occupies only gigabytes (or less) of space. This is not merely a triumph in data storage but a reflection of how these models distill and encapsulate vast information, enabling them to ‘understand’ and apply this knowledge effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implications-and-future-prospects&quot;&gt;Implications and Future Prospects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The implications of Artificial Understanding are vast and far-reaching. In the realm of customer service, it could lead to chatbots that not only answer queries but understand the emotions and intents behind them. In data analysis, AU could enable systems to not just process numbers but to interpret trends and insights in a contextually rich manner. The potential applications are limitless, stretching across various domains from healthcare, where understanding patient history and symptoms could revolutionize diagnoses, to finance, where understanding market nuances is key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Artificial Understanding is more than just an incremental addition to the AI landscape; it is a paradigm shift. It challenges our preconceptions of machine capabilities, opening doors to possibilities where machines don’t just calculate but comprehend. As we stand at the precipice of this new era in AI, the promise and potential of Artificial Understanding beckon a future where the lines between human and machine understanding become increasingly blurred, leading to innovations we can only begin to imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[This post was created with the assistance of LLMs]&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="futures" /><summary type="html">Introduction: In our journey through the technological renaissance, we’ve witnessed the rise and evolution of artificial intelligence (AI). However, a new concept is emerging, poised to redefine our understanding of machine intelligence: and I call it Artificial Understanding (AU). This groundbreaking idea extends the capabilities of AI, pushing it beyond mere data processing and content generation. Today, we explore what Artificial Understanding entails and how it can reshape the landscape of AI. The Essence of Artificial Understanding Artificial Understanding represents a significant leap in the field of AI. It’s about endowing machines with the ability to not just process but to interpret and comprehend information in a contextually meaningful way. AU takes AI a step further from performing predefined tasks to possessing a level of understanding akin to basic human cognition. This advancement is pivotal as it transforms AI from a tool that follows instructions to an entity that can grasp context, nuances, and the subtleties of the data it processes. Point 1: Transformers - The Building Blocks of Understanding Understanding Sequences of Text Central to the concept of AU are transformer models. Unlike conventional algorithms that treat data as isolated points, transformers understand sequences of text, grasping the context and relationships within. This capability is akin to a rudimentary form of understanding, where the model discerns patterns and meanings beyond mere words. Case Studies GPT (Generative Pre-trained Transformer) and BERT (Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers) serve as prime examples of this technology. They demonstrate how transformers can not only generate coherent and contextually relevant text but also interpret and respond to human language with a surprising degree of understanding. Point 2: Efficient Compression of Knowledge Beyond Generative Capabilities The true marvel of transformer models, such as GPT or Gemini, lies in their remarkable efficiency in knowledge compression. This efficiency is a critical aspect of Artificial Understanding. These models manage to compress vast amounts of text – potentially equivalent to petabytes of data – into a model of just a few billion (or hundred-million) parameters, which occupies only gigabytes (or less) of space. This is not merely a triumph in data storage but a reflection of how these models distill and encapsulate vast information, enabling them to ‘understand’ and apply this knowledge effectively. Implications and Future Prospects The implications of Artificial Understanding are vast and far-reaching. In the realm of customer service, it could lead to chatbots that not only answer queries but understand the emotions and intents behind them. In data analysis, AU could enable systems to not just process numbers but to interpret trends and insights in a contextually rich manner. The potential applications are limitless, stretching across various domains from healthcare, where understanding patient history and symptoms could revolutionize diagnoses, to finance, where understanding market nuances is key. Conclusion Artificial Understanding is more than just an incremental addition to the AI landscape; it is a paradigm shift. It challenges our preconceptions of machine capabilities, opening doors to possibilities where machines don’t just calculate but comprehend. As we stand at the precipice of this new era in AI, the promise and potential of Artificial Understanding beckon a future where the lines between human and machine understanding become increasingly blurred, leading to innovations we can only begin to imagine. [This post was created with the assistance of LLMs]</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Evaluating Hallucination - A danger of LLMs</title><link href="/2023/11/29/evaluating-hallucination.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evaluating Hallucination - A danger of LLMs" /><published>2023-11-29T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-29T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/2023/11/29/evaluating-hallucination</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/11/29/evaluating-hallucination.html">&lt;p&gt;I just read a very interesting paper on Arxiv titled “The impact of using an AI chatbot to respond to patient messages.” where an evaluation of human-chat versus GPT-chat was done, measuring effectiveness, efficiency, and the potential danger of hallucination. YOu can see the paper [here] (https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.17703)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The integration of Artificial Intelligence (AI) into healthcare is a rapidly evolving frontier, promising to revolutionize patient care and clinician workflow. A recent study published on arXiv.org delves into this topic, exploring the effects of using an AI chatbot, specifically GPT-4, for responding to patient messages in a healthcare setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ai-med.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;AI in Medicine&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;overview-of-the-study&quot;&gt;Overview of the Study&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study aimed to assess the acceptability, safety, and efficiency of using an AI-based chatbot in drafting responses to patient queries. Conducted at Brigham and Women’s Hospital, Boston, in 2023, it involved six board-certified oncologists who responded to 100 realistic cancer patient scenarios. The study was designed in two stages, where in the first stage, oncologists manually responded to patient messages, and in the second stage, they edited responses generated by GPT-4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-findings&quot;&gt;Key Findings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results were significant:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Efficiency Improvement&lt;/strong&gt;: In 77% of cases, the use of GPT-4 improved documentation efficiency.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Safety&lt;/strong&gt;: 82% of the time, the AI-generated responses were considered safe.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk of Harm&lt;/strong&gt;: However, there was a 7.7% chance that unedited GPT-4 responses could lead to severe harm or death.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;physician-perception-of-ai-responses&quot;&gt;Physician Perception of AI Responses&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, in 31% of cases, physicians believed the GPT-4 drafts were written by humans. This perception highlights the sophistication of AI-generated responses but also underscores the necessity for careful review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impact-on-patient-education-and-clinical-actions&quot;&gt;Impact on Patient Education and Clinical Actions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of AI led to an increase in patient education recommendations but a decrease in direct clinical actions. This shift suggests that while AI can enhance informational support, it might underrepresent the need for immediate clinical interventions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;risks-and-challenges&quot;&gt;Risks and Challenges&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the benefits, the study highlights critical risks associated with AI in healthcare:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Potential for severe harm in a small but significant percentage of responses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The need for diligent oversight and human intervention to ensure patient safety.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;future-implications&quot;&gt;Future Implications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study opens up a discussion about the future role of AI in healthcare communication. While AI shows promise in reducing clinician workload and enhancing patient education, its impact on clinical decision-making and the potential risks involved require ongoing scrutiny and responsible implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, this study on using AI chatbots for patient communication reveals a complex balance. While AI can significantly enhance efficiency and patient education, it introduces risks that necessitate vigilant oversight. The future of AI in healthcare holds great promise but demands a cautious and well-informed approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chen, S., et al. (2023). The impact of using an AI chatbot to respond to patient messages. arXiv.org. &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.17703&quot;&gt;arXiv:2310.17703&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please note that this blog post is a summary and interpretation of the study and does not cover all aspects of the research. For a comprehensive understanding, readers are encouraged to refer to the original paper.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note: This post was written with the assistance of Large Language Models&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="regulation" /><summary type="html">I just read a very interesting paper on Arxiv titled “The impact of using an AI chatbot to respond to patient messages.” where an evaluation of human-chat versus GPT-chat was done, measuring effectiveness, efficiency, and the potential danger of hallucination. YOu can see the paper [here] (https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.17703) Introduction The integration of Artificial Intelligence (AI) into healthcare is a rapidly evolving frontier, promising to revolutionize patient care and clinician workflow. A recent study published on arXiv.org delves into this topic, exploring the effects of using an AI chatbot, specifically GPT-4, for responding to patient messages in a healthcare setting. Overview of the Study This study aimed to assess the acceptability, safety, and efficiency of using an AI-based chatbot in drafting responses to patient queries. Conducted at Brigham and Women’s Hospital, Boston, in 2023, it involved six board-certified oncologists who responded to 100 realistic cancer patient scenarios. The study was designed in two stages, where in the first stage, oncologists manually responded to patient messages, and in the second stage, they edited responses generated by GPT-4. Key Findings The results were significant: Efficiency Improvement: In 77% of cases, the use of GPT-4 improved documentation efficiency. Safety: 82% of the time, the AI-generated responses were considered safe. Risk of Harm: However, there was a 7.7% chance that unedited GPT-4 responses could lead to severe harm or death. Physician Perception of AI Responses Interestingly, in 31% of cases, physicians believed the GPT-4 drafts were written by humans. This perception highlights the sophistication of AI-generated responses but also underscores the necessity for careful review. Impact on Patient Education and Clinical Actions The use of AI led to an increase in patient education recommendations but a decrease in direct clinical actions. This shift suggests that while AI can enhance informational support, it might underrepresent the need for immediate clinical interventions. Risks and Challenges Despite the benefits, the study highlights critical risks associated with AI in healthcare: Potential for severe harm in a small but significant percentage of responses. The need for diligent oversight and human intervention to ensure patient safety. Future Implications The study opens up a discussion about the future role of AI in healthcare communication. While AI shows promise in reducing clinician workload and enhancing patient education, its impact on clinical decision-making and the potential risks involved require ongoing scrutiny and responsible implementation. Conclusion In conclusion, this study on using AI chatbots for patient communication reveals a complex balance. While AI can significantly enhance efficiency and patient education, it introduces risks that necessitate vigilant oversight. The future of AI in healthcare holds great promise but demands a cautious and well-informed approach. References Chen, S., et al. (2023). The impact of using an AI chatbot to respond to patient messages. arXiv.org. arXiv:2310.17703 Please note that this blog post is a summary and interpretation of the study and does not cover all aspects of the research. For a comprehensive understanding, readers are encouraged to refer to the original paper. Note: This post was written with the assistance of Large Language Models</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Navigating the AI Landscape - The Need for Expert-Led Regulation</title><link href="/2023/11/10/ai-regulation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Navigating the AI Landscape - The Need for Expert-Led Regulation" /><published>2023-11-10T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-10T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/2023/11/10/ai-regulation</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/11/10/ai-regulation.html">&lt;p&gt;In recent years, artificial intelligence (AI) has leaped from science fiction into our daily lives, bringing both incredible potential and significant challenges. As AI continues to evolve and integrate into various sectors, the question of regulation becomes increasingly pressing. However, the key to effective AI regulation lies not in reactive policies driven by fear and misunderstanding, but in informed, expert-led approaches that understand the nuances of AI technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ai-regulation.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Regulation and Expertise&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;understanding-the-fear-and-the-reality&quot;&gt;Understanding the Fear and the Reality&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI, much like any transformative technology, has been met with its share of public apprehension. Stories of AI going rogue or replacing human jobs have fueled a narrative that often strays from reality. It is crucial to distinguish between irrational fears, often amplified by sensationalist media, and legitimate concerns regarding privacy, security, and ethical use of AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-role-of-experts-in-ai-regulation&quot;&gt;The Role of Experts in AI Regulation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effective AI regulation requires a deep understanding of the technology’s capabilities, limitations, and impact across various domains. This level of insight is typically beyond the scope of political expertise. AI experts, including scientists, ethicists, and technologists, are better equipped to foresee the implications of restricting AI development and use. They can provide balanced views that consider both the potential risks and the immense benefits AI offers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;balancing-innovation-and-safety&quot;&gt;Balancing Innovation and Safety&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of regulation should be to mitigate risks without stifling innovation. Overly restrictive regulations, born from misunderstandings or fear, could hinder the advancement of AI technologies that have the potential to solve some of our most pressing global challenges. Experts can help draft regulations that ensure safety and ethical practices while still encouraging innovation and research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;collaborative-approach-for-holistic-regulation&quot;&gt;Collaborative Approach for Holistic Regulation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regulation should not be a unilateral process dictated by a single group. A collaborative approach, involving AI experts, policymakers, industry leaders, and the public, is essential. Such collaboration can ensure that regulations are practical, well-informed, and considerate of diverse perspectives and societal needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;looking-forward&quot;&gt;Looking Forward&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As AI becomes increasingly integrated into our world, the need for thoughtful, informed regulation becomes more apparent. Entrusting this task to those who understand the intricate workings and potential of AI is not just prudent; it is &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; to harness the full potential of AI technologies while safeguarding societal values and human welfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regulating AI should be a forward-looking endeavor, not a reactionary one. By leaning on the expertise of those who best understand the technology, we can create a regulatory framework that balances innovation with responsibility, ensuring that AI serves as a tool for human progress, not a subject of unfounded fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note: This post was written with the assistance of Large Language Models&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="regulation" /><summary type="html">In recent years, artificial intelligence (AI) has leaped from science fiction into our daily lives, bringing both incredible potential and significant challenges. As AI continues to evolve and integrate into various sectors, the question of regulation becomes increasingly pressing. However, the key to effective AI regulation lies not in reactive policies driven by fear and misunderstanding, but in informed, expert-led approaches that understand the nuances of AI technology. Understanding the Fear and the Reality AI, much like any transformative technology, has been met with its share of public apprehension. Stories of AI going rogue or replacing human jobs have fueled a narrative that often strays from reality. It is crucial to distinguish between irrational fears, often amplified by sensationalist media, and legitimate concerns regarding privacy, security, and ethical use of AI. The Role of Experts in AI Regulation Effective AI regulation requires a deep understanding of the technology’s capabilities, limitations, and impact across various domains. This level of insight is typically beyond the scope of political expertise. AI experts, including scientists, ethicists, and technologists, are better equipped to foresee the implications of restricting AI development and use. They can provide balanced views that consider both the potential risks and the immense benefits AI offers. Balancing Innovation and Safety The goal of regulation should be to mitigate risks without stifling innovation. Overly restrictive regulations, born from misunderstandings or fear, could hinder the advancement of AI technologies that have the potential to solve some of our most pressing global challenges. Experts can help draft regulations that ensure safety and ethical practices while still encouraging innovation and research. Collaborative Approach for Holistic Regulation Regulation should not be a unilateral process dictated by a single group. A collaborative approach, involving AI experts, policymakers, industry leaders, and the public, is essential. Such collaboration can ensure that regulations are practical, well-informed, and considerate of diverse perspectives and societal needs. Looking Forward As AI becomes increasingly integrated into our world, the need for thoughtful, informed regulation becomes more apparent. Entrusting this task to those who understand the intricate workings and potential of AI is not just prudent; it is necessary to harness the full potential of AI technologies while safeguarding societal values and human welfare. Regulating AI should be a forward-looking endeavor, not a reactionary one. By leaning on the expertise of those who best understand the technology, we can create a regulatory framework that balances innovation with responsibility, ensuring that AI serves as a tool for human progress, not a subject of unfounded fear. Note: This post was written with the assistance of Large Language Models</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Beatles Now and Then - made possible by AI</title><link href="/2023/11/02/nowandthen.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Beatles Now and Then - made possible by AI" /><published>2023-11-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-11-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2023/11/02/nowandthen</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/11/02/nowandthen.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-final-beatles-song&quot;&gt;The Final Beatles Song&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now and then is a beautiful song, and it will be the last song from the Beatles. Made possible by AI extracting audio of old recording sessions to access content such as John Lennon’s voice, it’s an epic and beautiful recording.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s particularly poignant when you listen to the lyrics “Now and then, I miss you, I want you to be there for me”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on the track started in February 1995 as part of the Beatles anthology project, but it had to halt because of the technological challenges in extracting John’s voice from a tape recording from 20 years earlier. It looked like it wouldn’t be possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, enter Peter Jackson, of ‘Lord of the Rings’ fame, who figured out how to uncouple John’s vocal from background sound. It’s musical archaeology in action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s a beautiful and fitting song!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen to it here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/AW55J2zE3N4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="coding" /><summary type="html">The Final Beatles Song Now and then is a beautiful song, and it will be the last song from the Beatles. Made possible by AI extracting audio of old recording sessions to access content such as John Lennon’s voice, it’s an epic and beautiful recording. And it’s particularly poignant when you listen to the lyrics “Now and then, I miss you, I want you to be there for me” Work on the track started in February 1995 as part of the Beatles anthology project, but it had to halt because of the technological challenges in extracting John’s voice from a tape recording from 20 years earlier. It looked like it wouldn’t be possible. Then, enter Peter Jackson, of ‘Lord of the Rings’ fame, who figured out how to uncouple John’s vocal from background sound. It’s musical archaeology in action. And it’s a beautiful and fitting song! Listen to it here:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AI-phobia and the damage it can bring</title><link href="/2023/09/03/nofear.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI-phobia and the damage it can bring" /><published>2023-09-03T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-09-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2023/09/03/nofear</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/09/03/nofear.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;ai-where-the-only-thing-to-fear-is-fear-itself&quot;&gt;AI: Where the Only Thing to Fear is Fear Itself&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In today’s world, the majority of headlines I see around Artificial Intelligence (AI) skew negative. Fueled by decades of science fiction projecting AI to be a future antagonist, and present day attention-grabbing headlines, many view AI as the ominous cloud on the horizon of human evolution. As something that will overtake us, and having done so, will then wipe us out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sentiment brings to mind the profound words of Franklin D. Roosevelt: “The only thing we have to fear is fear itself.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-birth-of-fear&quot;&gt;The Birth of Fear&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the work done in AI is a major and encouraging pinnacle of human ingenuity, representing our innate desire to break barriers and redefine the possible. With it, we have been able to break through computational barriers, building applications the likes of which were previously thought impossible. And we’re only getting started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, like any revolutionary advancement, the right hand of power can bring the left hand of darkness, in this case, that of uncertainty and apprehension. But is this fear rooted in the technology itself or our misunderstanding of it? I argue the latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Movies, novels, and popular culture have, for decades, painted AI as the unstoppable force that will eventually surpass human intelligence, casting a shadow over our dominion. These depictions are, of course, tailored for entertainment, emphasizing conflict and drama over factual representation. Yet, the impact of these narratives on public perception is undeniable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But one thing stands clear. Intelligence alone is not enough, be it artificial or biological. A living, conscious, sentient entity, capable of making value judgements – for good or evil – is a lot more than just an intelligence. Yet the column inches of fear focus entirely on the ‘I’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take Bostrom’s famous &lt;a href=&quot;https://cepr.org/voxeu/columns/ai-and-paperclip-problem#:~:text=Bostrom&apos;s%20thought%20experiment%20goes%20like,to%20achieve%20its%20goal%20better.&quot;&gt;paper clip thought experiment&lt;/a&gt; In this, an AI is tasked with making paperclips, and, given that it can learn how to make better paperclips, it will eventually realize that all of humanity’s resources are effectively wasted if they’re not being used to make paperclips, and it will run away, and destroy humanity in an apocalypse of paperclips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/clip-fun.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Clippy making a joke&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fallacy here, of course, is that in the discussion of the &lt;em&gt;possible&lt;/em&gt;, we’re ignoring the &lt;em&gt;probable&lt;/em&gt;, and the largest factor determining probability of this outcome would be giving this paper clip generator access to the resources that would allow it to destroy humanity. Maybe it could evolve a level of intelligence that would allow it to theorize a methodology to ‘break out’ of its thought experiment confines, but does that give it the ability to do so? And, when creating any kind of artificial intelligence, the model, while very sophisticated is usually very limited. It has a one-tracked mind, if you will, and this experiment pre-supposes that it can evolve beyond that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The narrative is overtaken by fear of the possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ai-as-a-mirror&quot;&gt;AI as a Mirror&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s essential to understand that AI, at its core, is neutral. It’s a tool, an extension of our collective knowledge. AI doesn’t have emotions, ambitions, or ulterior motives. It operates on data, algorithms, and the instructions we feed it. In many ways, AI is a mirror, reflecting both the biases of its creators and the vast potential of its applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps our fear of AI comes from the fact that we’re looking in that mirror and seeing what is terrifying in ourselves? Perhaps this is a great wakeup call for us as a species to recognize that which in ourselves is dangerous, and do something about it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I also think of historic mistakes made by our species. Today, AI is that great, feared, unknown. But that wasn’t always the case, was it? Modern day racism is rooted in the same ‘othering’ of outsiders. We made many mistakes, treating (or more accurately &lt;em&gt;mis&lt;/em&gt;treating) others outside our known civilizations as savages, less than human, something to be feared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we all continue to pay the price for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe this is an opportunity not to repeat that mistake. What if, some years from now, AI becomes AL – Artificial Life. Wouldn’t it be nice to be ready to be in a position where we can understand and treat with each other with mutual respect?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-real-challenge&quot;&gt;The Real Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to today, the actual challenge lies not in the technology but in its application. A well-programmed application that uses AI can help doctors diagnose diseases, assist students in learning, or predict weather patterns with astonishing accuracy. Conversely, an poorly built one can reinforce societal prejudices, make unfair decisions, or invade privacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This dichotomy means that our real focus should be on ensuring that our work should be to develop and grow AI and ML responsibly. One underlooked aspect of respobnsible development is in mitigating fear. When allowed to dominate the narrative, fear stunts critical thinking. It can halt progress and can keep us from harnessing the transformative power of AI for the greater good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-path-forward&quot;&gt;The Path Forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of getting wrapped up in a cycle of fear and misinformation, we need to channel our collective energies towards education, open dialogue, and understanding. Collaborative efforts between tech developers, ethicists, policymakers, and the public can ensure that AI’s development remains aligned with humanity’s best interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Embracing the future means embracing AI, but with open eyes, clear minds, and fearless hearts. We stand at the cusp of a technological renaissance, and our approach will determine the legacy of this era. As we move forward, let’s remember that the most significant achievements in history were born from hope and understanding, not from fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note: I used LLMs to help me create this post. They helped me hone my thoughts and sharpen my argument. They did not replace me as a writer, nor did they drive my opinion)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="coding" /><summary type="html">AI: Where the Only Thing to Fear is Fear Itself In today’s world, the majority of headlines I see around Artificial Intelligence (AI) skew negative. Fueled by decades of science fiction projecting AI to be a future antagonist, and present day attention-grabbing headlines, many view AI as the ominous cloud on the horizon of human evolution. As something that will overtake us, and having done so, will then wipe us out. This sentiment brings to mind the profound words of Franklin D. Roosevelt: “The only thing we have to fear is fear itself.” The Birth of Fear Much of the work done in AI is a major and encouraging pinnacle of human ingenuity, representing our innate desire to break barriers and redefine the possible. With it, we have been able to break through computational barriers, building applications the likes of which were previously thought impossible. And we’re only getting started. Yet, like any revolutionary advancement, the right hand of power can bring the left hand of darkness, in this case, that of uncertainty and apprehension. But is this fear rooted in the technology itself or our misunderstanding of it? I argue the latter. Movies, novels, and popular culture have, for decades, painted AI as the unstoppable force that will eventually surpass human intelligence, casting a shadow over our dominion. These depictions are, of course, tailored for entertainment, emphasizing conflict and drama over factual representation. Yet, the impact of these narratives on public perception is undeniable. But one thing stands clear. Intelligence alone is not enough, be it artificial or biological. A living, conscious, sentient entity, capable of making value judgements – for good or evil – is a lot more than just an intelligence. Yet the column inches of fear focus entirely on the ‘I’ Take Bostrom’s famous paper clip thought experiment In this, an AI is tasked with making paperclips, and, given that it can learn how to make better paperclips, it will eventually realize that all of humanity’s resources are effectively wasted if they’re not being used to make paperclips, and it will run away, and destroy humanity in an apocalypse of paperclips. The fallacy here, of course, is that in the discussion of the possible, we’re ignoring the probable, and the largest factor determining probability of this outcome would be giving this paper clip generator access to the resources that would allow it to destroy humanity. Maybe it could evolve a level of intelligence that would allow it to theorize a methodology to ‘break out’ of its thought experiment confines, but does that give it the ability to do so? And, when creating any kind of artificial intelligence, the model, while very sophisticated is usually very limited. It has a one-tracked mind, if you will, and this experiment pre-supposes that it can evolve beyond that. The narrative is overtaken by fear of the possible. AI as a Mirror It’s essential to understand that AI, at its core, is neutral. It’s a tool, an extension of our collective knowledge. AI doesn’t have emotions, ambitions, or ulterior motives. It operates on data, algorithms, and the instructions we feed it. In many ways, AI is a mirror, reflecting both the biases of its creators and the vast potential of its applications. Perhaps our fear of AI comes from the fact that we’re looking in that mirror and seeing what is terrifying in ourselves? Perhaps this is a great wakeup call for us as a species to recognize that which in ourselves is dangerous, and do something about it? Finally, I also think of historic mistakes made by our species. Today, AI is that great, feared, unknown. But that wasn’t always the case, was it? Modern day racism is rooted in the same ‘othering’ of outsiders. We made many mistakes, treating (or more accurately mistreating) others outside our known civilizations as savages, less than human, something to be feared. And we all continue to pay the price for that. Maybe this is an opportunity not to repeat that mistake. What if, some years from now, AI becomes AL – Artificial Life. Wouldn’t it be nice to be ready to be in a position where we can understand and treat with each other with mutual respect? The Real Challenge Back to today, the actual challenge lies not in the technology but in its application. A well-programmed application that uses AI can help doctors diagnose diseases, assist students in learning, or predict weather patterns with astonishing accuracy. Conversely, an poorly built one can reinforce societal prejudices, make unfair decisions, or invade privacy. This dichotomy means that our real focus should be on ensuring that our work should be to develop and grow AI and ML responsibly. One underlooked aspect of respobnsible development is in mitigating fear. When allowed to dominate the narrative, fear stunts critical thinking. It can halt progress and can keep us from harnessing the transformative power of AI for the greater good. The Path Forward Instead of getting wrapped up in a cycle of fear and misinformation, we need to channel our collective energies towards education, open dialogue, and understanding. Collaborative efforts between tech developers, ethicists, policymakers, and the public can ensure that AI’s development remains aligned with humanity’s best interests. Embracing the future means embracing AI, but with open eyes, clear minds, and fearless hearts. We stand at the cusp of a technological renaissance, and our approach will determine the legacy of this era. As we move forward, let’s remember that the most significant achievements in history were born from hope and understanding, not from fear. (Note: I used LLMs to help me create this post. They helped me hone my thoughts and sharpen my argument. They did not replace me as a writer, nor did they drive my opinion)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/roadway.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/roadway.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">AI-Generated 2.5D</title><link href="/2023/05/22/kenburns.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI-Generated 2.5D" /><published>2023-05-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-05-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2023/05/22/kenburns</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/05/22/kenburns.html">&lt;p&gt;I really love the combination of the ‘Ken Burns’ effect to bring images to life, with a way to cut the image up into layers, and then move each layer separately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s usually a lot of work in photoshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now, with the amazing work from &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1909.05483&quot;&gt;Simon Niklaus et al&lt;/a&gt;, it seems that ML models can perform this task by using segmentation to figure out foreground from background and inpainting to fill in the missing pixels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s ingenious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played with the image from above, and got this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hC6Ie4XTa-s&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still a bit of work to be done, and I’m hoping I can tweak for higher resolution in the video, but the effect is definitely stunning…considering it’s entirely automated!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="coding" /><summary type="html">I really love the combination of the ‘Ken Burns’ effect to bring images to life, with a way to cut the image up into layers, and then move each layer separately. It’s usually a lot of work in photoshop. But now, with the amazing work from Simon Niklaus et al, it seems that ML models can perform this task by using segmentation to figure out foreground from background and inpainting to fill in the missing pixels. It’s ingenious. I played with the image from above, and got this: Still a bit of work to be done, and I’m hoping I can tweak for higher resolution in the video, but the effect is definitely stunning…considering it’s entirely automated!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/scene.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/scene.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Artificial Intelligence - Where to start</title><link href="/ai%20tech%20google/2023/05/21/getstarted.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Artificial Intelligence - Where to start" /><published>2023-05-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-05-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/ai%20tech%20google/2023/05/21/getstarted</id><content type="html" xml:base="/ai%20tech%20google/2023/05/21/getstarted.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m often asked about how to get started in the field of Artificial Intelligence. First, it’s important to understand what you’re asking. What &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; AI? Why should you be interested?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At my talk for Google IO 2023, I made a quick video to give you the lay of the land. What it is, why you should care, and what it’s all about to get data, train models, deploy and manage them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal is to give you a good understanding in a short timeframe – so it’s just a few minutes to hopefully at least give you enough info to start asking all the right questions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3K1414RwNDU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="AI Tech Google" /><category term="life" /><category term="tech" /><summary type="html">I’m often asked about how to get started in the field of Artificial Intelligence. First, it’s important to understand what you’re asking. What is AI? Why should you be interested? At my talk for Google IO 2023, I made a quick video to give you the lay of the land. What it is, why you should care, and what it’s all about to get data, train models, deploy and manage them. The goal is to give you a good understanding in a short timeframe – so it’s just a few minutes to hopefully at least give you enough info to start asking all the right questions!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/ai-future.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/ai-future.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Space Cadets - An AI-illustrated Novel. Part Three.</title><link href="/2022/06/26/Space_Cadets_Part_Three.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Space Cadets - An AI-illustrated Novel. Part Three." /><published>2022-06-26T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2022/06/26/Space_Cadets_Part_Three</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2022/06/26/Space_Cadets_Part_Three.html">&lt;p&gt;Continuing my experiment to illustrate a novel using AI text-to-image generation techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, I’m going to use MidJourney. Previous chapters used DALL-E. Let me know what you think twitter.com/lmoroney&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;chapter-3&quot;&gt;CHAPTER 3&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;launch&quot;&gt;Launch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We should always reach for the sky.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From the very beginning of history, our ancestors were looking up and wondering what was beyond their reach. The stars were calling them. They weaved stories of gods and angels, but behind them all was the intense desire to be out there. A desire born of an instinct for survival.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of a girl looking at the stars from the african savannah&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It’s something we’ve forgotten as we’ve become civilized. We’ve become comfortable in our homes, our cities and our countries. We’ve defeated nature and haven’t had the same worries that they had. But we lost something in that complacency, I fear. And now, as our world gets overcrowded, as our environment collapses under us, we need to rediscover it. We need to look up, and not worry about tripping as we race towards a new destiny. We will be those gods and angels if we want to. And you can be one of them, if you just keep trying, and never give up…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of Aisha looking out the windows of the hotel towards the spaceport&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;THE SPACE ELEVATOR. Its relatively simple name belied the sheer scale of it. Craning her neck, Aisha looked up as it disappeared impossibly into the deep blue sky. The ‘shuttle’ was a box-like structure that could easily pass for another building, but for the rocket boosters placed on its corners. These boosters would provide the initial ‘launch’ to get the craft moving out of its gravitational inertia. After that, the rotation of the Earth would take over and drive the shuttle up the cable into orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of a space elevator viewed from orbit&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was so glad for last night’s dinner with Mother. Beforehand, it had felt like there was a tension building between them. Mother’s basking in her status had gotten under Aisha’s skin, and she had been worried that she might blow up at her before leaving. She was worried that she might end up regretting it, but there was only so long she could bite her tongue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of a Aishas mother watching the shuttle in the distance&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She almost thanked the reporter for his rude question. It had brought them closer together. She felt a pang of pride again at Mother’s words that she had done exactly what Father would have done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the same reporter had wrestled his way to the front of the audience, and was barking out questions to the cadets as they boarded the shuttle. She was happy she knew where he was, so she could actively ignore him as she passed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She gave Mother one final hug, and turned and walked along the long ramp up to the shuttle. With every step away from her, Aisha felt more and more alone. As the entrance loomed toward her, she felt the urge to turn and run back to Mother’s welcoming arms. Mother would hold her and protect her, and to heck with anyone who would criticize her for not going through with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of the spaceport on a hawaiian island&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But she didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She continued step-by-step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the top of the ramp, she turned for one more look back at the Earth. She caught Mother’s eye as she waved frantically, blowing kisses and smiling. “That’s my little girl!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She raised her hand to wave, hearing cameras popping, and returned the smile before turning to enter the shuttle. Her feet suddenly felt heavy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was really going through with this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was really leaving home and going into &lt;em&gt;space&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each step seemed to be a chore, doubt and indecision weighing on her more heavily than gravity ever could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step-by-step she continued forward. The entrance lobby curved away from the door, and in a few moments, the daylight was lost. Words she had learned from history came back to her. Alea iacta est. She smiled, thinking that her Classics teacher would be proud of her. The die is cast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of the entrance lobby of a space elevator shuttle, windows overlooking to ocean beyond&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interior of the shuttle was clearly designed to impress and soothe its occupants. Instead of the functional ships of yesteryear, it was all polished chrome and intricately-designed surfaces. In the days of rocket travel to the stars, every ounce of payload had to be carefully measured, with no room for luxury, as propelling something into orbit required enormous amounts of energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Space Elevator changed all that, so designers of spacecraft were free to allow their occupants to be comfortable with traveling into space. This was also an important factor as many more people would leave the surface of the Earth – and a good, comfortable experience made it more tolerable, and thus less training was necessary. Indeed, Aisha had little more training than a couple of video tutorials explaining how to deal with weightlessness, and what to eat or not to eat prior to boarding. It was also good advice to use the bathroom before getting on the ship, for while facilities were available, using them in weightless conditions wasn’t optimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She climbed stairs to the observation deck where she would spend most of the journey. The deck was a wide circle with multi story windows, and acceleration couches arranged facing outwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-7.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of the space elevator observation deck&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As we rise up the cable, the shuttle will spin slowly,” she had remembered the tutorial video telling her. “So pick any seat, and you’ll still be able to see everything.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-9.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of Aisha in an acceleration sofa&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deck was terraced, so that seats near the back would still have a great view, and their occupants may not have the feeling of vertigo that those closer to the front would encounter. She picked one in the back row, next to an Asian girl who looked about Aisha’s age. The girl was intensely reading a book on her tablet, and didn’t look up as Aisha sat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-8.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of Aisha in an acceleration sofa&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She suddenly spoke. “Aisha Parks, celebrity.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha looked at her. “I’m not sure about that.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The girl looked up, and her intense eyes searched Aisha’s. “Good to know,” she said finally, reaching a hand out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Soo-Kyung Kim,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-10.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of Aisha meeting Soo-Kyung&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I don’t need to tell you my name, I guess.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soo-Kyung smiled. Her plain face lit up when she smiled. She was beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So where are you from?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soo-Kyung smiled again. “You haven’t heard of me? Good. I guess I am not a celebrity, either.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an odd answer, and from Soo-Kyung’s reaction, it was clear that Aisha’s confusion was written on her face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I think we are going to be good friends,” said Soo-Kyung. “I like how you are straightforward. I am too, but that intimidates some people.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-11.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of Aisha and Soo-Kyung chatting&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So where are you from?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am from a small village called Sijungho,” continued Soo Kyung. “There’s not much to see there.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Sounds Korean,” said Aisha. “You from South Korea?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“North Korea,” corrected Soo-Kyung. “I’ve never even been to South Korea.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha felt her insides go cold. Against her will, she shuddered a little, and felt a sob begin to escape from her throat. Her father had died as a result of radiation sickness incurred in the second Korean War. And there was a North Korean girl here with her. Going into space with her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She knew there was incredulity in her voice, but she couldn’t mask it. “Are you going to the Academy too?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yes,” said Soo-Kyung. “And don’t worry, I’m as surprised as you are.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s what you meant by celebrity?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It seems the media made as big a deal about me being the first North Korean as it did about you being the first African-American to go through open enrollment. It’s all a sham though, isn’t it?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m beginning to gather that.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I mean, when the Academy was first built, it was apparent that it was for the Elites, most of whom are from Western society, with a few Russians and Chinese thrown in to get funding. Nobody really knows who the students were, but it was typically those who would be in private elite schools on the surface, so being in space made little difference.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha thought about what Soo-Kyung was saying, and realized that she was right. Amazing that she had never thought of this herself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Korean girl continued. “Now that they are all in place and established, it’s time to open it up to the rest of the world, so we can get their proverbial ‘sloppy seconds’, I guess.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s an academy,” said Aisha. “And we’re cadets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The cannon fodder, while they are the officers ordering us around.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So why are you going through with it? Why am &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; going through with it?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soo-Kyung shrugged. “Because it’s better than &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going through with it. Besides, there might be something great waiting for normal people like us.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“My father died in Korea,” said Aisha, surprising even herself at the change in subject. “But he always told my mother to tell me that I had a destiny. That the emerging age of space flight was one in which we must be free to explore the universe. He fought so that that freedom would still exist, so that I could do this. I can’t turn back.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Most of my family died in the same war,” said Soo-Kyung. “But nothing ever really changed, did it?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aisha realized that she must have sounded bitter, and the bitterness was reflected in Soo-Kyung’s answer. 
“I’m sorry,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No need,” said Soo-Kyung. “I’m glad that you are open and honest with me. Most people, particularly outside of my country, are not. They learn about where I’m from and think I need special treatment. I don’t. I’ve learned to stand on my own.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I wish I had your strength.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You don’t,” said Soo-Kyung, suddenly serious. “&lt;em&gt;That&lt;/em&gt; kind of strength comes from trying to make a life in a country destroyed by nuclear war. You never want it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-12.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of Soo-Kyung as a little girl in North Korea as nukes fall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s why we’re going into space, isn’t it? To make sure that wars like those will never put our species’ survival at risk.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That would be nice,” said Soo-Kyung. “But if anything I think it will cause more wars and hardship before things get better.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Why?” 
“Because the only thing that stopped the entire world from burning during the war over my country was that it was the only world we have. If we discover more planets, livable ones, that will no longer be the case. And I want to be as far away from this world as possible before the next bombs fall.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before Aisha could answer, the soft tone of the launch warning sounded. The rocket boost would be gentler than a typical aircraft take off, but safety protocols required that they be buckled into their crash seats in case anything went wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She rolled her eyes and smiled, and strapped herself in. When everything was snug, she turned to look at Soo-Kyung. Their eyes met again, and Soo-Kyung bowed slightly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The engines kicked in, and their seats lurched a little. From all around came the muffled sounds of the rockets roaring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the windows, Aisha could see the ground begin to slowly fall away. Within a few seconds the flotilla was no longer visible, and as they began to rise, she could see the entire outline of the nearby Kiritimati, where only yesterday they had landed. It felt like an eternity ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She wondered how Mother felt, watching her shuttle rise slowly to the sky. As suddenly as they had begun, the rockets cut out, and there was another slight lurch as the inertia of the ship was stopped. She remembered the video training – this was the scariest part of the trip, where the shuttle, under normal gravity, could fall back to Earth and kill everyone aboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it didn’t, and the force on the Space Elevator started pushing them skyward, with ever-increasing speed. The horizon began to spin also, and as they rose up, she watched the island recede. Before long they were high enough to see that the horizon was curved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was it. This was for real. She was headed into space!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://storage.googleapis.com/odml-codelabs/Images/SC/Part1/space-cadets-3-13.png&quot; alt=&quot;Midjourney generated image of Aisha&apos;s mother watching the shuttle lift into space&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="books" /><category term="personal" /><summary type="html">Continuing my experiment to illustrate a novel using AI text-to-image generation techniques. In this article, I’m going to use MidJourney. Previous chapters used DALL-E. Let me know what you think twitter.com/lmoroney CHAPTER 3 Launch We should always reach for the sky. From the very beginning of history, our ancestors were looking up and wondering what was beyond their reach. The stars were calling them. They weaved stories of gods and angels, but behind them all was the intense desire to be out there. A desire born of an instinct for survival. It’s something we’ve forgotten as we’ve become civilized. We’ve become comfortable in our homes, our cities and our countries. We’ve defeated nature and haven’t had the same worries that they had. But we lost something in that complacency, I fear. And now, as our world gets overcrowded, as our environment collapses under us, we need to rediscover it. We need to look up, and not worry about tripping as we race towards a new destiny. We will be those gods and angels if we want to. And you can be one of them, if you just keep trying, and never give up… THE SPACE ELEVATOR. Its relatively simple name belied the sheer scale of it. Craning her neck, Aisha looked up as it disappeared impossibly into the deep blue sky. The ‘shuttle’ was a box-like structure that could easily pass for another building, but for the rocket boosters placed on its corners. These boosters would provide the initial ‘launch’ to get the craft moving out of its gravitational inertia. After that, the rotation of the Earth would take over and drive the shuttle up the cable into orbit. She was so glad for last night’s dinner with Mother. Beforehand, it had felt like there was a tension building between them. Mother’s basking in her status had gotten under Aisha’s skin, and she had been worried that she might blow up at her before leaving. She was worried that she might end up regretting it, but there was only so long she could bite her tongue. She almost thanked the reporter for his rude question. It had brought them closer together. She felt a pang of pride again at Mother’s words that she had done exactly what Father would have done. Of course, the same reporter had wrestled his way to the front of the audience, and was barking out questions to the cadets as they boarded the shuttle. She was happy she knew where he was, so she could actively ignore him as she passed. She gave Mother one final hug, and turned and walked along the long ramp up to the shuttle. With every step away from her, Aisha felt more and more alone. As the entrance loomed toward her, she felt the urge to turn and run back to Mother’s welcoming arms. Mother would hold her and protect her, and to heck with anyone who would criticize her for not going through with it. But she didn’t. She continued step-by-step. At the top of the ramp, she turned for one more look back at the Earth. She caught Mother’s eye as she waved frantically, blowing kisses and smiling. “That’s my little girl!” She raised her hand to wave, hearing cameras popping, and returned the smile before turning to enter the shuttle. Her feet suddenly felt heavy. She was really going through with this. She was really leaving home and going into space. Each step seemed to be a chore, doubt and indecision weighing on her more heavily than gravity ever could. Step-by-step she continued forward. The entrance lobby curved away from the door, and in a few moments, the daylight was lost. Words she had learned from history came back to her. Alea iacta est. She smiled, thinking that her Classics teacher would be proud of her. The die is cast. The interior of the shuttle was clearly designed to impress and soothe its occupants. Instead of the functional ships of yesteryear, it was all polished chrome and intricately-designed surfaces. In the days of rocket travel to the stars, every ounce of payload had to be carefully measured, with no room for luxury, as propelling something into orbit required enormous amounts of energy. The Space Elevator changed all that, so designers of spacecraft were free to allow their occupants to be comfortable with traveling into space. This was also an important factor as many more people would leave the surface of the Earth – and a good, comfortable experience made it more tolerable, and thus less training was necessary. Indeed, Aisha had little more training than a couple of video tutorials explaining how to deal with weightlessness, and what to eat or not to eat prior to boarding. It was also good advice to use the bathroom before getting on the ship, for while facilities were available, using them in weightless conditions wasn’t optimal. She climbed stairs to the observation deck where she would spend most of the journey. The deck was a wide circle with multi story windows, and acceleration couches arranged facing outwards. “As we rise up the cable, the shuttle will spin slowly,” she had remembered the tutorial video telling her. “So pick any seat, and you’ll still be able to see everything.” The deck was terraced, so that seats near the back would still have a great view, and their occupants may not have the feeling of vertigo that those closer to the front would encounter. She picked one in the back row, next to an Asian girl who looked about Aisha’s age. The girl was intensely reading a book on her tablet, and didn’t look up as Aisha sat. She suddenly spoke. “Aisha Parks, celebrity.” Aisha looked at her. “I’m not sure about that.” The girl looked up, and her intense eyes searched Aisha’s. “Good to know,” she said finally, reaching a hand out. “Soo-Kyung Kim,” she said. “I don’t need to tell you my name, I guess.” Soo-Kyung smiled. Her plain face lit up when she smiled. She was beautiful. “So where are you from?” Soo-Kyung smiled again. “You haven’t heard of me? Good. I guess I am not a celebrity, either.” Such an odd answer, and from Soo-Kyung’s reaction, it was clear that Aisha’s confusion was written on her face. “I think we are going to be good friends,” said Soo-Kyung. “I like how you are straightforward. I am too, but that intimidates some people.” “So where are you from?” “I am from a small village called Sijungho,” continued Soo Kyung. “There’s not much to see there.” “Sounds Korean,” said Aisha. “You from South Korea?” “North Korea,” corrected Soo-Kyung. “I’ve never even been to South Korea.” Aisha felt her insides go cold. Against her will, she shuddered a little, and felt a sob begin to escape from her throat. Her father had died as a result of radiation sickness incurred in the second Korean War. And there was a North Korean girl here with her. Going into space with her. She knew there was incredulity in her voice, but she couldn’t mask it. “Are you going to the Academy too?” “Yes,” said Soo-Kyung. “And don’t worry, I’m as surprised as you are.” “That’s what you meant by celebrity?” “It seems the media made as big a deal about me being the first North Korean as it did about you being the first African-American to go through open enrollment. It’s all a sham though, isn’t it?” “I’m beginning to gather that.” “I mean, when the Academy was first built, it was apparent that it was for the Elites, most of whom are from Western society, with a few Russians and Chinese thrown in to get funding. Nobody really knows who the students were, but it was typically those who would be in private elite schools on the surface, so being in space made little difference.” Aisha thought about what Soo-Kyung was saying, and realized that she was right. Amazing that she had never thought of this herself. The Korean girl continued. “Now that they are all in place and established, it’s time to open it up to the rest of the world, so we can get their proverbial ‘sloppy seconds’, I guess.” “It’s an academy,” said Aisha. “And we’re cadets.” “The cannon fodder, while they are the officers ordering us around.” “So why are you going through with it? Why am I going through with it?” Soo-Kyung shrugged. “Because it’s better than not going through with it. Besides, there might be something great waiting for normal people like us.” “My father died in Korea,” said Aisha, surprising even herself at the change in subject. “But he always told my mother to tell me that I had a destiny. That the emerging age of space flight was one in which we must be free to explore the universe. He fought so that that freedom would still exist, so that I could do this. I can’t turn back.” “Most of my family died in the same war,” said Soo-Kyung. “But nothing ever really changed, did it?” Aisha realized that she must have sounded bitter, and the bitterness was reflected in Soo-Kyung’s answer. “I’m sorry,” she said. “No need,” said Soo-Kyung. “I’m glad that you are open and honest with me. Most people, particularly outside of my country, are not. They learn about where I’m from and think I need special treatment. I don’t. I’ve learned to stand on my own.” “I wish I had your strength.” “You don’t,” said Soo-Kyung, suddenly serious. “That kind of strength comes from trying to make a life in a country destroyed by nuclear war. You never want it.” “That’s why we’re going into space, isn’t it? To make sure that wars like those will never put our species’ survival at risk.” “That would be nice,” said Soo-Kyung. “But if anything I think it will cause more wars and hardship before things get better.” “Why?” “Because the only thing that stopped the entire world from burning during the war over my country was that it was the only world we have. If we discover more planets, livable ones, that will no longer be the case. And I want to be as far away from this world as possible before the next bombs fall.” Before Aisha could answer, the soft tone of the launch warning sounded. The rocket boost would be gentler than a typical aircraft take off, but safety protocols required that they be buckled into their crash seats in case anything went wrong. She rolled her eyes and smiled, and strapped herself in. When everything was snug, she turned to look at Soo-Kyung. Their eyes met again, and Soo-Kyung bowed slightly. The engines kicked in, and their seats lurched a little. From all around came the muffled sounds of the rockets roaring. Through the windows, Aisha could see the ground begin to slowly fall away. Within a few seconds the flotilla was no longer visible, and as they began to rise, she could see the entire outline of the nearby Kiritimati, where only yesterday they had landed. It felt like an eternity ago. She wondered how Mother felt, watching her shuttle rise slowly to the sky. As suddenly as they had begun, the rockets cut out, and there was another slight lurch as the inertia of the ship was stopped. She remembered the video training – this was the scariest part of the trip, where the shuttle, under normal gravity, could fall back to Earth and kill everyone aboard. But it didn’t, and the force on the Space Elevator started pushing them skyward, with ever-increasing speed. The horizon began to spin also, and as they rose up, she watched the island recede. Before long they were high enough to see that the horizon was curved. This was it. This was for real. She was headed into space!</summary></entry></feed>