<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-01-30T14:34:47-08:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Laurence Moroney - The AI Guy.</title><subtitle>This is the blog and general web site of Laurence Moroney, author, lecturer, teacher and AI lead at Google with Musings on AI, Quantum and other future tech
</subtitle><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><entry><title type="html">From Blog to Video with Veed</title><link href="/2024/01/30/veed.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Blog to Video with Veed" /><published>2024-01-30T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-30T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/2024/01/30/veed</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/01/30/veed.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-case-study-in-turning-a-blog-post-into-a-video&quot;&gt;A case study in turning a blog post into a video…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days back, I wrote this &lt;a href=&quot;https://laurencemoroney.com/2024/01/27/materials.html&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;, covering a passion of mine – how AI can be used to change things that we use every day, and while so doing, improving costs, efficiency, and reducing waste, giving an overall positive impact on society and environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then I turned it into a video like this! It took about an hour of tweaking, and maybe $10 worth of my subscription credits to create this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;extensions extensions--video&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VPNFioRQ47M?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was achieved using a service caled VEED, that I discovered via their ChatGPT plugin called ‘Video GPT by VEED’. And while I didn’t use that tool to create this video, it struck my that by creating that custom GPT, they improved their discovery, and won me as a customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VEED gives you an in-browser video creation and editing tool with all the basic bells and whistles you’d expect like a timeline editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/veed.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Veed Editor in action&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where it &lt;em&gt;shines&lt;/em&gt; is in its use of AI to provide services above and beyond. Some examples of this are&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The AI-Generated Avatar. The news reader in the above video is entirely AI generated – or at least her lip sync is!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Automated subtitles, including emphasis words&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And my current favorite – translation!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explore them here in Cantonese and Japanese:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;extensions extensions--video&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/27AMp5CnTO0?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;extensions extensions--video&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NdaCstomns4?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, this can be a terrific tool to help bloggers and content creators to extend their reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not perfect – occasionally creating the AI avatar crashes, but still uses up some of your minutes (I have 60 in my annual subscription, and after creating this video, I have 56 left) – and the transitions can be awkward if you created multiple AI avatar snippets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the whole, it’s fun, though! And I’d thoroughly recommend trying it out. I’m going to create more stuff, including trying something that clones my own voice!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="futures" /><summary type="html">A case study in turning a blog post into a video… A few days back, I wrote this blog post, covering a passion of mine – how AI can be used to change things that we use every day, and while so doing, improving costs, efficiency, and reducing waste, giving an overall positive impact on society and environment. And then I turned it into a video like this! It took about an hour of tweaking, and maybe $10 worth of my subscription credits to create this: This was achieved using a service caled VEED, that I discovered via their ChatGPT plugin called ‘Video GPT by VEED’. And while I didn’t use that tool to create this video, it struck my that by creating that custom GPT, they improved their discovery, and won me as a customer. VEED gives you an in-browser video creation and editing tool with all the basic bells and whistles you’d expect like a timeline editor. Where it shines is in its use of AI to provide services above and beyond. Some examples of this are The AI-Generated Avatar. The news reader in the above video is entirely AI generated – or at least her lip sync is! Automated subtitles, including emphasis words And my current favorite – translation! Explore them here in Cantonese and Japanese: Overall, this can be a terrific tool to help bloggers and content creators to extend their reach. It’s not perfect – occasionally creating the AI avatar crashes, but still uses up some of your minutes (I have 60 in my annual subscription, and after creating this video, I have 56 left) – and the transitions can be awkward if you created multiple AI avatar snippets. On the whole, it’s fun, though! And I’d thoroughly recommend trying it out. I’m going to create more stuff, including trying something that clones my own voice!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring text to video with DeCohere</title><link href="/2024/01/28/test2vid-copy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring text to video with DeCohere" /><published>2024-01-28T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-28T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/2024/01/28/test2vid%20copy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/01/28/test2vid-copy.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;exploring-the-wonders-of-ai-generated-imagery-with-decohere-a-personal-journey&quot;&gt;Exploring the Wonders of AI-Generated Imagery with Decohere: A Personal Journey&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the ever-evolving world of technology, AI’s role in creative fields is becoming increasingly prominent, as I recently explored through a fun experience with the Decohere website. This blog post will delve into two fascinating instances that highlight the capabilities of AI in generating unique visual content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/decohere.png&quot; alt=&quot;A sci-fi image of a Japanese girl&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;real-time-image-creation-a-sci-fi-vision&quot;&gt;Real-Time Image Creation: A Sci-Fi Vision&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first interaction with Decohere involved crafting a scenario featuring a young Asian girl in a sci-fi setting. The platform’s real-time response was impressive; it kept pace with my edits, dynamically generating images as I refined my prompt. This experience wasn’t just about creating a static image; it was a journey through imagination, where each edit brought a new aspect of the scene to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;extensions extensions--video&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/iCzN0k_OoNE?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I particularly liked how they underwent an enhancement process once I finished typing. This step brought a level of depth and clarity to the visuals, transforming them into more polished and vivid representations of my original idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of all – while these images may have limitations in how they could be used for a real production – due to coherence issues (more on that in a moment) – I can see where tools like this can be excellent in unlocking creativity. For example, it might be hard for me to think about details of how her uniform might look, if I was writing a novel. Exploring different views like this can help inspire me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I mention coherence – you can see what I mean in the images – when it generates people, they’ll all be different. If had wanted to create a movie or graphic novel with this young girl in it, I’d have challenges – because if I were to describe her in a different environment, or interacting with people, she, her clothing, and other details would be different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;venturing-into-ai-generated-video-a-navajo-girls-sci-fi-adventure&quot;&gt;Venturing into AI-Generated Video: A Navajo Girl’s Sci-Fi Adventure&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second part of my exploration took an even more ambitious turn as I tested Decohere’s video creation tool. Here, the task was to create a video depicting a young Navajo girl in a sci-fi environment. The result, although sped up for demonstration purposes, was nothing short of astonishing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video’s creation process illustrated both the strengths and limitations of current AI technology. While the AI managed to craft a visually appealing narrative, there were noticeable inconsistencies, particularly in the character’s clothing, which varied throughout the video. This highlighted a challenge in maintaining coherence in AI-generated content over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite these variations, the overall quality of the video was impressive, showcasing AI’s potential in creating complex and dynamic visual narratives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;extensions extensions--video&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/lXAjGJrI2G4?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;embracing-the-future-of-ai-in-creativity&quot;&gt;Embracing the Future of AI in Creativity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These experiences with Decohere should hopefully open your eyes to the vast potential of AI in the realm of creative digital media. The ability to generate images and videos based on specific prompts is not only a testament to the technology’s advancement but also a glimpse into a future where AI can be a collaborative tool for artists and storytellers. My personal opinion is that it will be most effective when used as an enhancement to your creative workflow – giving you inspiration and/or taking some of the slower and more labor intensive parts of the creation process and automating them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we continue to explore and refine these technologies, the possibilities for creative expression are boundless. Decohere is but one example – and I’ll explore others in time, but it’s a pretty cool one!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[This Blog Post was written with the assistance of LLMs]&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="futures" /><summary type="html">Exploring the Wonders of AI-Generated Imagery with Decohere: A Personal Journey In the ever-evolving world of technology, AI’s role in creative fields is becoming increasingly prominent, as I recently explored through a fun experience with the Decohere website. This blog post will delve into two fascinating instances that highlight the capabilities of AI in generating unique visual content. Real-Time Image Creation: A Sci-Fi Vision My first interaction with Decohere involved crafting a scenario featuring a young Asian girl in a sci-fi setting. The platform’s real-time response was impressive; it kept pace with my edits, dynamically generating images as I refined my prompt. This experience wasn’t just about creating a static image; it was a journey through imagination, where each edit brought a new aspect of the scene to life. I particularly liked how they underwent an enhancement process once I finished typing. This step brought a level of depth and clarity to the visuals, transforming them into more polished and vivid representations of my original idea. Most of all – while these images may have limitations in how they could be used for a real production – due to coherence issues (more on that in a moment) – I can see where tools like this can be excellent in unlocking creativity. For example, it might be hard for me to think about details of how her uniform might look, if I was writing a novel. Exploring different views like this can help inspire me. When I mention coherence – you can see what I mean in the images – when it generates people, they’ll all be different. If had wanted to create a movie or graphic novel with this young girl in it, I’d have challenges – because if I were to describe her in a different environment, or interacting with people, she, her clothing, and other details would be different. Venturing into AI-Generated Video: A Navajo Girl’s Sci-Fi Adventure The second part of my exploration took an even more ambitious turn as I tested Decohere’s video creation tool. Here, the task was to create a video depicting a young Navajo girl in a sci-fi environment. The result, although sped up for demonstration purposes, was nothing short of astonishing. The video’s creation process illustrated both the strengths and limitations of current AI technology. While the AI managed to craft a visually appealing narrative, there were noticeable inconsistencies, particularly in the character’s clothing, which varied throughout the video. This highlighted a challenge in maintaining coherence in AI-generated content over time. Despite these variations, the overall quality of the video was impressive, showcasing AI’s potential in creating complex and dynamic visual narratives. Embracing the Future of AI in Creativity These experiences with Decohere should hopefully open your eyes to the vast potential of AI in the realm of creative digital media. The ability to generate images and videos based on specific prompts is not only a testament to the technology’s advancement but also a glimpse into a future where AI can be a collaborative tool for artists and storytellers. My personal opinion is that it will be most effective when used as an enhancement to your creative workflow – giving you inspiration and/or taking some of the slower and more labor intensive parts of the creation process and automating them. As we continue to explore and refine these technologies, the possibilities for creative expression are boundless. Decohere is but one example – and I’ll explore others in time, but it’s a pretty cool one! [This Blog Post was written with the assistance of LLMs]</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Revolutionizing Batteries with AI</title><link href="/2024/01/27/materials.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Revolutionizing Batteries with AI" /><published>2024-01-27T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-27T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/2024/01/27/materials</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/01/27/materials.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;revolutionizing-batteries-with-ai-a-leap-towards-sustainable-technology&quot;&gt;Revolutionizing Batteries with AI: A Leap Towards Sustainable Technology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a world increasingly dependent on technology, the quest for efficient and environmentally friendly power sources is more crucial than ever. A recent breakthrough, as reported by New Scientist, showcases how artificial intelligence (AI) is leading this charge, offering a glimpse into a future where technology and sustainability go hand in hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;understanding-the-breakthrough&quot;&gt;Understanding the Breakthrough&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The heart of this advancement lies in an AI-designed battery that dramatically reduces the need for lithium - a costly and environmentally taxing material. This isn’t just a minor tweak; it’s a game-changing reduction of up to 70% less lithium compared to conventional batteries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-role-of-ai-in-material-discovery&quot;&gt;The Role of AI in Material Discovery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first glance, AI and material science might seem like distant cousins. However, they share a common language: the language of patterns. AI excels at identifying patterns and making predictions, a skill that proves invaluable in the realm of material science. In this case, AI algorithms sifted through millions of potential materials, identifying the ones most likely to yield effective, less lithium-dependent batteries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-process-from-data-to-discovery&quot;&gt;The Process: From Data to Discovery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine a world of possibilities, millions of potential materials each holding the key to the next big discovery. The challenge lies not in creating these materials but in finding the proverbial needle in the haystack. This is where AI steps in. By rapidly analyzing and dismissing unsuitable candidates, AI narrows down the search to a manageable list, transforming years of human effort into mere months of computation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/filter.png&quot; alt=&quot;An AI filtering many materials into fewer valuable ones&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;from-simulation-to-reality&quot;&gt;From Simulation to Reality&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The journey from AI-simulated predictions to real-world applications is a critical one. In this scenario, the AI’s recommendations were not just theoretical musings but were synthesized and tested in the lab. The result? A functional battery that, despite its lower conductivity, stands as a testament to the potential of AI-driven material innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-this-matters&quot;&gt;Why This Matters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This breakthrough is more than just a scientific curiosity; it’s a beacon of hope in our quest for sustainable technology. Lithium, while effective, comes with a hefty environmental cost. By reducing our reliance on this mineral, we pave the way for more sustainable and less harmful technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;looking-ahead&quot;&gt;Looking Ahead&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of this project is a clarion call to the scientific community. AI’s ability to augment and accelerate the material discovery process is a tool we can no longer afford to overlook. As we stand on the brink of a technological revolution, it’s clear that AI will be a driving force, not just in computing, but in helping us build a more sustainable world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, the collaboration between AI and material science is more than just a novel experiment; it’s a pathway to a future where technology and the environment can coexist harmoniously. This AI-driven battery design is just the beginning. As we harness the power of AI for material discovery, we open doors to endless possibilities - cleaner energy, sustainable technologies, and a brighter future for our planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a deeper dive into this fascinating development, check out the links below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newscientist.com/article/2411374-ai-comes-up-with-battery-design-that-uses-70-per-cent-less-lithium/&quot;&gt;AI comes up with battery design that uses 70 per cent less lithium.” New Scientist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.04070&quot;&gt;Research paper on arXiv.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[This Blog Post was written with the assistance of LLMs]&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="futures" /><summary type="html">Revolutionizing Batteries with AI: A Leap Towards Sustainable Technology In a world increasingly dependent on technology, the quest for efficient and environmentally friendly power sources is more crucial than ever. A recent breakthrough, as reported by New Scientist, showcases how artificial intelligence (AI) is leading this charge, offering a glimpse into a future where technology and sustainability go hand in hand. Understanding the Breakthrough The heart of this advancement lies in an AI-designed battery that dramatically reduces the need for lithium - a costly and environmentally taxing material. This isn’t just a minor tweak; it’s a game-changing reduction of up to 70% less lithium compared to conventional batteries. The Role of AI in Material Discovery At first glance, AI and material science might seem like distant cousins. However, they share a common language: the language of patterns. AI excels at identifying patterns and making predictions, a skill that proves invaluable in the realm of material science. In this case, AI algorithms sifted through millions of potential materials, identifying the ones most likely to yield effective, less lithium-dependent batteries. The Process: From Data to Discovery Imagine a world of possibilities, millions of potential materials each holding the key to the next big discovery. The challenge lies not in creating these materials but in finding the proverbial needle in the haystack. This is where AI steps in. By rapidly analyzing and dismissing unsuitable candidates, AI narrows down the search to a manageable list, transforming years of human effort into mere months of computation. From Simulation to Reality The journey from AI-simulated predictions to real-world applications is a critical one. In this scenario, the AI’s recommendations were not just theoretical musings but were synthesized and tested in the lab. The result? A functional battery that, despite its lower conductivity, stands as a testament to the potential of AI-driven material innovation. Why This Matters This breakthrough is more than just a scientific curiosity; it’s a beacon of hope in our quest for sustainable technology. Lithium, while effective, comes with a hefty environmental cost. By reducing our reliance on this mineral, we pave the way for more sustainable and less harmful technologies. Looking Ahead The success of this project is a clarion call to the scientific community. AI’s ability to augment and accelerate the material discovery process is a tool we can no longer afford to overlook. As we stand on the brink of a technological revolution, it’s clear that AI will be a driving force, not just in computing, but in helping us build a more sustainable world. Conclusion In conclusion, the collaboration between AI and material science is more than just a novel experiment; it’s a pathway to a future where technology and the environment can coexist harmoniously. This AI-driven battery design is just the beginning. As we harness the power of AI for material discovery, we open doors to endless possibilities - cleaner energy, sustainable technologies, and a brighter future for our planet. For a deeper dive into this fascinating development, check out the links below. References: AI comes up with battery design that uses 70 per cent less lithium.” New Scientist. Research paper on arXiv. [This Blog Post was written with the assistance of LLMs]</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NFTs - Navigating Beyond the Hype Towards Real Value</title><link href="/2024/01/26/nft.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NFTs - Navigating Beyond the Hype Towards Real Value" /><published>2024-01-26T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-26T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/2024/01/26/nft</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/01/26/nft.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/boredape.png&quot; alt=&quot;A Bored Ape&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the wake of the cryptocurrency boom, Non-Fungible Tokens (NFTs) emerged as the digital darlings of the art and collectibles world. However, as we navigate through 2024, the luster of NFTs seems to be fading. A recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://dappgambl.com/nfts/dead-nfts/&quot;&gt;report by DappGambl&lt;/a&gt; highlights that a staggering 95% of NFT collections are now considered ‘dead,’ with little to no market value. This stark revelation is a wake-up call to the NFT community and potential investors, signaling a shift from the gold rush mentality to a more sustainable and value-oriented approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial appeal of NFTs lay in their novelty as unique digital assets - be it art, music, or video clips. This allure drove a speculative frenzy, culminating in record-breaking sales and headline-grabbing auctions. However, as with any gold rush, the inevitable market correction has left many investors holding assets with diminished or no value. According to DappGambl, the majority of NFT collections have failed to find a sustainable market, reflecting an oversupply and a lack of adequate demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps more pressing than the market dynamics is the environmental cost of NFTs. The energy-intensive process of minting NFTs on blockchain networks has significant carbon footprints. With thousands of NFTs generating emissions equivalent to that of small countries, the environmental impact is no longer a secondary concern but a primary issue that needs addressing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/pile.png&quot; alt=&quot;A Waste Pile of old NFTs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amidst this backdrop, the future of NFTs hinges on a critical pivot - from transient, speculative assets to digital assets with intrinsic, tangible value. The era of NFTs serving merely as digital avatars or speculative art pieces is waning. Instead, the real opportunity lies in leveraging the unique properties of NFTs for applications with inherent utility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine digital assets that are not just collectibles but integral to digital identity, gaming, real estate, and more. NFTs could represent fractional ownership in physical assets, offer exclusive access to services, or play a crucial role in supply chain management. The key is in their uniqueness and the immutable proof of ownership that blockchain technology provides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the evolution of NFTs must be cognizant of the environmental impact. The shift towards more energy-efficient blockchain protocols or the integration of eco-friendly practices in NFT creation and trading could mitigate the environmental concerns, aligning the NFT market with broader sustainability goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, while the hype around NFTs as speculative art pieces may be fading, their potential as digital assets with real-world utility is only beginning to be tapped. As the market matures and becomes more discerning, the future of NFTs will likely be defined by their ability to offer value beyond the digital realm, aligning with environmental considerations and practical use cases. The gold rush might be over, but a more sustainable and value-driven era for NFTs is on the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[This Blog Post was written with the assistance of LLMs]&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="futures" /><summary type="html">In the wake of the cryptocurrency boom, Non-Fungible Tokens (NFTs) emerged as the digital darlings of the art and collectibles world. However, as we navigate through 2024, the luster of NFTs seems to be fading. A recent report by DappGambl highlights that a staggering 95% of NFT collections are now considered ‘dead,’ with little to no market value. This stark revelation is a wake-up call to the NFT community and potential investors, signaling a shift from the gold rush mentality to a more sustainable and value-oriented approach. The initial appeal of NFTs lay in their novelty as unique digital assets - be it art, music, or video clips. This allure drove a speculative frenzy, culminating in record-breaking sales and headline-grabbing auctions. However, as with any gold rush, the inevitable market correction has left many investors holding assets with diminished or no value. According to DappGambl, the majority of NFT collections have failed to find a sustainable market, reflecting an oversupply and a lack of adequate demand. But perhaps more pressing than the market dynamics is the environmental cost of NFTs. The energy-intensive process of minting NFTs on blockchain networks has significant carbon footprints. With thousands of NFTs generating emissions equivalent to that of small countries, the environmental impact is no longer a secondary concern but a primary issue that needs addressing. Amidst this backdrop, the future of NFTs hinges on a critical pivot - from transient, speculative assets to digital assets with intrinsic, tangible value. The era of NFTs serving merely as digital avatars or speculative art pieces is waning. Instead, the real opportunity lies in leveraging the unique properties of NFTs for applications with inherent utility. Imagine digital assets that are not just collectibles but integral to digital identity, gaming, real estate, and more. NFTs could represent fractional ownership in physical assets, offer exclusive access to services, or play a crucial role in supply chain management. The key is in their uniqueness and the immutable proof of ownership that blockchain technology provides. Moreover, the evolution of NFTs must be cognizant of the environmental impact. The shift towards more energy-efficient blockchain protocols or the integration of eco-friendly practices in NFT creation and trading could mitigate the environmental concerns, aligning the NFT market with broader sustainability goals. In conclusion, while the hype around NFTs as speculative art pieces may be fading, their potential as digital assets with real-world utility is only beginning to be tapped. As the market matures and becomes more discerning, the future of NFTs will likely be defined by their ability to offer value beyond the digital realm, aligning with environmental considerations and practical use cases. The gold rush might be over, but a more sustainable and value-driven era for NFTs is on the horizon. [This Blog Post was written with the assistance of LLMs]</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Prompt Engineering Best Practices</title><link href="/2023/12/19/prompts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Prompt Engineering Best Practices" /><published>2023-12-19T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-12-19T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/2023/12/19/prompts</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/12/19/prompts.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;effective-prompt-design-strategies-and-best-practices&quot;&gt;Effective Prompt Design: Strategies and Best Practices&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The art of prompt design is pivotal in harnessing the full potential of AI models. A well-crafted prompt can be the difference between an average and an exceptional AI response. My team in Google have published guidelines for this that are well worth &lt;a href=&quot;https://ai.google.dev/docs/prompt_best_practices&quot;&gt;checking out in more detail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/prompt_eng.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Prompt Engineering, visualized&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some key strategies and best practices to consider:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;clarity-in-instructions&quot;&gt;Clarity in Instructions:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clear, concise instructions are crucial. They guide the AI to understand and respond accurately to the task at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;inclusion-of-examples&quot;&gt;Inclusion of Examples:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Including examples in prompts can significantly enhance the model’s understanding and accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;partial-input-completion&quot;&gt;Partial Input Completion:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Designing prompts that allow the model to complete partial inputs can lead to more precise and relevant responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;specific-response-formats&quot;&gt;Specific Response Formats:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prompting for responses in specific formats ensures consistency and relevance in the outputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;contextual-information&quot;&gt;Contextual Information:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding context to prompts helps in refining and focusing the model’s responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;effective-use-of-prefixes&quot;&gt;Effective Use of Prefixes:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prefixes can guide the model in understanding the kind of response expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;experimentation&quot;&gt;Experimentation:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trying different phrasings, parameter values, and prompt structures can lead to improved outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;iterative-design&quot;&gt;Iterative Design:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continuous refinement and iteration of prompts are key to achieving optimal responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fallback-responses&quot;&gt;Fallback Responses:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Planning for fallback responses in case of inadequate or incorrect outputs is essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;caution-with-factual-generation&quot;&gt;Caution with Factual Generation:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be wary of over-reliance on the model for generating factual content, and exercise caution with tasks involving complex logic or mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These strategies, rooted in Google AI’s guidelines, are fundamental in crafting effective prompts that lead to high-quality, reliable AI outputs. For a more detailed exploration of these best practices, visit Google AI’s Prompt Design Strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="futures" /><summary type="html">Effective Prompt Design: Strategies and Best Practices The art of prompt design is pivotal in harnessing the full potential of AI models. A well-crafted prompt can be the difference between an average and an exceptional AI response. My team in Google have published guidelines for this that are well worth checking out in more detail Here are some key strategies and best practices to consider: Clarity in Instructions: Clear, concise instructions are crucial. They guide the AI to understand and respond accurately to the task at hand. Inclusion of Examples: Including examples in prompts can significantly enhance the model’s understanding and accuracy. Partial Input Completion: Designing prompts that allow the model to complete partial inputs can lead to more precise and relevant responses. Specific Response Formats: Prompting for responses in specific formats ensures consistency and relevance in the outputs. Contextual Information: Adding context to prompts helps in refining and focusing the model’s responses. Effective Use of Prefixes: Prefixes can guide the model in understanding the kind of response expected. Experimentation: Trying different phrasings, parameter values, and prompt structures can lead to improved outcomes. Iterative Design: Continuous refinement and iteration of prompts are key to achieving optimal responses. Fallback Responses: Planning for fallback responses in case of inadequate or incorrect outputs is essential. Caution with Factual Generation: Be wary of over-reliance on the model for generating factual content, and exercise caution with tasks involving complex logic or mathematics. Conclusion: These strategies, rooted in Google AI’s guidelines, are fundamental in crafting effective prompts that lead to high-quality, reliable AI outputs. For a more detailed exploration of these best practices, visit Google AI’s Prompt Design Strategies.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Towards Artificial Understanding</title><link href="/2023/12/14/towards-au.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Towards Artificial Understanding" /><published>2023-12-14T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-12-14T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/2023/12/14/towards-au</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/12/14/towards-au.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our journey through the technological renaissance, we’ve witnessed the rise and evolution of artificial intelligence (AI). However, a new concept is emerging, poised to redefine our understanding of machine intelligence: and I call it Artificial Understanding (AU). This groundbreaking idea extends the capabilities of AI, pushing it beyond mere data processing and content generation. Today, we explore what Artificial Understanding entails and how it can reshape the landscape of AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/au.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;AU drawn by DALL-E&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-essence-of-artificial-understanding&quot;&gt;The Essence of Artificial &lt;em&gt;Understanding&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Artificial Understanding represents a significant leap in the field of AI. It’s about endowing machines with the ability to not just process but to interpret and comprehend information in a contextually meaningful way. AU takes AI a step further from performing predefined tasks to possessing a level of understanding akin to basic human cognition. This advancement is pivotal as it transforms AI from a tool that follows instructions to an entity that can grasp context, nuances, and the subtleties of the data it processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;point-1-transformers---the-building-blocks-of-understanding&quot;&gt;Point 1: Transformers - The Building Blocks of Understanding&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;understanding-sequences-of-text&quot;&gt;Understanding Sequences of Text&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Central to the concept of AU are transformer models. Unlike conventional algorithms that treat data as isolated points, transformers understand sequences of text, grasping the context and relationships within. This capability is akin to a rudimentary form of understanding, where the model discerns patterns and meanings beyond mere words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;case-studies&quot;&gt;Case Studies&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GPT (Generative Pre-trained Transformer) and BERT (Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers) serve as prime examples of this technology. They demonstrate how transformers can not only generate coherent and contextually relevant text but also interpret and respond to human language with a surprising degree of understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;point-2-efficient-compression-of-knowledge&quot;&gt;Point 2: Efficient Compression of Knowledge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;beyond-generative-capabilities&quot;&gt;Beyond Generative Capabilities&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The true marvel of transformer models, such as GPT or Gemini, lies in their remarkable efficiency in knowledge compression. This efficiency is a critical aspect of Artificial Understanding. These models manage to compress vast amounts of text – potentially equivalent to petabytes of data – into a model of just a few billion (or hundred-million) parameters, which occupies only gigabytes (or less) of space. This is not merely a triumph in data storage but a reflection of how these models distill and encapsulate vast information, enabling them to ‘understand’ and apply this knowledge effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implications-and-future-prospects&quot;&gt;Implications and Future Prospects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The implications of Artificial Understanding are vast and far-reaching. In the realm of customer service, it could lead to chatbots that not only answer queries but understand the emotions and intents behind them. In data analysis, AU could enable systems to not just process numbers but to interpret trends and insights in a contextually rich manner. The potential applications are limitless, stretching across various domains from healthcare, where understanding patient history and symptoms could revolutionize diagnoses, to finance, where understanding market nuances is key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Artificial Understanding is more than just an incremental addition to the AI landscape; it is a paradigm shift. It challenges our preconceptions of machine capabilities, opening doors to possibilities where machines don’t just calculate but comprehend. As we stand at the precipice of this new era in AI, the promise and potential of Artificial Understanding beckon a future where the lines between human and machine understanding become increasingly blurred, leading to innovations we can only begin to imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[This post was created with the assistance of LLMs]&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="futures" /><summary type="html">Introduction: In our journey through the technological renaissance, we’ve witnessed the rise and evolution of artificial intelligence (AI). However, a new concept is emerging, poised to redefine our understanding of machine intelligence: and I call it Artificial Understanding (AU). This groundbreaking idea extends the capabilities of AI, pushing it beyond mere data processing and content generation. Today, we explore what Artificial Understanding entails and how it can reshape the landscape of AI. The Essence of Artificial Understanding Artificial Understanding represents a significant leap in the field of AI. It’s about endowing machines with the ability to not just process but to interpret and comprehend information in a contextually meaningful way. AU takes AI a step further from performing predefined tasks to possessing a level of understanding akin to basic human cognition. This advancement is pivotal as it transforms AI from a tool that follows instructions to an entity that can grasp context, nuances, and the subtleties of the data it processes. Point 1: Transformers - The Building Blocks of Understanding Understanding Sequences of Text Central to the concept of AU are transformer models. Unlike conventional algorithms that treat data as isolated points, transformers understand sequences of text, grasping the context and relationships within. This capability is akin to a rudimentary form of understanding, where the model discerns patterns and meanings beyond mere words. Case Studies GPT (Generative Pre-trained Transformer) and BERT (Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers) serve as prime examples of this technology. They demonstrate how transformers can not only generate coherent and contextually relevant text but also interpret and respond to human language with a surprising degree of understanding. Point 2: Efficient Compression of Knowledge Beyond Generative Capabilities The true marvel of transformer models, such as GPT or Gemini, lies in their remarkable efficiency in knowledge compression. This efficiency is a critical aspect of Artificial Understanding. These models manage to compress vast amounts of text – potentially equivalent to petabytes of data – into a model of just a few billion (or hundred-million) parameters, which occupies only gigabytes (or less) of space. This is not merely a triumph in data storage but a reflection of how these models distill and encapsulate vast information, enabling them to ‘understand’ and apply this knowledge effectively. Implications and Future Prospects The implications of Artificial Understanding are vast and far-reaching. In the realm of customer service, it could lead to chatbots that not only answer queries but understand the emotions and intents behind them. In data analysis, AU could enable systems to not just process numbers but to interpret trends and insights in a contextually rich manner. The potential applications are limitless, stretching across various domains from healthcare, where understanding patient history and symptoms could revolutionize diagnoses, to finance, where understanding market nuances is key. Conclusion Artificial Understanding is more than just an incremental addition to the AI landscape; it is a paradigm shift. It challenges our preconceptions of machine capabilities, opening doors to possibilities where machines don’t just calculate but comprehend. As we stand at the precipice of this new era in AI, the promise and potential of Artificial Understanding beckon a future where the lines between human and machine understanding become increasingly blurred, leading to innovations we can only begin to imagine. [This post was created with the assistance of LLMs]</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Evaluating Hallucination - A danger of LLMs</title><link href="/2023/11/29/evaluating-hallucination.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evaluating Hallucination - A danger of LLMs" /><published>2023-11-29T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-29T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/2023/11/29/evaluating-hallucination</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/11/29/evaluating-hallucination.html">&lt;p&gt;I just read a very interesting paper on Arxiv titled “The impact of using an AI chatbot to respond to patient messages.” where an evaluation of human-chat versus GPT-chat was done, measuring effectiveness, efficiency, and the potential danger of hallucination. YOu can see the paper [here] (https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.17703)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The integration of Artificial Intelligence (AI) into healthcare is a rapidly evolving frontier, promising to revolutionize patient care and clinician workflow. A recent study published on arXiv.org delves into this topic, exploring the effects of using an AI chatbot, specifically GPT-4, for responding to patient messages in a healthcare setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ai-med.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;AI in Medicine&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;overview-of-the-study&quot;&gt;Overview of the Study&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study aimed to assess the acceptability, safety, and efficiency of using an AI-based chatbot in drafting responses to patient queries. Conducted at Brigham and Women’s Hospital, Boston, in 2023, it involved six board-certified oncologists who responded to 100 realistic cancer patient scenarios. The study was designed in two stages, where in the first stage, oncologists manually responded to patient messages, and in the second stage, they edited responses generated by GPT-4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-findings&quot;&gt;Key Findings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results were significant:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Efficiency Improvement&lt;/strong&gt;: In 77% of cases, the use of GPT-4 improved documentation efficiency.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Safety&lt;/strong&gt;: 82% of the time, the AI-generated responses were considered safe.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk of Harm&lt;/strong&gt;: However, there was a 7.7% chance that unedited GPT-4 responses could lead to severe harm or death.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;physician-perception-of-ai-responses&quot;&gt;Physician Perception of AI Responses&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, in 31% of cases, physicians believed the GPT-4 drafts were written by humans. This perception highlights the sophistication of AI-generated responses but also underscores the necessity for careful review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impact-on-patient-education-and-clinical-actions&quot;&gt;Impact on Patient Education and Clinical Actions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of AI led to an increase in patient education recommendations but a decrease in direct clinical actions. This shift suggests that while AI can enhance informational support, it might underrepresent the need for immediate clinical interventions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;risks-and-challenges&quot;&gt;Risks and Challenges&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the benefits, the study highlights critical risks associated with AI in healthcare:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Potential for severe harm in a small but significant percentage of responses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The need for diligent oversight and human intervention to ensure patient safety.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;future-implications&quot;&gt;Future Implications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study opens up a discussion about the future role of AI in healthcare communication. While AI shows promise in reducing clinician workload and enhancing patient education, its impact on clinical decision-making and the potential risks involved require ongoing scrutiny and responsible implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, this study on using AI chatbots for patient communication reveals a complex balance. While AI can significantly enhance efficiency and patient education, it introduces risks that necessitate vigilant oversight. The future of AI in healthcare holds great promise but demands a cautious and well-informed approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chen, S., et al. (2023). The impact of using an AI chatbot to respond to patient messages. arXiv.org. &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.17703&quot;&gt;arXiv:2310.17703&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please note that this blog post is a summary and interpretation of the study and does not cover all aspects of the research. For a comprehensive understanding, readers are encouraged to refer to the original paper.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note: This post was written with the assistance of Large Language Models&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="regulation" /><summary type="html">I just read a very interesting paper on Arxiv titled “The impact of using an AI chatbot to respond to patient messages.” where an evaluation of human-chat versus GPT-chat was done, measuring effectiveness, efficiency, and the potential danger of hallucination. YOu can see the paper [here] (https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.17703) Introduction The integration of Artificial Intelligence (AI) into healthcare is a rapidly evolving frontier, promising to revolutionize patient care and clinician workflow. A recent study published on arXiv.org delves into this topic, exploring the effects of using an AI chatbot, specifically GPT-4, for responding to patient messages in a healthcare setting. Overview of the Study This study aimed to assess the acceptability, safety, and efficiency of using an AI-based chatbot in drafting responses to patient queries. Conducted at Brigham and Women’s Hospital, Boston, in 2023, it involved six board-certified oncologists who responded to 100 realistic cancer patient scenarios. The study was designed in two stages, where in the first stage, oncologists manually responded to patient messages, and in the second stage, they edited responses generated by GPT-4. Key Findings The results were significant: Efficiency Improvement: In 77% of cases, the use of GPT-4 improved documentation efficiency. Safety: 82% of the time, the AI-generated responses were considered safe. Risk of Harm: However, there was a 7.7% chance that unedited GPT-4 responses could lead to severe harm or death. Physician Perception of AI Responses Interestingly, in 31% of cases, physicians believed the GPT-4 drafts were written by humans. This perception highlights the sophistication of AI-generated responses but also underscores the necessity for careful review. Impact on Patient Education and Clinical Actions The use of AI led to an increase in patient education recommendations but a decrease in direct clinical actions. This shift suggests that while AI can enhance informational support, it might underrepresent the need for immediate clinical interventions. Risks and Challenges Despite the benefits, the study highlights critical risks associated with AI in healthcare: Potential for severe harm in a small but significant percentage of responses. The need for diligent oversight and human intervention to ensure patient safety. Future Implications The study opens up a discussion about the future role of AI in healthcare communication. While AI shows promise in reducing clinician workload and enhancing patient education, its impact on clinical decision-making and the potential risks involved require ongoing scrutiny and responsible implementation. Conclusion In conclusion, this study on using AI chatbots for patient communication reveals a complex balance. While AI can significantly enhance efficiency and patient education, it introduces risks that necessitate vigilant oversight. The future of AI in healthcare holds great promise but demands a cautious and well-informed approach. References Chen, S., et al. (2023). The impact of using an AI chatbot to respond to patient messages. arXiv.org. arXiv:2310.17703 Please note that this blog post is a summary and interpretation of the study and does not cover all aspects of the research. For a comprehensive understanding, readers are encouraged to refer to the original paper. Note: This post was written with the assistance of Large Language Models</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Navigating the AI Landscape - The Need for Expert-Led Regulation</title><link href="/2023/11/10/ai-regulation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Navigating the AI Landscape - The Need for Expert-Led Regulation" /><published>2023-11-10T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-10T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>/2023/11/10/ai-regulation</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/11/10/ai-regulation.html">&lt;p&gt;In recent years, artificial intelligence (AI) has leaped from science fiction into our daily lives, bringing both incredible potential and significant challenges. As AI continues to evolve and integrate into various sectors, the question of regulation becomes increasingly pressing. However, the key to effective AI regulation lies not in reactive policies driven by fear and misunderstanding, but in informed, expert-led approaches that understand the nuances of AI technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ai-regulation.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Regulation and Expertise&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;understanding-the-fear-and-the-reality&quot;&gt;Understanding the Fear and the Reality&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI, much like any transformative technology, has been met with its share of public apprehension. Stories of AI going rogue or replacing human jobs have fueled a narrative that often strays from reality. It is crucial to distinguish between irrational fears, often amplified by sensationalist media, and legitimate concerns regarding privacy, security, and ethical use of AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-role-of-experts-in-ai-regulation&quot;&gt;The Role of Experts in AI Regulation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effective AI regulation requires a deep understanding of the technology’s capabilities, limitations, and impact across various domains. This level of insight is typically beyond the scope of political expertise. AI experts, including scientists, ethicists, and technologists, are better equipped to foresee the implications of restricting AI development and use. They can provide balanced views that consider both the potential risks and the immense benefits AI offers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;balancing-innovation-and-safety&quot;&gt;Balancing Innovation and Safety&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of regulation should be to mitigate risks without stifling innovation. Overly restrictive regulations, born from misunderstandings or fear, could hinder the advancement of AI technologies that have the potential to solve some of our most pressing global challenges. Experts can help draft regulations that ensure safety and ethical practices while still encouraging innovation and research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;collaborative-approach-for-holistic-regulation&quot;&gt;Collaborative Approach for Holistic Regulation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regulation should not be a unilateral process dictated by a single group. A collaborative approach, involving AI experts, policymakers, industry leaders, and the public, is essential. Such collaboration can ensure that regulations are practical, well-informed, and considerate of diverse perspectives and societal needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;looking-forward&quot;&gt;Looking Forward&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As AI becomes increasingly integrated into our world, the need for thoughtful, informed regulation becomes more apparent. Entrusting this task to those who understand the intricate workings and potential of AI is not just prudent; it is &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; to harness the full potential of AI technologies while safeguarding societal values and human welfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regulating AI should be a forward-looking endeavor, not a reactionary one. By leaning on the expertise of those who best understand the technology, we can create a regulatory framework that balances innovation with responsibility, ensuring that AI serves as a tool for human progress, not a subject of unfounded fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note: This post was written with the assistance of Large Language Models&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="regulation" /><summary type="html">In recent years, artificial intelligence (AI) has leaped from science fiction into our daily lives, bringing both incredible potential and significant challenges. As AI continues to evolve and integrate into various sectors, the question of regulation becomes increasingly pressing. However, the key to effective AI regulation lies not in reactive policies driven by fear and misunderstanding, but in informed, expert-led approaches that understand the nuances of AI technology. Understanding the Fear and the Reality AI, much like any transformative technology, has been met with its share of public apprehension. Stories of AI going rogue or replacing human jobs have fueled a narrative that often strays from reality. It is crucial to distinguish between irrational fears, often amplified by sensationalist media, and legitimate concerns regarding privacy, security, and ethical use of AI. The Role of Experts in AI Regulation Effective AI regulation requires a deep understanding of the technology’s capabilities, limitations, and impact across various domains. This level of insight is typically beyond the scope of political expertise. AI experts, including scientists, ethicists, and technologists, are better equipped to foresee the implications of restricting AI development and use. They can provide balanced views that consider both the potential risks and the immense benefits AI offers. Balancing Innovation and Safety The goal of regulation should be to mitigate risks without stifling innovation. Overly restrictive regulations, born from misunderstandings or fear, could hinder the advancement of AI technologies that have the potential to solve some of our most pressing global challenges. Experts can help draft regulations that ensure safety and ethical practices while still encouraging innovation and research. Collaborative Approach for Holistic Regulation Regulation should not be a unilateral process dictated by a single group. A collaborative approach, involving AI experts, policymakers, industry leaders, and the public, is essential. Such collaboration can ensure that regulations are practical, well-informed, and considerate of diverse perspectives and societal needs. Looking Forward As AI becomes increasingly integrated into our world, the need for thoughtful, informed regulation becomes more apparent. Entrusting this task to those who understand the intricate workings and potential of AI is not just prudent; it is necessary to harness the full potential of AI technologies while safeguarding societal values and human welfare. Regulating AI should be a forward-looking endeavor, not a reactionary one. By leaning on the expertise of those who best understand the technology, we can create a regulatory framework that balances innovation with responsibility, ensuring that AI serves as a tool for human progress, not a subject of unfounded fear. Note: This post was written with the assistance of Large Language Models</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Beatles Now and Then - made possible by AI</title><link href="/2023/11/02/nowandthen.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Beatles Now and Then - made possible by AI" /><published>2023-11-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-11-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2023/11/02/nowandthen</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/11/02/nowandthen.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-final-beatles-song&quot;&gt;The Final Beatles Song&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now and then is a beautiful song, and it will be the last song from the Beatles. Made possible by AI extracting audio of old recording sessions to access content such as John Lennon’s voice, it’s an epic and beautiful recording.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s particularly poignant when you listen to the lyrics “Now and then, I miss you, I want you to be there for me”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work on the track started in February 1995 as part of the Beatles anthology project, but it had to halt because of the technological challenges in extracting John’s voice from a tape recording from 20 years earlier. It looked like it wouldn’t be possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, enter Peter Jackson, of ‘Lord of the Rings’ fame, who figured out how to uncouple John’s vocal from background sound. It’s musical archaeology in action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s a beautiful and fitting song!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen to it here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/AW55J2zE3N4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="coding" /><summary type="html">The Final Beatles Song Now and then is a beautiful song, and it will be the last song from the Beatles. Made possible by AI extracting audio of old recording sessions to access content such as John Lennon’s voice, it’s an epic and beautiful recording. And it’s particularly poignant when you listen to the lyrics “Now and then, I miss you, I want you to be there for me” Work on the track started in February 1995 as part of the Beatles anthology project, but it had to halt because of the technological challenges in extracting John’s voice from a tape recording from 20 years earlier. It looked like it wouldn’t be possible. Then, enter Peter Jackson, of ‘Lord of the Rings’ fame, who figured out how to uncouple John’s vocal from background sound. It’s musical archaeology in action. And it’s a beautiful and fitting song! Listen to it here:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AI-phobia and the damage it can bring</title><link href="/2023/09/03/nofear.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI-phobia and the damage it can bring" /><published>2023-09-03T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-09-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2023/09/03/nofear</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/09/03/nofear.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;ai-where-the-only-thing-to-fear-is-fear-itself&quot;&gt;AI: Where the Only Thing to Fear is Fear Itself&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In today’s world, the majority of headlines I see around Artificial Intelligence (AI) skew negative. Fueled by decades of science fiction projecting AI to be a future antagonist, and present day attention-grabbing headlines, many view AI as the ominous cloud on the horizon of human evolution. As something that will overtake us, and having done so, will then wipe us out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sentiment brings to mind the profound words of Franklin D. Roosevelt: “The only thing we have to fear is fear itself.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-birth-of-fear&quot;&gt;The Birth of Fear&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the work done in AI is a major and encouraging pinnacle of human ingenuity, representing our innate desire to break barriers and redefine the possible. With it, we have been able to break through computational barriers, building applications the likes of which were previously thought impossible. And we’re only getting started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, like any revolutionary advancement, the right hand of power can bring the left hand of darkness, in this case, that of uncertainty and apprehension. But is this fear rooted in the technology itself or our misunderstanding of it? I argue the latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Movies, novels, and popular culture have, for decades, painted AI as the unstoppable force that will eventually surpass human intelligence, casting a shadow over our dominion. These depictions are, of course, tailored for entertainment, emphasizing conflict and drama over factual representation. Yet, the impact of these narratives on public perception is undeniable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But one thing stands clear. Intelligence alone is not enough, be it artificial or biological. A living, conscious, sentient entity, capable of making value judgements – for good or evil – is a lot more than just an intelligence. Yet the column inches of fear focus entirely on the ‘I’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take Bostrom’s famous &lt;a href=&quot;https://cepr.org/voxeu/columns/ai-and-paperclip-problem#:~:text=Bostrom's%20thought%20experiment%20goes%20like,to%20achieve%20its%20goal%20better.&quot;&gt;paper clip thought experiment&lt;/a&gt; In this, an AI is tasked with making paperclips, and, given that it can learn how to make better paperclips, it will eventually realize that all of humanity’s resources are effectively wasted if they’re not being used to make paperclips, and it will run away, and destroy humanity in an apocalypse of paperclips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/clip-fun.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Clippy making a joke&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fallacy here, of course, is that in the discussion of the &lt;em&gt;possible&lt;/em&gt;, we’re ignoring the &lt;em&gt;probable&lt;/em&gt;, and the largest factor determining probability of this outcome would be giving this paper clip generator access to the resources that would allow it to destroy humanity. Maybe it could evolve a level of intelligence that would allow it to theorize a methodology to ‘break out’ of its thought experiment confines, but does that give it the ability to do so? And, when creating any kind of artificial intelligence, the model, while very sophisticated is usually very limited. It has a one-tracked mind, if you will, and this experiment pre-supposes that it can evolve beyond that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The narrative is overtaken by fear of the possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ai-as-a-mirror&quot;&gt;AI as a Mirror&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s essential to understand that AI, at its core, is neutral. It’s a tool, an extension of our collective knowledge. AI doesn’t have emotions, ambitions, or ulterior motives. It operates on data, algorithms, and the instructions we feed it. In many ways, AI is a mirror, reflecting both the biases of its creators and the vast potential of its applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps our fear of AI comes from the fact that we’re looking in that mirror and seeing what is terrifying in ourselves? Perhaps this is a great wakeup call for us as a species to recognize that which in ourselves is dangerous, and do something about it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I also think of historic mistakes made by our species. Today, AI is that great, feared, unknown. But that wasn’t always the case, was it? Modern day racism is rooted in the same ‘othering’ of outsiders. We made many mistakes, treating (or more accurately &lt;em&gt;mis&lt;/em&gt;treating) others outside our known civilizations as savages, less than human, something to be feared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we all continue to pay the price for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe this is an opportunity not to repeat that mistake. What if, some years from now, AI becomes AL – Artificial Life. Wouldn’t it be nice to be ready to be in a position where we can understand and treat with each other with mutual respect?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-real-challenge&quot;&gt;The Real Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to today, the actual challenge lies not in the technology but in its application. A well-programmed application that uses AI can help doctors diagnose diseases, assist students in learning, or predict weather patterns with astonishing accuracy. Conversely, an poorly built one can reinforce societal prejudices, make unfair decisions, or invade privacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This dichotomy means that our real focus should be on ensuring that our work should be to develop and grow AI and ML responsibly. One underlooked aspect of respobnsible development is in mitigating fear. When allowed to dominate the narrative, fear stunts critical thinking. It can halt progress and can keep us from harnessing the transformative power of AI for the greater good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-path-forward&quot;&gt;The Path Forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of getting wrapped up in a cycle of fear and misinformation, we need to channel our collective energies towards education, open dialogue, and understanding. Collaborative efforts between tech developers, ethicists, policymakers, and the public can ensure that AI’s development remains aligned with humanity’s best interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Embracing the future means embracing AI, but with open eyes, clear minds, and fearless hearts. We stand at the cusp of a technological renaissance, and our approach will determine the legacy of this era. As we move forward, let’s remember that the most significant achievements in history were born from hope and understanding, not from fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note: I used LLMs to help me create this post. They helped me hone my thoughts and sharpen my argument. They did not replace me as a writer, nor did they drive my opinion)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Laurence Moroney</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="coding" /><summary type="html">AI: Where the Only Thing to Fear is Fear Itself In today’s world, the majority of headlines I see around Artificial Intelligence (AI) skew negative. Fueled by decades of science fiction projecting AI to be a future antagonist, and present day attention-grabbing headlines, many view AI as the ominous cloud on the horizon of human evolution. As something that will overtake us, and having done so, will then wipe us out. This sentiment brings to mind the profound words of Franklin D. Roosevelt: “The only thing we have to fear is fear itself.” The Birth of Fear Much of the work done in AI is a major and encouraging pinnacle of human ingenuity, representing our innate desire to break barriers and redefine the possible. With it, we have been able to break through computational barriers, building applications the likes of which were previously thought impossible. And we’re only getting started. Yet, like any revolutionary advancement, the right hand of power can bring the left hand of darkness, in this case, that of uncertainty and apprehension. But is this fear rooted in the technology itself or our misunderstanding of it? I argue the latter. Movies, novels, and popular culture have, for decades, painted AI as the unstoppable force that will eventually surpass human intelligence, casting a shadow over our dominion. These depictions are, of course, tailored for entertainment, emphasizing conflict and drama over factual representation. Yet, the impact of these narratives on public perception is undeniable. But one thing stands clear. Intelligence alone is not enough, be it artificial or biological. A living, conscious, sentient entity, capable of making value judgements – for good or evil – is a lot more than just an intelligence. Yet the column inches of fear focus entirely on the ‘I’ Take Bostrom’s famous paper clip thought experiment In this, an AI is tasked with making paperclips, and, given that it can learn how to make better paperclips, it will eventually realize that all of humanity’s resources are effectively wasted if they’re not being used to make paperclips, and it will run away, and destroy humanity in an apocalypse of paperclips. The fallacy here, of course, is that in the discussion of the possible, we’re ignoring the probable, and the largest factor determining probability of this outcome would be giving this paper clip generator access to the resources that would allow it to destroy humanity. Maybe it could evolve a level of intelligence that would allow it to theorize a methodology to ‘break out’ of its thought experiment confines, but does that give it the ability to do so? And, when creating any kind of artificial intelligence, the model, while very sophisticated is usually very limited. It has a one-tracked mind, if you will, and this experiment pre-supposes that it can evolve beyond that. The narrative is overtaken by fear of the possible. AI as a Mirror It’s essential to understand that AI, at its core, is neutral. It’s a tool, an extension of our collective knowledge. AI doesn’t have emotions, ambitions, or ulterior motives. It operates on data, algorithms, and the instructions we feed it. In many ways, AI is a mirror, reflecting both the biases of its creators and the vast potential of its applications. Perhaps our fear of AI comes from the fact that we’re looking in that mirror and seeing what is terrifying in ourselves? Perhaps this is a great wakeup call for us as a species to recognize that which in ourselves is dangerous, and do something about it? Finally, I also think of historic mistakes made by our species. Today, AI is that great, feared, unknown. But that wasn’t always the case, was it? Modern day racism is rooted in the same ‘othering’ of outsiders. We made many mistakes, treating (or more accurately mistreating) others outside our known civilizations as savages, less than human, something to be feared. And we all continue to pay the price for that. Maybe this is an opportunity not to repeat that mistake. What if, some years from now, AI becomes AL – Artificial Life. Wouldn’t it be nice to be ready to be in a position where we can understand and treat with each other with mutual respect? The Real Challenge Back to today, the actual challenge lies not in the technology but in its application. A well-programmed application that uses AI can help doctors diagnose diseases, assist students in learning, or predict weather patterns with astonishing accuracy. Conversely, an poorly built one can reinforce societal prejudices, make unfair decisions, or invade privacy. This dichotomy means that our real focus should be on ensuring that our work should be to develop and grow AI and ML responsibly. One underlooked aspect of respobnsible development is in mitigating fear. When allowed to dominate the narrative, fear stunts critical thinking. It can halt progress and can keep us from harnessing the transformative power of AI for the greater good. The Path Forward Instead of getting wrapped up in a cycle of fear and misinformation, we need to channel our collective energies towards education, open dialogue, and understanding. Collaborative efforts between tech developers, ethicists, policymakers, and the public can ensure that AI’s development remains aligned with humanity’s best interests. Embracing the future means embracing AI, but with open eyes, clear minds, and fearless hearts. We stand at the cusp of a technological renaissance, and our approach will determine the legacy of this era. As we move forward, let’s remember that the most significant achievements in history were born from hope and understanding, not from fear. (Note: I used LLMs to help me create this post. They helped me hone my thoughts and sharpen my argument. They did not replace me as a writer, nor did they drive my opinion)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/roadway.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/roadway.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>